You mentioned me Hoover.
Can can we have the
screen?
Hello? Can anybody hear me?
Hi, Yucca. How are you?
Yeah. I'm fine.
Thank you. Can you hear and see me?
Yes. We can see you. Maybe can
you share your screen?
Oh, I'm not going to share anything. I don't have
any slides. I'm just going to speak freely.
Okay. Okay. Would you mind me to introduce
you or introduce or you introduce
yourself?
Well, I can introduce myself. My name is
Jorgen, and I'm interested in AI.
Okay. You can go on.
Like, start your talk. Now.
And, well, all know that,
you are the pioneer of, artificial
intelligence, and you are always forehead
of everything. And we are
looking forward for your talk today.
And, everything everyone is excited
in the room to for
your talk. You can start.
That's very kind of you to say that, Thank
you so much. Hello in the audience.
I cannot see you. But I
hope, we will have
quite an audience, today
It will be about world models and
about a particular kind of world
model that is exploiting the latence
space, to solve problems.
Now these wild models, they go
back. I like to
say they go back to the ancient Greeks
and, Plato,
he already suggested that we,
recognize objects by
collecting internal
blue blueprints or or templates
and then,
the idea is that, and that is
what, his successor, I totally
erode, that mental images
allow humans to imagine the future and to
plan action sequences,
by mentally manipulating images
in the absence of the actual,
objects. Now,
that is old stuff from
2,300 years ago, and more recently,
people have started to look at
artificial neural networks as world
models. And, and,
first, pioneer in work along these lines was
done in the eighties, by Paul
Wuerbauer. He had a paper in 1987
and then another one in 1989
where he basically talked about two artificial
neural networks. One is,
a a controller, which, sees
inputs from the environment and then there are
actions, and now the other one is,
a network that does, what he calls
system identification. Why did
he call it system identification? Because
people in control theory had called
it system identification for a
long time, and this model is just
predicting what's going to happen as a consequence
of the action. That is emitted
by the controller, and then you have the wire model
as it is called now, and the
back propagation procedure can be
used to come up with,
with, good gradients
for the controller such that the output actions of
the controller lead to
high predicted reward
of, somewhere
where the model of the model predicts the reward.
So, 1987, Paul
Wroe was and then Paul Munoz in 1987
had something very similar. And,
and other people follow it. And in 1990,
I was dissatisfied with,
with the current state of the
of these, of these
world models? I I I call
them world model.
And to to represent
or to stand for
general purpose, controllers and general,
purpose prediction
machines that work not only in
in,
in fully
observable environments,
That's good enough for, that's what
feat four neural networks are good enough for.
But also in partially observable
environments. And that's where you need
something like a return network or a
similar memory based system
And then, the
the the
important thing. One of the important thing was
really that the network, it's
itself, the controller itself,
as, as an
input, sees the
reward signals. It
doesn't just wants to it doesn't
just want to maximize the reward, No. It
wants to observe the reward and
then somehow learn as
strategy to translate these observed reward
signals in into
better actions, that lead
to more rewards.
And this is also essential
for meta learning. So suppose
the the controller is a
powerful computer that, in principle,
can learn to improve its
own learning algorithm. To do that, it
must see the evaluation
signals that are coming out from the that
are coming in from the out outside,
from the world that is changing through the actions
of the controller, and so you
want to give it access to the
error signals that
that the wilders
deducing,
from the actions of,
of the controller. And you want to
give, the controller an input
that represents all the pain sensors
and our robots have pain sensors, and they
have not only one reward signal, no. They
have very informative,
multitudes of pain sensors such that the robot
knows. Which exactly
is the weak point that I'm currently
running into as my,
body is moving into an obstacle and
it's hurting at certain parts of my
body body, but not at,
but other parts are not hurting. And so
you you want to give the error signals and
the reward signals as an input, and
the outputs, you want to feed into
the, model network, into the
VAD model, as I called it back then, the
previous authors, who did some
systems like that with feeds forward networks,
I didn't call them, wild models. So you want
to feed that into the the
wild model and then make certain predictions
about future inputs of the
controller, which, include the reward signals,
but also the neutral signals
that you get from the video and from the the audio and from
tactile sensors and so on.
And then, of course, back then, immediately,
the question came up in 1990.
The beginning, the world model is really stupid,
and it doesn't know anything about the world. So
what can the controller do
to create a better world model?
And it's clear the controller has to become
something like a little scientist, which
generates, actions
that lead to additional data from the
environment such that
the wild model can learn something that it
didn't know And back then, the
stupid idea was really just
okay. Let's look at the prediction
error of the WAN model,
and, it's trying to minimize that.
The one model is trying to,
adjust its connection weights so that it becomes
a better predictor. Trying to minimize
the mean squared error, and,
and doing basically the same thing that
Gauguin did two hundred twenty
ago when they had the first, artificial
neural networks, which were not
neural networks back then, but they were called linear
regression. And in the nineties,
this was called, linear neural
networks. So 02/2020 year
old, sir. So you just minimize
the the the
prediction error. However,
at the same time, the controller
needs an incentive to come up with action
sequences or experiments that lead
to to
surprises for the predict machine, for the wall model.
And so we
we let the controller maximize
the same error and that the model
is minimizing, which means that
whenever the model starts
getting really good at predicting,
aspects of the environment
then the controller gets bored.
Because there's no additional reward
coming from that behavior. So it wants
to invent a new,
action sequence that leads that leads to
another part of the environment so that it can still
learn something that it didn't know. And,
there was basically a mini max
game. Where two guys were fighting each
other, and the controller had,
controller had these these,
Gaussian units hidden
units. The Gaussian hidden units, they
had, a mean and a variance that
could be adapted through gradient descent.
And that's how the control learn to become a better
generator of experiments, of
action sequences. And, today,
they call that, generative and
adversarial network.
I just called it artificial curiosity.
Now, of course,
what we did back then was, in many
ways, very limited because,
what you really want to do what you
really want to do is, you
you you don't want to
to plan future action sequences
in the milli by millisecond
fashion that I had back then in 1990,
where you where you just,
do mental simulations of
possible action sequences in your
your wall model, and then,
you pick one of those action sequences
that lead to a lot of reward, a lot of
predicted reward. So you do these mental
rollouts of the future, and you pick a future
that is promising.
And, if it turns out to be,
if it turns out to be now here it says my
Internet connection is unstained. Unstable. Can
you still hear me?
You still hear me?
Is anybody still there?
There are many people still here. Can you still
Can you still hear me?
Yeah. Yeah. We can hear you.
Alright. Excellent. Good. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
So so
what what you really want to do
is not millisecond by millisecond planning. No. You
want to do something more sophisticated,
And, and one way
of, doing something a little bit more sophisticated
not what you really want to do, but something
that is cool in some ways.
That's what we did a couple of years later.
Where we said, okay, let's not predict
every single pixel
or something like that. Instead, let's predict,
abstract representations, RC inputs,
such that these abstract representations
internal representations of what's coming in from
the outside, such that they
are, you know, you know, such that they lose
information, but are
still informative. And,
and such that you then learn
to create internal representations
lose some of the information about the input
but such that they are
still predictable, and
still carry as much information about,
the input as as possible.
So, certainly, we say, okay. Now
the the prediction,
error
is not going to be minimized only by the predictor,
No. It's also going to be minimized by the
guy who is creating the internal representations,
such that the internal representations become
more predictable on. And,
thirty years later, another guy called
that what a one of
JPAR, joined Embedding Prediction
architecture, but it's exactly the same old thing.
And, and what we did back then,
we had two terms. One is for, you
know, for
encoding the, the input
in a way that that allows
you to,
that allow us this system to convey
information about the input. So some sort of
information conserving error term,
and, I think it was called DL
or d one or d two back then in this
1992 paper about discovering
predictable classifications.
With Daniel Prelinger, my student, who did the experiments.
And then, you you have
the other network, which is just trying to predict
the, internal representations, but at
the same time, the internal representations become
more predictable, and then you
have two types of errors that you want to minimize. One
is the prediction error, and the other
one is this, information
preserving
a term that that
wants to preserve as much as you can about
the input. So you don't have what
people now call it collapse. Especially
you don't get something that is super predictable but
doesn't tell you anything about the
about the current input that you are predicting.
And so, all of that
was, was, tested in lots
of little experiments, Back then, of course,
compute was about 1,000,000 times
more expensive than today.
And, we didn't call that j p
a or or or something like
that. No. We called it predictability and
maximization. And,
and, it's it's one
interesting way of coming
up with abstract representations of
the of the I'll
see.
Complex inputs that you get from the world.
And if you generalize to recurrent networks,
then you you get absolute representations of
complex spatial
temporal event sequences,
that are then predictable.
And then we had a whole bunch
of applications
of that. And, recently,
it turned out that,
I technique called build
your own latent. Build your
own latent by,
Michael Valko's, team
is closely related to that.
And, Michael Walco basically
had still
this prediction error that he wanted to, minimize,
but then he removed this deal
term that was
the
internal representations to be predicted,
making them informative. And then
he had a bunch of tricks to to,
still make this work. And this was called
BYOL, build your own latent.
And, and,
he pointed out, that it was
actually this, 20,
build your own latent paper, which,
first made the p max
so the predictability maximization skeleton
work at scale
on the image net. Dataset.
That was, you know, thirty years
after, we did our little thing with
computers that were a million times slower
than that. And, and then,
the
this this the traits
that he had there. He had a toolkit, a collapse prevention
toolkit, that was,
introduced to survive the old terms that
we had in the 1992 Pmax
and then, that was later
adopted in, in, various
variants of what was called JPAR,
like I JPAR and v JPAR. And,
the cool thing, the punchline is that that
Michael Valco pointed out
in 2025,
there was, paper called Le
JAPAN Le JAPAN, and,
it dropped, all these tracks entirely
and went back to this explicit
anti collapse, regularizer
that we had back then in 1992.
So that's a full circle return to
the original 1992
predictability maximization philosophy
of explicit information maximization
terms. So even within
the this lineage,
the the p max JPAR line
lineage, as Michael Larko pointed
out, we we had a trajectory
that goes from the explicit,
DL terms in 1992,
to build your own
latence implicit architectural tricks
in 2020, and then
Lacun's JPAR are using
build your own lightning tracks, 2023,
2024. And then
back to explicit DL and
and and let's say, So
the the field spent five years exploring
the the regime opened
up by, build your own latent
and then came home to, the
original smaller than one
design of the predictability
maximization paper from 1992. So
it's it's not just the case that
j per is exactly p max. It's even
the detour away from explicit
DL even eventually led back to
the origins of Pmax
that's kind of cool. And, and
then however,
as I always point it out,
j per or p max,
like, things aren't really
aren't really
very promising paths to
to AGI or something like that. No. It's just, you
know, it's a a little technique
to make,
internal representations that are predictable,
in the sense that they are not as informative
as the raw pixels. But still
tell you something about the pixels and on
abstract representation of the pixels that,
that that is re predictable.
I think what you really should do is
not that. I think what you really should
do is you still should try to predict
everything. You should look at the holy
data, the holy data that you get
over your lifetime and you have
one single lifetime, you have one single
trial in your life. And that's where you want to
maximize your reward. And there,
you want to exploit
the fact that there's a lot of, algorithmic
information in the in the
in the neutral data, in the vision,
the video data that is coming in, and
then the audio data, which has
not much to do with the reinforcement learning
signals, which you really want to maximize,
but you can learn so much from
these extra from these highly
from these high dimensional data, from the
from the vision and from the audio, you can
learn so much about how the world works.
And that it's a three-dimensional world, and that
it has gravity, and you can
learn all that by predicting every little pixel.
Now, of course, there are things that want that you cannot
predict, but you don't care. Because,
as you're predicting as you're trying to predict
everything, and in advance,
you don't know what is predictable and what's not, as
you're trying to predict everything, you
will get all kinds of internal,
representations that are really good
at predicting well, maybe not the details
of what's happening, but you
know, predicting expected values
of, of individual pixels
predicting essentially probability distributions
over these possibly bands. So you can have that.
And these internal representations,
they can be very sophisticated. Because
if you want to predict this pixel here,
maybe you can't predict it only if you memorize
something that happened a thousand steps ago.
And, you know, a a good learning algorithm,
model a wild model learning algorithm is going
to figure that out over time.
Through gradient descent or more
sophisticated ways of doing it. So
there you have then,
still the if you're all stupid, objective,
of, of minimizing your prediction
error, but
you don't do the stupid thing. The stupid thing
would be now to simulate the
world using this world model, and
then step by step simulate it. No.
What you really want to do is you you
want to take all the information that is
now contained in this wild
model and, and some of
it refers to predictable islands
islands of predictability, and other
things refer to you know,
random stuff, that is
hardly predict and whatever,
But what you can do now
is you can do something more sophisticated.
You can say, okay. The controller, which is
exploiting the wild model to come up with better
action sequences, the controller
has to learn to become a
prompt engineer
which sends prompt sequences,
sequences of
number vectors, basically,
into the world model.
And somehow, in this way,
address internal representations
that the world model has learned,
on its, on its often
difficult path towards predicting
everything, it cannot predict everything, but it will have
lots of, cool internal representations.
So the the controller wants to address
these internal representations, and
then something will come back, from
the model to the
controller which is supposed to solve
our task, maximizing reward
or something like that, and
and something will come back. And the connectors
that can send
information into the hidden units of the
one model and the connections are
coming back from the world model and
back to the controller such that the controller can
somehow use the information that
comes back as a reaction
to its own prompts that it sent in.
So it it sends in
questions and back, the answers.
These connections all belong to the controller.
Now the controller
has to learn over time to become a better product
engineer. Who sends in better
questions and, and
learns to better interpret whatever comes back.
And the ASR test is on, or is does
does the controller learn a new
task faster
from scratch by ignoring the
one model? Or is it easier
for the controller to know, send a couple
of cranks into the wild model?
And and the crumbs are in a self invented language.
They are not in in English or something,
and something comes back, and then you,
you can use the algorithmic information
that, is coming back and you
over time, as you're doing that many
times again and again and again,
you will get a at that last
to better address the important part
of, world model given the current
context, given the current task that it wants to solve, and
then use the information that's going
back to maybe edit a
few, bits of the behavior
of the policy that it's executing and
then profit from this
algorithmic information that's in the
in the in the world
world model. So that's a
much better way
of exploiting in arbitrary computable
ways all this information that is
hidden in the hidden units and the internal
representations that the wall model
has created in response to
the raw data, through the holy
to to the the holy data, which contains
all the information that you
can ever know about the world. The only
thing that you can ever know about the world is
the raw data, and, you shouldn't
throw any of the raw data away.
If your storage is big enough to store everything,
don't throw any of it away. Once I calculate
it to the human brain, has about,
well, if you if you assume that it has maybe
four bits or five bits of,
information per synapse, then it
has enough internal storage
to store a human lifetime at higher
resolution. So if
you have enough storage, don't
throw any of the data away. The data's holy.
But on top of the raw data, which
costs you a lot, so costs a lot,
cost a lot of storage, there is this
more interesting, this tiny little,
algorithm, which somehow
just extracts patterns
and regularities from the raw data
and that's what you're really, interested in
as you're trying to solve new problems.
So the the raw data helps you just
to extract,
certain raw, certain
regularities and compressibilities
and you you want to discover new,
patterns of this kind where you can
compress the entire data
in a way that is better than what
you had so far, and then
the controller wants to
take this high level data and,
and address it through prompts,
through algorithms that learn to address the
important parts of the hidden units
and ignore the unimportant parts.
And this was what the 2015,
paper was about, learning to think and
to think. And apparently and apparently,
there's a pretty famous tweet, about that.
Apparently, this is what, Deepseak used
in 2025, something quite
like it, to to to
to strip,
1,000 billion dollars off
the stock market.
Anyway, so,
on the one hand, we have, systems
that, like, like, predictable
maximization, now sometimes
called JPaa, but it's p max is
the old Pmax of nineteen eight two,
to extract, abstract, representation
data points of images and whatever,
On the other hand, we have a system
the 2015 system on on
wild models that are not being
used for millisecond by millisecond second planning
through rollouts, which is not where you wanna do it.
This is super expensive, but you don't wanna
do that. Now
for world models that become the target
of prompt engineers, and the control is a prompt
engineer and that Lawrence over time to send
data questions into into
the wild model. And something is
coming back and it learns to interpret these
answers, and the the connections
of these of the controller
are responsible for sending good stuff,
good questions, and interpreting
the answers. And you have to
do lots of tasks to
to, to make it a a
good controller a good a controller that is
good at asking at addressing
the important parts of the world model and ignoring
the irrelevant parts. Given the
current context, the current task,
how many more minutes do I have? Can somebody tell
me that?
Do we have any kind of communication going
on here? Is there maybe some
can somebody somebody type into the
chat how much more time I have left?
Five minutes.
Five more minutes. Excellent. Okay.
Good. So, maybe
we now have, a
very selective
selection of, previous work on
wild models, 1990,
very very general world models
recurrent neural networks, which are general purpose
computers. Can you see that they are
general purpose computers? Well, because
a couple of recurrent connectors, you can
implement a NAND gate.
A NAND gate. And now you
know maybe it's that you learn
in the first semester of computer science that
the arithmetic, unit of your
laptop can be
emulated just by a network of NAND
gate. Which means that,
a recurrent network is as powerful
as as your laptop at least.
So it's not universal in the sense that
the storage is limited and
and in this universe, we don't have
any any universal
computers, because that would
require, infinite storage or
potentially infinite storage. So, apparently,
we don't have that, but we can always add a
little bit of storage whenever
whenever we need more. And so in that
sense, we have these laptops and
other computers, which are
reasonably close to this notion of
universality. So we can't
otherwise are like that, and then we,
can use them in the stupid way, which was the 1990
way, which is planned millisecond by millisecond,
but it's still what, you know, people
twenty, thirty years later did, for
for certain board games, like chess and
Go. It's still the way to go, where you really
simulate millisecond by millisecond, and then you
have a a giant, search tree
and exponentially growing search tree,
and then you can use function approximation to,
you know, cut
cut off most of these,
these growing branches of the search
tree. And so there are ways
of of doing these,
millisecond by millisecond rollouts and
and in simple situations like with board
games, that's good enough. But for the real world, it
doesn't work. For the real world, all of that doesn't
work. No. There you have to deal
with abstractions, and,
and with higher level concepts that allow
you to to decompose your future
plans into chunks. You know,
where you say, okay, now I want to go to,
to real, you know, from where I am
and and to do that, I'm
not going to simulate my future like
this. I'm not going to say, okay. Let's
suppose I move my little pinky like
this. And then I grab my
phone like this, and then I call
a taxi, and I'm not simulating all of that.
No. I'm thinking about a couple
of crucial events that have to
happen on my way to Rio, and,
and I already have sub
programs, stored for going from
Kia to the taxi station, and
then, I know the taxi station is going to
bring me to the airport. I have to check-in,
And then for nine hours, nothing is going
to happen, and I get off in a real
and stuff. So you you already
have all kinds of sub programs that can deal
with, with these
these
these action sequences that,
that are already under control, And the
only thing that you are doing while you're planning
is you you are looking at these high
level junctions from
one,
one one one
sub sequence of your journey to the next
one. So there are these these junctions,
and and that is what you are looking at
as you're planning your futures. So
that you are just
looking at a small set of possible high level
futures. And all of this is computer
stuff. And all of this can be
implemented by
recurrent control networks that learn to
prompt recurrent
model networks, raw models,
And I think that's, what humans do.
That's what I do, what you do.
And our, artificial
neural networks,
we'll have to do the same thing to become efficient.
And in many ways, I think it's already happening.
And, and many of the
large language models a more limited
domain are already doing that.
And there, the prompts are not just arbitrary
number sequences. No. The prompts are usually
natural language, often
English. But, you know, there
are many other kinds of prompts, which are just
images And all of that,
you can you can
send as prompt
sequences into your model and wake
up the internal representations that are relevant
for whatever
you want to achieve at the moment.
And then something comes back. And
there, you then do learning
by now, learning by
hierarchical planning. All this stuff that is computable can
be in principle, learned
by systems like that, and they can become much
more efficient than,
those systems that we had in 1990, which
we did millisecond by millisecond
planning.
Are there any questions?
So before we get on to yeah. We'll give a random applause
for our speaker.
Yeah. Thank you. By the
way, I should also mention
that, unfortunately, Jorgen didn't
have time today so he sent me
his avatar.
So we have, time for, I think, two questions before
we move on to our next speaker, if anyone wants to
Hi. My name is Josef. Thank you for your talk.
I think one problem that we have with this millisecond
prediction is that our prediction
are actually conditioned on their actions.
And our actions is actually on this
midsectional space How do
you see this problem? If you agree, how could you move
from the midsections to
abstract actions?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Now, of course, all these,
it can go away. If you look at
general purpose neural networks such as
recurrent neural networks, because
there, the one model really sees all the
previous actions So it sees a
long sequence of actions, and it sees,
all also a long sequence of inputs.
Because, you know, when I press the controller and
executes a millisecond actor, then something
changes the video that comes in
changes a little bit. But the the one model of
Power sees, also has seen
the second before that and the five minutes
before that It's all part of,
of what it takes into account to make the next,
prediction. And then,
it give an up sees and internal representations, which
stand for abstract stuff. So now there's
a hidden unit, which is only on if
somebody said,
I want to build a wild model that,
ignores the details of the pixel
So there are many ways of saying that sentence,
but there are a few units
that are always on within, you know, the
hidden units your Walmart, whenever you say that.
And the the reinforcement learning prompt
engineer, the controller, wants to
find those and wants to address those and maybe
a few others which are relevant in
context of the current task, which is not
a millisecond by millisecond task, but
is maybe, a task that will require
a a day you know, like,
going to Rio from here.
I see. Thank you.
Hi. For the talk. What do
you think are the promising avenues to
bring back all that body of knowledge of work
like twenty five years ago on hierarchical
high school planning, symbolic settings, Yeah. The
already worked on those abstraction problems. Now that
we have all models that don't
have to learn all the time because they are
already good. And so you can interleave plenty
and learning. Just like Diana
did What do you think would
be a good way to address all that?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So
Daimler, what did Dina do? Dina,
did planning also by rollouts. You know?
And it had a basically, it didn't have
a neural network to do with the predictions. No. It
had a lookup table. No?
So that was, a
very simple kind of
world model. And,
and and
and one interesting thing is maybe also in 1991,
we had this even 1990,
we had a SOCO generator which,
however, was in in retrospect
from today's perspective was to
restrict it. But it was kinda cool. You know?
So how does it work? You have,
you have, you a
system that has already learned a couple of things,
a reinforcement learning system, go from
a to b, go from
b to z, go
from this point to this point and
so on. So it knows already a couple subprograms.
The system has learned that by reinforcement learning.
Now we have an evaluator, an
evaluator whose only task is
to get as an input, start
and a goal, and predict
whether whether the current
system is able to achieve that. So you
say, zero if there is
no effort in going from a to b,
and from start to goal, and you say
one if there's maximum effort, if
if you don't know any, way of getting there.
And then you can build
an adaptive subcode generator, a gradient
based subcode generator, which learns so
gradient descent to generate subcodes. How does that
work? Well, you take two copies
of the evaluator. You the evaluator
should get as an input a start
and a subgoal, which we don't know yet.
And then the subgoal, and
the the the start goal into the evaluator,
and it makes a prediction about
how easy it is to go from, from
start to the subgoal. You have another
copy of the evaluator, which goes from sub goal
to goal. And makes a prediction
about how easy it is to do that. And
then you have beneath
that, you have a ZIP code generator,
and the guy is seeing start and
goal and is generating subcodes.
It's a neural network that generates sub
goals given start and goal, And then,
of course, you train it by taking these
two copies of the evaluator
and you say you want to minimize the,
costs of going from star to gold by minimizing
the sum of the costs of the first
element em em em em em em evaluator and the second
evaluator, and then you propagate backwards,
and then it learns to become a better and better subcarrier
generator. That was another 1990
system that was already doing
cool, subco generation, jumping
across long sequences
of actions and just going to the importance
of course and then learning to
generate better and better of calls. Oh,
nineteen ninety nine ninety one. But it's
not as general as the, reinforcement
learning prompt engineer that I,
published in 2015 and the learning to
think paper learning to think,
exploiting algorithmic information in the
world model to,
to solve, any sub goal
problem or other kind
in, in
a computable way, a system
that is general enough to run
all possible algorithms. Recon
networks, or similar things that have
memory and that, can
learn by creating descent to to
exploit that memory.
Thanks a lot for the data the detailed
answer. So let's, thank
our speaker again for an awesome talk.
Thank you, my friends. Thank
you. And, we'll move
on to the next session. In the
speaker line of today. So today, I'm going
to be welcoming doctor Sarah Parrso who's
a principal research manager in the People
Centric AI group at Microsoft Research in
Cambridge. Her research interests are
data efficient learning, large vision language
models, and controllability of visual generative
models, including interactive world models, and their application
just support creative ideation. So
let's welcome Sarah.
Hello, everyone. Thank you for staying until the
last day of the conference.
Alright. So today I'll be talking
about building role models for this specific purpose
of enabling creators to build
new types of interactive experiences.
First of all, to make sure that we're all on the same page,
I know there is many ways to define warm models
nowadays. So what I'm going to be talking
about is models that generate
possible future states of an environment given
a history of states and actions.
These models have been getting increasingly
popular in recent years and have
seen applications in robotics, autonomous
driving, and gaming. And they're often
marketed as one
of the key approaches on the path to AGI.
Now we're gonna be a bit wild today and we're
not gonna look into anything related to
AGI. We're actually more interested
in tapping into the
potential of our model for interactive
entertainment. And more specifically,
we want to put the creator back in the center
and see how they can be using world models
to create entirely new types
of interactive entertainment.
So to understand what creative professionals
would need, for this purpose,
we went ahead and had conversations with them.
So we had interviews with creative
professionals who interacted with some of these
AI generated interactive environments.
And got their thoughts on what they
would wanna see from this from these models.
Some of the key takeaways we got was that
what I want to see is rapid creative for
the the typing. So being able to try new ideas
quickly and test them in an interactive
world. They're also interested
in very personalized experience.
So some kind of co creation between
the creator and the user who
will be crafting their own
experience. And lastly, large
scale experiences that are personalized to
the user to their
creator style. So thinking, for example,
about going back to a concert
hall after your favorite artist has given a show.
Now in this talk, we're going
to be focusing on the first angle, rapid
creative prototyping which
requires being able to try new
ideas quickly a world model. So
we'll be looking at real time inference, fast
fine tuning on small datasets, and
ability to control the world model
without having ML expertise.
On our team, the project started with
the word in human action model
which was published in Nature in February
2025. And the goal was to answer
the question of given a very large
transformer, is it possible to
learn complex three d environments and
in-depth interactions using
only raw video footage.
Based on this slide, the answer is, yes.
We the the videos you can see
on the right hand side are all generated by
the boring human action model, which we called one
for short.
And to get a bit of clear idea
of how one works, it's
actually a very simple architecture
of which is inspired from
large language models. First,
we train a
vector quantized tokenizer
which converts our images into a sequence.
Of tokens, discrete tokens,
we then take our input image, convert them
into tokens, convert our actions into
token as well. And build
interleave sequences of image and actions,
which are then fed to a causal transformer.
Which does next token predictions to predicting
the next token based on the sequence history.
So something that's interesting about one here is
that it's not just predicting the next
observation, but it's also predicting the next
action in the sequence depending on where we are.
In the sequence. This means that
one is not only doing world molding,
can also predict the next action given an
observation. Or it can also predict entire
sequences of gameplay on its own.
One thing that's very important to us because
we are keen to put creators in the center,
and work with them towards building these models,
It's very important to us that we don't crawl the
web and potentially steal their work.
So we've been using
as our training data set data from
a game called Bleeding Edge. Which is,
twenty twenty third person
multiplayer game it has 13 characters,
all of which has their innate set of actions,
And it's quite a complicated
very fast environment, so quite difficult
to learn. For a model.
In a partnership with Ninja Theory, which is
the game studio behind Bleeding Edge, we were able to collect
about seven years of actual human
playing the game.
Now again, going back to our idea of
we want to build models so that creatives can do
something fun with them. We
didn't just build
one in the February 2525
Nature Paper. There was also a
big part of its work which was a
user study again, having conversations
with game designers trying to understand
how they would wanna use these models and what they would
wanna see as in terms of capabilities
from these models. And this was used
to, inform our evaluation strategy
from three key axis. First one
is consistency. That's the model generate accurate
content. Diversity. Can the
model generate different plausible outcome given
the position? And persistency, can
the model incorporate and maintain user edits?
So In terms of consistency, we started
looking at what happens as we scale up training
Taking here an example of a ground truth
human gameplay, what we're going to do is
provide our model with the few starting frames
of these videos and then
generate the rest of the video
by providing the controller actions from this
input sequence. So you can see from this input
sequence, we have a character breaking a power
cell. This is incrementing the count of seeds
collected, one thing that's important about
this character, it is the only character in the game
capable of flying So this is a game mechanic
that is relatively rare and a bit more difficult
to learn. Early on in training,
we start seeing that the model has learned a little
bit of the environment but it quickly degrades
into, blobs of nothingness.
Which is not something we would like to see.
As we continue training, we get a much
more stable environment. But some of the
core mechanics are not there yet. So for example, the
character hasn't learned to fly yet.
And as we get to, full
fully training the model, we
now have very consistent environments,
and our character has finally learned to fly.
Which is very nice to see.
In terms of diversity, the task
was simple. We would start from a
point where there's a lot of possibilities
to explore. And let the
model generate full sequences of gameplay.
Looking at whether we get very different
outcomes. And based on these videos, you can see that we
get quite diverse outcomes from the same
starting point.
Lastly, my favorite part looking
at persistency of user edits.
So what we tried here was adding objects
on an input frame, seeing what happens
in the game. So this power cell,
has been put in a place where it never spawns in
the game. And what you can
see is that it's immediately in trick or taking the game
and our playable character is even going
to attack it and destroy it.
Similarly, we can insert a character
in an input frame and sing what
happens.
Oops.
And sorry about
that. The character gets
integrated and immediately starts attacking
our poor playable character. So
doesn't go very well for us here.
But quite good news in terms of persistency
of user edits.
Now one was a really cool,
model that we built, but it thinking
back into we wanna be able to do a
creative prototyping, There's
there were quite a few limitations that prevented
us from achieving this.
The biggest limitation was the slow inference
process. So one was doing next look and
prediction. Which
means very slow inference for images.
It was impossible to test and interact with the
model in real time. The model
was also trained on a very large dataset
Seven years of gameplay is huge.
Which means prohibitive compute. If I'm a creator
and I want to create my own model on my own environment,
I probably don't have capacity to
train on seven years of gameplay.
And lastly, the model is trained on a fixed
set of mechanics. Means that we cannot generate
content that deviates from the original gameplay
so it's quite difficult to try out new ideas.
Addressing the first limitation we built,
one more t, short for one real time,
achieving real time inference by making modification
to our architecture. So if you remember,
one is this very simple
next token prediction transformer with a pretrained
tokenizer. Didn't make any changes
to the tokenizer there. But we made quite a
few changes to one. To achieve
real time inference. So firstly,
our causal transformer is now bidirectional,
which enables us to predict all the tokens simultaneously.
What I like to say is,
now the backbone is predicting the first draft
of the image. And,
this is enabled by set of learnable input
tokens, which provide a scaffolding to
guide the generation of the first frame.
We also have context tokens which
comprise the larger information of the context.
This is very important, again, for efficiency
as it will be fed into a
low cost transformer, which iteratively
refines the prediction of the backbone
using a masking that type
inference procedure. So
what does that look like in terms of acceleration?
You can see one was going at 0.2
frames per second. If we do not compress
the token and fill the whole sequence into the
refinement transformer, we get an
acceleration, but still not real time with four
frame per second. And one more
t, you achieve 17 frame per second.
With, the first draft of the
backbone being up to 25 frame per second,
but then we would have substantial reduction of quality.
So in terms of what it looks like
when we interact with the model, on the left, you
have one, we enter an
action press predict, wait a while for
the few frames to be generated, On
the right, we we have one more t, which instantly
responds to controller actions. And
you can essentially kind of play the model
as you would play a game.
Although it's not as fun. Well,
it is quite fun.
Now it's pretty good. We have a real
time model that we can interact within
real time, which is a great step forward in terms of
being able to do prototyping. However,
we still need seven years of gameplay to
train one model, which is
still pretty expensive. So
one of the, experiments we did
was first we tried to adapt one to a
different type of environment.
In this case, the quick two model.
The quick two game.
We didn't have any data from Quake two.
And, again, we didn't want to crawl the web.
So what we did was worked with Game Tester
to collect data by giving
them instructions on what we wanted to collect and how
we wanted to collect the data. It
was a great back and forth
process where we would collect data
train a model, see what the model was
not doing well, and going back and collecting the missing
data. By doing
this data collection very intentionally, we
were able to learn a full
model a full level of quake
two with only hundred hours of gameplay,
which is a massive reduction from the
seven years of gameplay that we needed.
For
the bleeding edge models. Some of the
other learnings we got from the QUIC two
model was that we this approach does generalize
across games. So here I have examples
of two of two games, but we did try
a few games internally.
And we also managed to double the resolution
at no additional inference cost by simply improving
our tokenizer slightly. You
wanna play the quick model, it is available on Copilot
Labs. Just for the
QR code.
Now speaking of increasing resolutions,
we didn't stop there.
We took the learnings that we got from Quake and applied
it to our bleeding edge dataset. We
now have a one point o.
Model which is working at x year resolution.
Real time, and hundred hours of gameplay.
This is still a work in progress. I
will not share the
secrets behind it. But if you do wanna
try it, I have a demo available, so come to
me after this talk.
So So now we have high resolution
real time models that can be trained in
about hundred hours of gameplay, which is
pretty good progress from our original one.
We're still
have the main issue of we have a fixed set
of gameplay mechanics that we cannot deviate from.
So how can we try new ideas quickly
and prototype them in the world
model? Without degrading its quality?
So the common idea thinking
of generating
something new is immediately scaling up to
more diverse content.
The problem with scaling up with very diverse
data is that behaviors
that emerge are not necessarily
predictable and not necessarily easy to
trigger reliably. So we decided
to look at a different approach, which is
more focused on control to make sure
that anything any behavior that
we generate have as can be
triggered very predictably and reliably.
To achieve this, we looked at building targeted
small sets dataset,
small scale datasets using parameter
efficient fine tuning to avoid degrading the quality
of the original model and using
an explicit trigger mechanism to make these new behaviors
happen. In this case, we use text.
As a proof of concept,
for environment editing, we use a
task which we call body swap. Where the
objective is to swap the playable character
to another using a test instruction.
So this is not a very complex task and we
use this for a few reasons.
Firstly, this is a task that is very easy
to evaluate both qualitatively and quantitatively.
So for quantitative evaluation, we fine
tune the VLM to recognize the characters.
Then we can prompt the model. To verify that
the swap has happened. This is also
a task that we can simulate pretty easily in
our training dataset.
And to do this, we curated
data sets to 55,000 training
samples, which is very, very small compared to
our original seven years of gameplay.
And the idea was to match different sequences
in our warm training set
finding locations on the map where
the characters are on the same location, similar camera
angle, and doing similar actions.
To enable fine tuning our model
with the body swap datasets,
was actually pretty easy because of the architecture
the transformer based architecture. We could just
integrate the text our sequence.
And learn the model to swap. Based
on this text. The text prompt that we use
are based on character appearance, character
skills in the game, and also the character's
name.
So this is what a VolleySwap model
looks like. We tested three
different ways of fine tuning the model.
Full fine tuning, which does degrade the quality
of the world model originally. And two
parameter efficient fine tuning methods, LoRa and
DORA. We didn't go very much in-depth
into using the best possible methods.
But the key idea here was to gather insights
on how we could find your models on these small
datasets. So
some of the key learnings here
fully functioning the model leads to the
best performance in terms of swapping characters.
This happens very reliably pretty much
with any prompt that you provide. However,
the quality of the world will degrades,
which is why the quantitative score of the
unique prompts a
bit lower than you would expect.
Because the VLM has
been trained on real world on real data,
and might struggle a bit more to recognize
the characters. The
LoRa and Dora models are doing really well when
the prompts are very specific. So, for example,
swap me to the character called buttercup.
But are struggling a bit more when the prompts are ambiguous
and there's multiple potential characters
it could swap to. So for example, swap
me to a character who's a female.
So the main takeaway here is that we are able to
learn these new mechanisms trigger them,
very reliably There's still a bit
of work to find the best fine tuning
methods, to
find the best way to both find a balance
between entirely preserving the the world model.
And,
achieving good quality new mechanisms.
So summarizing everything that's happened so
far,
we have one. Single model
has demonstrated that it can learn
game physics, character behaviors, environment in
dynamics from role gameplay video.
Now does the model know the learn of physics?
Definitely not. It but it does
learn how to transition from one state to the next
in a way that is consistent with the physics
of the game. We then have
one more t, our model which is improvement
of a one achieving real time inference
allowing to play the model as you would play a game.
Building one more T, we've also managed
to achieve training models with
substantially less data. Going from seven years to
hundred hours of gameplay. And evidence
that the model generalizes The approach
generalizes across multiple games.
We have, early stage one two
point o and g resolution model
at real time inference. Again,
trying on a hundred hours of gameplay.
And we have experiments trying out how we can
learn new controllable behaviors, learn
new game mechanics with a very small datasets
and very targeted experiments. So
obviously, our body swap is a proof of concept, and there's
a lot more that we could try. We are quite interested
in seeing how we cure can curate more
complexity mechanisms with
data curation pipelines.
And,
I wanted to conclude here by going back to
this slide. Highlighting
that we've only scratched the
surface of what can be done with the war bottles
for creative purposes. We've been looking
at creative prototyping, but
there's a whole lot of research questions that are very
excited there. And I definitely encourage you to
explore them. You
very much.
So, we have
some time for a few questions. If anyone's interested,
you can come up to the mic here and
Hi. Thanks for the amazing talk.
You mentioned multiple times that you collect
data with some players.
What prevents you from doing it from,
an AI agent?
So then the dataset that I've talked about we
are we're collected with humans. That's generally
better quality data. So when we can do that with human,
we would would do it.
We do have experiments on datasets that
are not open source that are using agents to collect data
as well. You.
Hi. Thank you. This was very interesting
talk. I'm sure you know the gaming industry
is going through mass massive layoffs these past years.
And, you said something you said that
creative professionals be really benefit from those
work. But in my personal experience in speaking
to game designers, I have found a lot more
people who are afraid of this kind of technology than people who
who are excited about it. Like, given your expertise,
I'm wondering how do you think this connects to the layoffs
that have happened before in these past years.
How do you think this will impact the industry
going forward? Sorry. Could you rephrase that? I didn't
Yeah. I'm wondering. Oh, I wasn't even
talking to me into it, I think. I'm wondering,
how do you think this kind of technology connects
to recent layoffs in the gaming industry?
And how do you think this will impact the industry
going forward? Yeah. I think
that's interesting. So we are using
game environments as as a test
bed because it's know, it's very easy.
We have visuals and controller actions. That's a great
way to develop the models. I
do feel like gaming is not the best place
for this type of technology.
We're essentially learning to reproduce game content
a game that's already there. So
my intuition is it's be more
interesting as something at the intersection between
media and gaming. So
yeah, more kind of interactive
experiences rather than making games
faster. Thank you.
Hi. Thank you for this great talk. It's really
cool what you do with video games. My
question is basically so it seems that you
stick with the autogenerate quantization technique,
where all the modern video
modern modern video generators are doing diffusion.
Of flow matching. How, what do
you think about that, and regarding,
you know, real time inference and this kind of
things. Yeah. I expected
this question. So,
yeah, I guess, historically, we started
exploring how the LLM type
of architectures can be used to
learn new types of behavior
and, you know, training at scale.
Historically, we started with discrete representations,
and we kind of built on our
expertise. The
question of our discretization
better than continuous are
autoregressive models better than diffusion models is
something that we're actively looking into, and we
we are very interested
in understanding this in more detail. The
consensus is diffusion models are the next
the best thing But
what we do feel is that most of
the evaluation on diffusion model is centered
around visual quality.
And there we can agree that a continuous
model, a continuous diffusion model would always have better
visual quality than a discrete model.
However, we don't have that much knowledge in terms
of long term consistency.
And all the quality of the war model. Like, all the features that
we would want from a war model. This is
something that we're looking into.
How does a war model
perform if we are using this representation
of if we are using continuous representation,
what is more stable,
This is going beyond visual quality.
Thank you very much.
So, if there's no more questions, we'll thank our speaker
again.
So we're gonna start the second poster
session now for the next half hour, and then our next talk is
going to be from professor Surgly Bean.
Speaker session. I'm really happy to introduce
professor Sergei Levine. Who works
from the department of electrical engineering and computer
science, Berkeley in California.
He's a cofounder of Physical Intelligence, a robotics
AI company building foundation models
for the physical world. His research also focuses on
machine learning for decision making and control
with an emphasis on deep reinforcement learning,
robotics, and autonomous agents.
Please. Welcome, Sergei.
So since, this is a workshop talk,
Since this is a workshop talk, I figured I would,
present on, something maybe a
little bit more half baked. This is not a talk
that has, like,
super polished and you know, complete results, but
maybe gives a little bit of food for thought and stirs
the pot a little bit. On what we think of
as a world model. So,
you know, probably the most common
perception is that world model is something
that provides a very high
fidelity simulation of the world. This is a video
from SORRAM,
but, you know, there's lots of generative models that produce
very realistic results these days. And, conventionally,
we would think of a world model as something that represents
like, p of s
t plus one given s t a t, like a transition
function. Or maybe, the
same thing, but in a partially observed space. With
partial observations, you have to, of course, account for history,
but it's basically the same idea.
So something like a learned simulator.
That's a very reasonable way to think about it,
but do we really need this?
Is there a more abstract
notion of a model that maybe
for a lot of use cases might be just as good
but could be more accessible? Or maybe
even better in some ways. So, here
are some natural ways to think about
a world model a model
that knows how the world works for
a person. Let's say that you're out
shopping you wanna answer a question
like, if I buy this ingredient, will
I be able to make a salad with it?
Or if you're navigating a subway map,
if I get off at the station, will it be easy
for me to walk home from there? Now,
these are not questions that
require you to generate an
entire video of what's gonna happen when
you're trying to decide if this ingredient will make for a nice
salad, you're probably not
playing back in your mind the entire process
from buying the ingredient all the way to going home
to your kitchen and preparing the
salad and then wondering how tasty it
is. You're probably, asking this question
in a more abstracted sense.
These questions are not about predicting the future frame
by frame, but they
entangle future events and the agent's
own capabilities. If you're thinking,
will this ingredient make a good salad? That's not just a question
about the ingredients, it's also a question about you and what you're
gonna be able to do with it. And your skill set, your
repertoire of behaviors, and so on. But it is,
in some sense, a very useful question to ask.
In fact, if you can answer all such questions,
you probably understand a great deal about the world.
Arguably, the ability to answer any question
of this sort is much closer
to a fully functional understanding
of the world than a model that generates the future pixel
by pixel. So,
learning to do this, I would argue, is actually easier
and more useful to you as an agent
trying to make decisions. Now,
this is a little bit abstract so far. So
let's try to take this intuition
and, ground it in, like, an actual
mathematical construct that we can try to implement
in a computer. So first, we'll
take a very reinforcement learning centric
perspective of all this. I'm a reinforcement learning
researcher, so it's more natural for me to think in this way.
Maybe it makes sense to you. Hopefully, it does.
In r l, pretty much any algorithm
for learning to do control can be decomposed
into three basic parts.
There is the part where you interact with the world and gather
information, really really important because if you wanna
learn how to act in the world, you have to gather information in the
world. Then there is a stage
where you learn something.
For example, you fit a model. Even model
free algorithms still learn something. Maybe
their model very rudimentary. Maybe it's something like a
value function or even a Monte Carlo estimator.
Of course, if we're concerned with world models, this is
the box that's typically going to have the most interesting
stuff. So fit something
that models something about the world.
Then use that thing you just fitted to make
your controller or your policy better.
And then go out and use it to collect some more
experience in the world Use
that additional experience to make your model even
better. Use that better model to make controller
even better, and then repeat forever.
So that's a a basic RL loop and pretty
much any RL algorithm whether model based or model
free is gonna have some building blocks like this.
And improving the policy actually
has a very simple mathematical definition.
You just want to make the value of that policy,
value is defined as the expected cumulative
sum of rewards. You wanna make that value
high as possible in the initial state. What improve the
policy means. And what's the purpose
of the model? To estimate v.
The model tells you how good your policy is.
The model does a good job of telling you how good your policy
is, and allows you to, of course, evaluate
counterfactual decisions, then you can use it to
make your policy better. So a
model needs to be able to evaluate the policy so that
it can improve In fact, that is the only thing it needs
to be able to do. There's a lot riding
on the word evaluate here. It's not a
simple concept, but if you can do it,
you can make your policy better, and that is all you need.
So starting from this basic starting point,
there's this old idea that is,
quite, neat, I think, called
a successor representation. And the successor representation
is a mathematical object that
blurs the line between world models and
value functions. And here's how it works.
This slide is gonna have a bit of math on it, but
I'll try to keep this, you know, fairly simple.
This is not a very mathy talk.
So, if you write down the value function,
this is like literally a text value
function, it's the sum over all the time steps
from now until the end,
of the discounted expected reward. Expected under what? Well, expected
under the system dynamics, the transition function,
and your policy. Okay? That all makes sense.
This is typically what a world model would predict.
It would predict your system dynamics.
But now, we're going to rearrange these terms a little
bit and find out that we actually don't need
a model that predicts the next state.
We actually get away with something more
abstract. So,
what we'll do next is we'll write this
in kind of a funny way, as a sum
over all of the future time
steps where we're taking the
expectation under the probability of seeing
a state s t prime at time step
t prime in the future, given that we're currently
in state s t. It's like, if I'm currently
here at time one, what is my distribution of
states at time 100? Okay.
Ordinarily, you would do this by marginalizing
out the distribution overall at intermediate states,
but let's not worry about that for now. And
then, I'll expand out the expectation as a
sum. That's just by definition of expectation.
And then I'll rearrange the the
summation terms so that I group all the probabilities
together. So notice that
I'm multiplying everything by the reward of some state,
so I can take the state outside of the summation
over time steps, and now it's a sum over all
states. Inside of it I have a sum over all
the time steps, the probability of landing in
each state at each time step. Multiply
by the discount, and around that I multiply by the
reward. So notice that all the probabilities
are grouped around these inside these parentheses.
And I can take this thing around inside these parentheses
and I can treat that
as a single monolithic distribution over
states. And specifically, it's
a distribution that,
has a geometric distribution over
time steps and inside of it, the
probability of reaching a particular state at
that time step. And this thing
is called, the successor representation.
It was invented by Peter Diane in
1993. And
essentially, what this distribution represents
is how likely am I am I to
see a particular state let's call it
s future, if I start in state
s t? And that kind of makes
sense. Like, if all you care about is the total
reward you're gonna get, you don't actually
care about when you're gonna get that reward.
All you care about is that at some point
in the future, some I don't care which
point, at some point in the future, I am likely to see
this state. And this is
simpler than a full
world model in the sense that it doesn't actually require
you to think about the sequence in which these things will happen.
Just care about how likely this to happen at some point
in the future. If I buy this ingredient, how
likely am I to eventually end up with a tasty salad in
front of me? I don't care if it's an hour from now
or two hours from now. What I care about
is how tasty the salad is.
So this kind of quote unquote model is
actually sufficient you want to evaluate and
improve policies because it's
literally derived from the equation for a value function.
So this derivation basically shows you that
this model is all you need if you wanna know how good your
policy is. And it's
simpler than a traditional world model
because it doesn't care about when something will happen,
it just cares about the probability
that some kind of state will be reached at
some point in the future. So,
So, essentially, it's saying, I know this will happen
in the future if I take this if
I start in the state, or if you want the queue version
of this if I take this action in this state.
So I think that's actually pretty interesting. And I think
in some ways, this type of model is actually
more intuitive
to me as a as a person because I don't typically
think of things in terms of the exact
occurrence of those events in time. If I want
to go to the airport, to fly,
back to California, I'm not thinking like,
hey, I need to know, leave this
building exactly you know, thirty seven seconds
from now, get into the the car,
you know, two minutes after that, reach the airport,
thirty two minutes and fifteen seconds later,
just think about the probability of those events
happening success successfully at some
term the near future.
Now, a few technical details.
The cool thing about these kinds of successor
representations that they can actually be represented as
value functions. So you can take this
probability of reaching some state s future given
that you start in s t, and and, you
can represent it as value function
that takes in two arguments, the current state
and the future state. Let's call it s plus just to make
the notation a little bit more concise.
And you can actually express this thing
via a recursive relationship very similar to
the Bellman equation. It
has two terms. The
current reward and
the future value. And it's just
like a bellman equation
where the reward is an indicator
for whether are in a particular state or
not. Essentially, you get a reward of one for
each s plus, a reward of zero for everything else,
then, as long as you do discounting correctly, the
value is literally the probability
you will reach the state s plus in the future.
Or the frequency with which you'll reach more
generally. So
because these things can be modeled with a Bellman
equation, represent a kind of a bridge
between model free and model based RL.
So like model based RL, they can be used to make
predictions about the future, And
like model free RL, they can be trained
with the Bellman equation with temporal
difference learning. Which is really appealing because that
allows us to train them with off policy
methods on on data,
it allows us to benefit from dynamic
programming and so on. Of course, you
can also write the Q function version of this, so the only
difference between the v version and the Q version is
that the Q version takes in
both a state and an action, it's making
the prediction if I start in state s t
and then take action a t,
likely am I to reach s plus? And that, of course,
gives you a nice way to maximize your
probability of reaching s plus by taking
the action for which this value is
largest. So if you are in a particular state s
t and you take the action for which
the queue value for your desired
s plus is very high, you are taking
the action that maximizes your chance
of getting there. If you wanna make a tasty
salad, plug in tasty salad for s plus,
plug in your current state for s t
and pick the action a t that maximizes this value.
So and this is, of course, very useful also
if you want to have a queue learning style
off policy algorithm which is really nice.
Okay. So
now this is a kind of old you know, very classic
stuff. This is basically just copy and paste from
Peter Dione's paper from, thirty years
ago. Let's talk about
more modern things. Let's talk about how
we can use this kind of idea
to train modern generative
models. So here's the key question. Can we train
modern generative models like diffusion models to
be these successor representations?
So the this is the the class equation.
It's, basically, a Bellman equation
a kind of weird q function that actually
learns these, future state
probabilities. The trouble is that
generative models typically,
maximize approximate log likelihoods.
They don't regress to probabilities. If you wanna
train a diffusion model, you don't need a
probability as a target, you want to generate
data such that if you maximize the likelihood
of that data, actually learn the distribution you
want. So, this is actually not what you want you're gonna
be training generative models, whether they're diffusion
models or LMs or whatever. So
you want something that looks like this. You want something
that looks like maximizing with respect to
parameters of your model the expectation under some
distribution of the log probability of your model.
Or a bound on the log probability, you use
diffusion or other variational methods.
So what is this something? What is the data
distribution that you can plug in so
that you learn a successor representation?
So you want basically this target
distribution over s plus given
s t a t. Okay. There
is one very, very simple way to construct this.
It's very simple, but it has a major limitation. So I'll
start with that, and then I'll describe the less limited version.
So the simple way to construct this is
a trajectories, consists
of videos, let's say, You pick a
particular time step s t, and
then you sample t prime
a geometric distribution with argument gamma
to get a future time step. So this is a
gamma discounted future step. And then you
set s plus to be s d prime.
That's it.
So there's a problem with this approach
to generating p target, of course, is that it assumes that
your trajectory came from
the policy for which you're computing,
the successor representation. Why is this important? Well,
your prediction about how likely
this ingredient is to make a tasty
salad depends on
your salad preparation skills. Depends on your
policy pie. If you are very good at making salads, maybe
you can make a delicious salad out of
lousy ingredients. And if you're very bad at it, maybe
you just need to buy a fully finished salad, such that
your cooking skills are only needed to, like, unpack
it from the box. So it depends on
pie. And, of course,
if you need all of your data to come from your
policy, really limits your ability
learn from external data sources. If you can only learn
from your own experience of buying ingredients
and cooking salads, then you will not be able to
use you know, third hand information
things people tell you, things you watch on TV, and so
on. So we really like to move beyond this limitation.
And, of course, the original
formulation the one that, Peter Diane
came up with, can
be implemented very easily with an off policy
estimator because we know that q learning
methods and all sorts of other value based
RL methods are off policy. So
they can use data from other policies
to learn the value of the desired policy.
And the way that works is, of course, the queue function
is a function of any action you want, and then
policy only shows up in the target value, so you
can evaluate it computationally even if
your dataset came from a different pulse.
So can we construct an off policy
estimator for this kind of generative objective?
And it turns out that we can. So,
this a slightly less old idea.
It's only six years old. It was
student Michael Chanorm in a policy called gamma
models. And,
the idea is the following. So, we want this,
p target So
is kind of the the the more correct way to write out the the
generate the general max cyclic objective. You're
gonna sum over all the states and actions in your data
set, you're going to use some kind
of generator to generate s plus
for that s a tuple. Then you're
gonna maximize its likelihood with your favorite generative
model.
So what you want p target to
produce is this
gamma distributed future state under your current
policy pi. Using
data from another policy, let's call it pi
beta. Okay?
And here's how we can factorize this distribution.
Basically, the the gamma
geometric distribution over future steps means
that can think of it as a probability you'll
stop at a particular time. So there's a one minus
gamma that you'll stop right away, then
a one minus gamma squared that you'll stop at the second
step, a one minus gamma cube that you'll stop at the third
step, and so on. So, that means that we can break up
this distribution to two terms, The
first term is the one that says,
what if you stop right now? And if you stop right now,
with probability one minus gamma, then you should
just return the next state. That's the next state
in your dataset. And then
if you stop at some point in the future,
then you can bootstrap this. You can actually use your
current model to produce
the future sample. So with probability
one minus gamma, just produce the next state,
with probability gamma, sample the future
from your own model, plugging
in the state ST plus one and
the action a t plus one from your current policy,
not from the dataset.
So it's it's like an analog to TDE
only generative. It's like a way to
sample a future state, using your own model
to train your own model. Of course, you need,
like, all the target networks and all that kind of business for this
to work. So, the procedure to sample
from the target distribution is to first
is with probability one minus gamma, just pick s
t plus one from the dataset. And
with probability gamma, pick
s plus from your current model
plugging in s d plus one and the
action a t plus one that you sample from your latest
policy. And this is an off policy
estimator. And you can use this to train any
generative model that can be that can be trained
to approximately maximize a log likelihood.
Okay. So
this includes GANs, normalizing
whatever you want.
And just to kind of remind everybody, what we're
doing is we're going from training a one step model that predicts
the next state to this multistep model
that's kind of predicted the predicting
this blurry future going going off into
infinity. With later steps
being exponential less likely than nearby steps.
So, this is a visualization for the
Hopper benchmark. And if you
train one of these things, it's very easy to then
predict values from it because you just have to
sample the states from your gamma model
and multiply them by the reward, average them together, and
that's your value. So this is a visualization
of this for the for the,
cart pole, RL benchmark task.
In the middle, you can see this blurry
probability distribution over future states. On the left
is the reward function, multiply them together,
and you get the value function on the right side. This is of course
a really toy
task. It's, two dimensional, but it this allows you to visualize that,
yes, the value function looks right. Those of you
that have done RL research might already know
might already have a visual classifier in your head for
what a good carpool value function looks like.
One on the right is in fact a good one, but you can
run this on a bunch and
model based RL method. In this case, we use it in
combination with m v and it
produces reasonable learning curves that learn pretty
quickly. And benefits from the model
as much as more explicit models that predict
s t plus one.
Now, so far, there's still a big limitation
with this approach, compared to a more
conventional world model, which is that this approach
is predicting future states
for a particular policy. It's off policy, so you can
plug in any policy you want, but once
you've trained it, it's really only making predictions
for the policy that you trained it for.
A good world model should predict counterfactuals.
It should tell you what would happen if I did
something different? So if you want to move
in that direction, have to modify
these,
successive representations also
take in some notion of intentions, some notion of
your plan about the future. And
we can do that. So, there are actually
many works that have done this. Sometimes it goes under the name
of universal successor features, things
like that. Gonna talk about a specific
instantiation called an intention
condition value function which has kind of an interesting
multilinear factorization.
So tension condition value functions
intuitively are trying to answer this question.
If you start from the state,
will you reach another state like will I open the cabinet?
If I act to
do x. So I open the cabinet if
I act a feshoe plate? Will I get a tasty
salad if I act to buy the lettuce? Okay?
So the green thing is the intention,
the red thing is the outcome. You care about what
is the probability of different outcomes given
different intentions. If you can make these predictions
for all outcomes and all intentions, then, of course,
you can make a plan by selecting the intention
that maximizes the probability
of your desired outcome. So now,
you're going to have a value function with three arguments,
your current state, the future
state s plus, and some
representation of a latent intention I'm going
to denote with the letter z. Okay?
And we call this an intention condition value
function.
The there are many ways you can represent these. You
can also look
train a bank of skills with any skill
discovery method and use that represent
z one interesting trick you can do
to represent them, with a linear representation.
So you can construct a future representation of
current states, future states, and intentions,
and represent your value function like this.
And this has some very interesting side effects.
So of course, you have to
pick a choice of z. And the way that we're gonna choose
z to make z a good representation
of rewards. Because what's a good representation
for intentions? Well, a good representation for intentions is the
reward you wanna maximize. If you intend to make a
tasty salad, then you plug
that in for z.
So how do we do this? Well, remember
that values are formed by
summing over your successor representation
times the reward. Now, doing
this over all states in in big continuous
state spaces is intractable because you have infinitely
many states, we're gonna do it in a feature
space. And the particular feature space that is
most natural to use here is actually
the same feature space we use to represent
s plus. Why? Because
the feature space we're using to represent s plus, that's
the thing that we're predicting over So if we can
embed the rewards into that same space,
then that's the natural representation to use
one of these intention condition value functions.
So we'll represent z's literally as
linear combinations of featurized future states
and rewards. So, basically, the way you can compute this
thing is sample a bunch of states that
you like, that you have rewards for,
featurize them, and average them together weighted
by their reward. And that gives you a c.
And then if you want to figure out how
good your intention is
for, like, achieving what it's supposed to do, then
you basically just plug it in for both the second and third
arguments. So you say, given this state, how
likely am I to have a tasty salad if I'm
intending to have a tasty salad? And then you
just plug you pick that as a z because that's what you wanna
accomplish. You can also evaluate counterfactors if you
want. And that might be useful if you
have if you believe that you haven't fully
trained this thing successfully for every possible intention,
and there are ways of doing that as well, but this is the simplest
way to do it. Okay? So train
on randomly selected start states, end states,
and random intentions, train it for all
these combinations. Okay. And
I should say this concept borrow borrows very heavily
a very nice paper introduced something called
the FB representation, by Tuarete
and Olivier. So
Okay. So there are a couple of ways
you could use this. One way you could use this
is for zero shot policy recovery.
This is kind of the analog of planning.
So, basically, once you've trained one of these,
things, then just compute the z
corresponds to your reward function. So you need a few
states that are labeled with rewards, average
them together, weight the features
of the future states by the reward, and just plug
in that z, so that's
the analog of planning. You can also use this for
feature extraction. So you can say, well, after I've trained this
thing, maybe I'm gonna use for model free RL.
It turns out that you can prove under very
fairly strong assumptions that phi of
s, the representation of current states, actually
sufficient to represent any queue function
for any reward. Long as you've trained everything to
convergence and the limit of infinitely many samples.
So that's basically the same as just using five
s in encoder of states putting a linear head
on top of it for your Q function.
And the theory shows that this is sufficient in
the limit of everything being, you know, infinitely
asymptotic. And
this thing actually works. You can use it for
some RL benchmark tasks like navigating a maze,
also use it for learning Atari games
from images. We actually
had a funny set of experiments where
we harvested Atari videos from
YouTube so they're for
some reason people post YouTube videos of themselves playing
Atari games, you can use it to train one of these
intention condition value functions that doesn't actually
require actions during training, and then you
can use it, as a feature representation for
various rapid. Queue learning to learn each
of the Atari games.
So Okay. And then to kind of
bring this back to the modern age, one of the things I
want to mention is a very recent
paper that combines these ideas, that combines
the generative TD updates, intention conditioning
that was actually presented at this site later by,
Zhang, Park, and Eisenbach
from Princeton. Where it
used essentially a pretraining recipe
that puts these things together with modern flow
master models So it trains an
intention, condition, success of representation
with flow matching and this generative TD
update in a pre training
phase. So starting with some offline
data, it discovers a set of skills in that
data. Those skills are the intentions, and that
uses mutual information skill discovery
then uses essentially, the gamma models
generative TD backup to learn successors
for each of those skills, So this
is the full objective, but it's it's basically just the
flow matching counterpart to the general
of TD equation that I had before. So it
has the same two terms, one minus
gamma times the next state. Plus
gamma times future states sample
from your model. And then, once you've trained
this thing, then you can have a post training phase where
you essentially use it to bootstrap RL.
So, you can get an initial queue function for your
task, by selecting,
by basically using your successor representation
to evaluate each of your skills kind of
a big equation, but it's saying something very simple, which is
sample from your successor representation, for
each of your skills, use it to evaluate
how good that's each of those skills is for your task.
And that gives you those value functions just like
before. Then you can use that in a
kind of a generalized policy iteration
framework to then refine the best skills further.
The equations are basically on implicit
q learning, Roughly speaking, you can think of it as
taking a max over your skills at each state.
Just like treating your skills as though they
were actions, maximizing over the skills to find
one most likely to perform your task in each state
and then iterating. And this ends
up working pretty well, so it does very well
on the on these, benchmark tasks that's
called OGBench. This is a
modern offline RL benchmark. It has
these, like, fairly difficult robotic manipulation
tasks like solving the the lights
puzzle or putting objects away in a
drawer, This method actually
matches or exceeds the state of the art
the time when it was published. So that's pretty
neat. That means that, you can actually instantiate these things
with modern generative techniques and they actually
work. Okay.
Now there is an important special
case of this kind of framework that I want to mention, that's
coming back to the title of my talk, which is that
successor representations, they actually have a very close
connection to goal conditioned reinforcement
learning. In fact, you can think of goal conditioned reinforcement
learning as a special case, as a restriction
of these more general value functions,
to the setting where all you care about is reaching
goals. So it's a special case of intention. In general,
your intention might be some arbitrary
set of future states, if your intention is
a single future state, then this essentially
goal conditioned reinforcement learning.
And goal conditioned reinforcement learning is a is an
important special case because it has
some special structure.
Here's a special structure. If you,
make a small transformation
of the original framework, which has a reward
of one for reaching the state and zero everywhere
else, you subtract a constant, you
subtract one from everything, then
your value function becomes a kind of a temporal
distance because you get a reward of minus one for
every time step until you reach the goal,
and zero when you reach it. So that
means that the negative of your value
is how far you are
from your destination. And that means
that the negative of your value function obeys
certain geometric properties. It looks a lot
like a distance. It's not actually a distance because a proper
distance should be symmetric, but it is a quasi
metric. So kind of an asymmetric distance,
and it obeys a triangle and
transitive property, which is say the distance
for reaching some distant point can be
bounded by the distance of reaching something in between, and
then from there, going to your goal. This
is again, this is not a new idea. This is a fairly
established idea. But the geometry of this
allows you to take
some shortcuts get more generalizable value
functions.
So, one of the things you can do is you can
use a neural network architecture
that captures this quasimetric property.
Again, this is not an idea that we came up
with, you can use something called a metric residual network
which basically by construction enforces
triangle inequality And then you
can learn a feature representation
of your states and goals but now
this feature representation is going to obey
that geometric property. So, if you
want a little bit of intuition for it, it's a little bit like embedding
your states in a Euclidean space where distances
are temporal distances
except that it's not a Euclidean space anymore because
it's a quasi metric rather than a full metric. But
roughly the same intuition. And
when you do this, you get better generalization
because now you can construct your embedding using nearby
states and have that embedding actually
generalized to longer distances. And that means
that you can accomplish more distant
goals the ones you trained on. So the key idea
that is that if trained properly, the features
actually generalize. And you can show
this theoretically as well. So
So, here's a little experiment on
this. A real world robotic scenario.
Took the bridge dataset, which consists of relatively
short atomic skills, like picking up one
object and putting it in a container. We trained
one of these distance models
these generalizable features. The method is called MQL.
It was actually presented at ICLIA this year.
And then we tested it just by commanding
a more distant goal. In this case, the goal requires
putting multiple objects on the plate. There
is no explicit planning over these objects.
It's literally just commanding a different goal
to a model trained on only on goals
required moving one object. So it really is kind of magical
generalization, metric
property. In this case, it's four objects.
And this method actually works quite well.
So, we have bank
of different evaluations single pick in
place, double, triple, quadruple,
and the more complex it gets, the more out
of distribution, the larger the advantage of this
metric method, m k, the one the
one labeled in dark green.
And it works on benchmark tasks as well, and that's
that's quite nice.
Okay. So, at this point, I see that I'm running a
little low on time. So I'm gonna actually,
skip ahead a little bit to
the conclusion and then I'll take some questions. There's some
other parts about using models, but
and and LLMs. You can do this with LLMs
as well. But in the interest of time, I'll skip through
this. Just go to the takeaways.
So world models
don't need to predict the next observation. And I think
it's actually very natural because when we think about
future events we don't necessarily imagine
a time synchronized movie of everything
that can happen. We think about like, hey, if I do this, here
an outcome that might happen at some point in the future.
A good outcome or a bad outcome. This will happen at some point in
the future is all you really need to plan
and act. And successive representations,
even though it's a very old idea, can be instantiated
with modern generative models, and we can
use these types of models to also predict
counterfactuals conditional intentions,
which allows us to essentially implement a kind
of planning Only the planning is much easier now
because you don't have to actually think about all the
sequential actions. Just the overall outcomes.
It's a special kind of a special kind of intention is
a goal, and that admits some really
nice structure and more
effective algorithms. These things can actually work
with robots in the real world. Which can
make them pretty practical can also work with LLMs.
I didn't get to that part, but you can train goal conditioned
language models actually get them to achieve conversational
goals. And that can work very well also.
Alright. I'll stop there and take questions. Thank you very
much.
Okay. Thank you, Sergei. That was a super
super interesting talk. So we have some
time for two questions, I think, if people wanna
line up here. See.
Anyone?
Thanks for the very
interesting talk. And, I
have a question about the details.
In the diverse
assumption, that it has assumption that
the data is comes from the policy?
Yeah. But I think if
we have a open
word but the data
also comes from other
persons' intention.
Other policy. So can you
Yeah. Yeah. Good question. So you
only need data from the current policy if you're using
the the naive kind of Monte Carlo estimator.
If you use the generative TD backup, then your data
can come from any policy. And I think these days,
the way that I would probably recommend doing it is to use
a method like
in the flow based paper that I mentioned,
where, we first take an offline
dataset break it up into the underlying
skills, which you can do in an unsupervised way. You
can think of it as a trajectory level
clustering, and then learn successive representations
for each of the skills. And now that
gives you a successor representation
condition on a particular policy, and you
have many policies available to you, and then you can
use you can either select the best one for your
task or you can do generalized policy
iteration you want to do multiple steps of improvement.
So as long as you use the more the more modern methods,
then you don't need data from the same policy that you're evaluating.
Thank you.
Thanks, Sergei. That's a really interesting talk.
I had a question about the
how sensitive the methods are to the diversity
of data that you train on. Are you assuming
that there are expert demonstrations Can you bootstrap
your way up and, like, you know,
decide what data to collect? Yeah. That's a
really good question. I mean, in general, any,
kind of offline RL method is gonna be very
Mhmm. And this is probably,
like, one of the most important yet under explored
aspects I mean, obviously, in an offline
RL theory, this is explored heavily, but at a somewhat
unsatisfying way that just says, like, if you have coverage, it
works, but coverage is a mysterious equation involving
a ratio two
probability distributions. In in terms of
the empirical results, it's a little hard to
say. I mean, like, the like for the Atari thing,
it worked using YouTube videos of people playing Atari,
but that's not like they don't play randomly. Obviously, if
someone posts a video of themselves playing an Atari game
inside because they're an RL researcher or because they're good
at playing Atari games. So I think empirically
it's kind of a complex question. I suspect
that probably the way it plays out is
you want data that is generally pretty good
but bad enough that there are mistakes and corrections.
And that's usually what, in practice, gives you coverage.
Yeah. Thanks.
Thanks for the talk. For someone with a
background in video understanding, I can't
see how we can go from you know, these
types of states to states that
are the level of tasty salad and add ingredient.
Do you foresee LLMs as the right
way going there? Or because hopefully,
we don't want to define these in a
handcrafted manner. So
there there is actually a lot of interesting
subjects to that question because it really comes
down to question of which representations we use.
Image pixels
are not generally a representation of state. Image pixels
are a representation of observations.
So kind of swept under the rug that distinction.
It becomes a little bit more apparent in LLM
world because in LLM world, you can't escape the fact that a token
is really not a state. Like, you know, in an LLM
world, a state really has to be a sequence.
And there, what you would basically end up doing
is you would have your state correspond to
some summary statistic. Now, a
summary statistic in some cases, is actually very easy to get
with an LLM. You can just ask an LLM a question
about a piece of text, and the answer to that question
is a summary statistic. So, you do need
to construct some representation and you need some reason
to believe that is at least
approximately Markovian for all of this to work. You can
do that, then you can apply these frameworks.
Awesome. So I think, we'll our
speaker again.
And I'll introduce our next speaker,
so it's my pleasure to introduce Mito Asran.
Who's a research scientist in, meta,
fair in Montreal. His research
focuses on self supervised learning and world
models especially joint embedding predictive
architectures, including IGP, VGP,
he received his PhD from McGill University
in Mila, and his work aims to build AI
systems learn abstract representations of the
world. Through prediction and latent space. And today,
he's gonna give us a talk on self supervised
learning for a world modeling. Let's please welcome
Nido.
Alright.
Hi. My name is Mido. I'm a research scientist
at FAIR. And, this talk is
gonna be about representation learning
for world modeling. So actually, that's quite a nice,
segue towards the end of Sergei's talk.
And in particular, I'll talk
about using self supervised learning to learn
good representations for world modeling.
And this work in particular, I'll focus on
b jappa two, which is
a method from, you know, a large team at
FAIR. It's about a year
old at this point, but I think it's still quite interesting
and we've been building on this work and wanting to continue
it. And vJEPT two is essentially
a method for self supervised learning from video.
And And, you know, maybe I don't need
this sort of slide at a workshop like this, but
I thought it was still fun to include them. So
let's just play the video.
K. Here you have a crow that's trying to get
access to some food. That's in a
tube, and that food is submerged in water.
So at first, the crow can't reach the food.
So it places a rock in the tube, causes the water
level, you know, causes displacement, the water level
tries. And now the crow can
actually reach the food. Now, I'm
I'm sure you've seen all sorts of fun examples
like these before. And,
you know, the truth is many species have a
demonstrated the ability to perform
these kinds of creative physical reasoning
tasks. Okay. And
so these kinds of creative physical reasoning tasks
require not just some common sense physical
understanding of the world, but also
low level motor control and planning.
Okay. And so the question is,
how can we kind of imbue
our computers or, you know, physical agents
with these kinds of abilities
to perform creative physical reasoning.
Well, one hypothesis is a world model.
Right? A hypothesis that, you know, maybe this
crow possesses a world model.
And, it can use that to simulate
sequences of actions that
lead it to its kind of desired goal state.
Okay. Now, getting a little bit into the mechanics
of it. One, you know,
fairly standardized,
formulation definition of world models at this point
in the community is as follows. A world
model takes in, a sequence
of observations and conditioned
on an action predicts future states
of the world. Now again,
you know, from the previous talk, this could be a one
step world model. Or it could be something hierarchical
that predicts further into the future. So
there's a lot of room here for abstraction.
And, you know, one of the things I want to focus on in this talk
is well, what is this representation space?
Again, it was kind of a nice segue from the previous talk.
Do we learn these world models? Do they predict
directly in pixel space?
Or did they learn in a more semantic
or learned abstract space?
Okay.
On you know,
world modeling in general is a very difficult
problem. Because modeling distributions
in high dimensional spaces is difficult.
And so me just play this video. It's quite
old at this point. This is a Soar model.
As good as some of these video generation models are getting,
you know, it's still very easy to find physical
inconsistencies in the
generated video.
And so again, not only is modeling distributions
in high dimensional space is difficult,
but it's also if you wanna use this kind
of world model for planning, it's
also not clear that
better pixel level prediction
is gonna lead to better planning.
Right? So planning over high dimensional observations
or state spaces is difficult. So
if your world model doesn't abstract away
a lot of this information, it said models every single
detail. If you distinguish between you
know, say there's a few specs on the wall and
I distinguish between those two states for
something that's irrelevant to my task, that makes
my planning problem harder. So
maybe, actually, pixel level
prediction or reconstruction does not
actually correlate with better planning performance.
Again, these are just all open questions. I don't know
what the right answer is.
And there's another challenge on top of all of
that. Which is that learning world models
for the physical world is hard because of
interaction data scarcity. Usually,
when we talk about foundation models, you know, in video
foundation models, we're talking about millions
of hours of video that we have access to.
But, you know, when we suddenly wanna train on robot data,
we're talking on the order of thousands of hours these
open source datasets. Right? So there's a huge difference
there. So again,
one kind of
can we leverage action
free video to learn a world model in a sample
efficient manner? So can you kind of try and leverage both?
And, this leads me to v j p two.
So,
this is kind of interesting work. It builds on
definitely a long history
of work by the community. There's a large
literature on this and, you know, method is a year
old at this point and we've been building on this
and growing. But here, the approach we
take, similar to other methods in the community,
is we start by learning from observation
data. So first, train a video
model on, you know, millions of hours of
Internet video. And then
we do a second stage where we
take kind of the video features learned from that first
stage, and train a latent dynamics
model on robot videos And here, we
only use, you know, sixty two hours
of unlabeled robot trajectories from the droid
dataset. And then we take
kind of our world model that operates in our
learned representation space and
we deploy zero shot on a robot,
our lab and another lab. So we deploy it on two
labs. Two Franco arms.
With image goals. So that's, you know, a bit of
the caveat also. And we try and just
have it, using planning, solve tasks.
To kind of try and match the, image
goal state. So I'll
start by discussing the learning from observation
part of the work.
So this is based on V Jeppe which is a joint
embedding architecture.
And the methodology is as follows.
So you have a video that you sample
from your dataset.
And then what you do is you mask it or you apply
some kind of corruption. So here, what we do
is we randomly drop out patches from
the video. And, it turns
out, actually, how you mask is very important.
Can lead to very different kinds of behavior.
I'll get into that a little bit in a second. But so we
take that video, we mask it by randomly drawing some
of the patches. And then we encode
that masked video with our video encoder.
Which is randomly initialized. And
then we use our predictor
to try and predict the representations
of the mass patches. Okay?
Now, which
which is that you can just output a constant vector,
right, regardless of the input video,
regardless of the patch. And, so that
would make this problem trivial.
Right? And so there have been many kind of
anti collapse terms proposed by
the community some of them are based for instance on contrastive
learning, So the idea where maybe you sample
like a batch of videos or images
and you try and push away representations of different
images or videos such that they don't all collapse.
To the same point. For instance, clustering
based losses where you kind of take a batch
of videos you cluster them and you enforce
your you know, something like a k means
for instance. You can have a a Gaussian mixture
model In short, you enforce
a clustering of your batch
and so you know, you enforce a kind of prior on your
cluster distribution And so that again prevents
collapse because it says you can't map everything to a
single vector.
And then there's bootstrapping and distillation.
This work, we actually just leverage,
bootstrapping and distillation. So our
target encoder here, which is what
computes the representations of target patches
that we're actually trying to predict, that's
an exponential moving average of our context
encoder. And again, all these networks are randomly
initialized. So this actually works. It does
prevent collapse.
I would say it's still not fully very well
understood why, distillation
based approaches maybe with something like
an exponential moving average Why this prevents collapse?
I've seen a few kind of, arguments
there's some theoretical works on this. But all
of them make some kind of simplifying assumptions. So I think there's
definitely still a lot to learn and understand.
And, you know, either I think we should
try and understand this better or try and
find simpler methods
that explicitly regularize this latent
space. So here, we just have an l one
loss kind of a reconstruction in latent
space, and then we rely
this exponential moving average on the stop gradient
to prevent collapse and kind of we hope
it leads us to dynamics that don't fall into
these, bad regions of the
space. But maybe alternatively, you know, we have
a shared encoder and we just apply a regularizer
here directly, and we enforce some kind of distribution
on our latent space. I think something like
this would be easier to understand and be much
simpler. But, it it does work well.
So that's what we use in this work.
And I also mentioned actually the masking
strategy how you drop patches makes a huge difference.
So it turns out if
you randomly drop patches throughout the video,
even with a with a high patch dropping ratio,
say you drop 80% of the
patches in the video, you end up learning
video features that are not very semantic.
An empirical observation. And so, it turns out what you have
to do is you have to mask out big
continuous chunks and blocks from your video
and, not just spatially, but temporally
extended as well. And so one
of the challenges we've seen is,
it's relevant for world modeling, is we wanna start going
towards kind of next state prediction.
And, again, you know, next state doesn't have
to be literally you know,
two hundred and fifty milliseconds or whatever control
frequency in the future. It could be a
representation of a future abstract state. But as you wanna
go towards something like next state prediction, unfortunately,
what we find is predicting kind
of representations of you
know, temporally adjacent or spatially adjacent
patches is just too easy. And so
it doesn't force the network to abstract away a
lot. Now, the intuition for why
this kind of training leads to
semantic representations is essentially as
follows. So the easiest way
for the network to simplify this task
is if it abstracts away the
input. So if rather than modeling every
single blade of grass in this video,
it tries to learn kind of an abstract summary of what's
there, that problem becomes easier.
Right? And the challenge is you don't wanna become too easy
such that it collapses everything to a a
non semantic vector. And so that's why you need
these kinds of two terms together.
And the masking strategy plays a role in kind of how
much your network needs to abstract
to make the prediction problem easier. So that's a bit of
the intuition.
Okay. And now, say we do this, how do we
know if we have good representations or
not? We need some way to evaluate that.
And so in this work, what we do
is we focus on frozen evaluations of our
video encoder. So what
that means is at test time, we take our video
encoder. We freeze it. And we
either process images or videos using
our network And we take those representations
and we try them on a bunch of downstream tasks.
So we train, downstream task probes, for
instance, for image recognition,
for action recognition, fine grained action
recognition, long video understanding,
detection, segmentation, and so on. So we look
at a wide range of tasks that require
understanding different aspects of the video.
So for instance, you know, something like kinetics
typically requires a bit more understanding
of appearance and,
kind of visual cues. Whereas something
like something something v two that dataset
really requires a fine grained understanding of motion.
So, you know, the datasets do test for complementary
things. And in the end, what we say
is, well, if our representation leads
to good downstream performance across
a wide range of tasks, then we've learned
a good video representation. One
of the other things we look at for instance is taking our
video representation, aligning it with an LLM, and
we also look at video question answering tasks.
So we look at some like perception test, minimal
video pairs and so on.
Now one would say, downside
here is what we actually care about
is prediction and planning. So
is a representation that is good at
image net classification or fine grained
action recognition or even video question
answering is that a good representation
space to be learning world models in? Is that
a good representation space for predicting
Is that a representation space that's easy to
plan in? And I would say we still
don't really know and I don't think they're
actually perfectly correlated. So towards the
end of the talk, we do have some experiments on
a real robot, at least to start evaluating this.
But I would say definitely a limitation is we need better
ways of evaluating representations that correlate
with how we wanna use them in world modeling for
prediction and planning. There has been some works,
you know, studying this. Obviously, representation autoencoders
related works. But think definitely we need a bit
more here. So
okay. And so if you drop a two, you know, there's a
two here, so this implies there was a vjepper
one. And so compared to V
Jeppa one, the methodology is not too different.
Really, the main differences are
we scale the data. So
we combined, we really scaled the video
dataset. We included images as well. We're trying
to make sure video and images using the
same kind of, mass prediction objective.
So the only difference is for images, you mask
out spatial temporal sorry, spatial regions.
In the video, you mask out spatial temporal
kind of tubes. But that that's
really the only difference.
So We scale the model size
And then we also train longer And then
we do this kind of high resolution and long
video duration annealing as well. This
turns out as quite interesting. So
I think the computer vision community in general has
seen a lot of benefit from training on high
resolution images.
Long duration video may be a bit less studied.
But the problem is it's very expensive. So it turns out
you only really need to do this for a little
bit towards the end of training. So what we do is
we do a a linear warm up of our learning rate.
And then a constant learning rate for the rest of training.
And we just train at a relatively
low resolution, you know, two fifty six or two
twenty four by two twenty four pixels.
And, you know, videos 16 frames. So
maybe about four second videos and so on.
And then towards the end, we maybe just do
a few epochs
where we really crank up the resolution and the video
duration. Significantly.
So this is quite expensive, but you just need a
little bit of that at the end when you're kind of decaying
your learning rate. And that also leads to
a kind of non trivial bump in, performance.
So here, I'm looking at average performance
across a set of tasks that test for
different things. So I've already kind of briefly mentioned these,
but something something b two,
diving, gesture, they all kind of test. These are
video tasks. And they test for kind
of fine grained motion understanding.
Kinetics, image, not maybe a bit
appearance based. One is image, one is video based.
And coin long video understanding.
So this is the average performance across these tasks.
As a function of these kinds of just,
design choices. So scaling data, model scaling, longer
training, and so on. So this
is a breakdown by task. So
here, in black
is Vjeppo one, and in blue
is VJEPO two. So already going from a VIT large
to another VIT large just by kind
of scaling the data longer training,
high resolution annealing, we already get
a big jump in performance. And I
think one of the things this indicates also
is you know, community has been focused
on learning from images for a long time, especially when
it comes to representation learning.
There's definitely work learning from video, but it's
think no one can deny it significantly much
less work learning from video than from images.
And, this just also shows kind of the
limitation here is our video
datasets are, much less mature, I would say,
than our image datasets. In a lot of ways.
So I would say this jump here from this black to this
blue it's really a data
an observation about data. So when
we augment our video data sets, we really scale the
video data sets. Spend a little
bit more effort here in curating the video data sets, and
we also combine that with image data
you got a big jump in performance. This is average task
accuracy across a bunch of tasks, so
image and video tasks. And
so I think there's still a lot much more work to be
done, on, the data side
for learning from video.
Then on the right here is a breakdown by tasks. So
you see ImageNet coins, something something v two
Kinetics. So in short, as we scale the
model, which is the x axis, we,
we see a good kind of improvement in, performance
on these downstream tasks.
Okay. So I also mentioned
one of the results we do is we evaluate our
video representation by aligning with an
LLM. And solving BQA,
that's, Khusstuf who kind of led this work on our
on our team. And,
we have some results where we fine tune the
video encoder. Along with the LMM, doing kind of
lava style adaption
we also have some results where we take this video encoder,
we freeze it, and we just train an adapter
and fine tune it along with the l m That also
actually works very well. Results
are not much, worse and we have those results in
the paper as well. In
short, you know, what we see is, okay, this VGAPA two encoder
you know, it's good at these kinds of downstream probes that
I before, image understanding,
video understanding. And for v q eight, it also does quite well. We get
state of the art on perception test, which is,
very interesting great dataset
put together by DeepMind on minimal video pairs
as well. So
these datasets kind of tests or these tasks
tend to test a little bit more for kind
of physical and spatial temporal
understanding. Which
we hypothesize is what's gonna be relevant
for what we're interested in, which is you know,
deploying these models on a robot. We wanna test the
kind of physical and spatial temporal
understanding.
One of the other things we look at the predictor. So
so far, I've only talked about the encoder
and the representations that we learn. But
technically, there's a predictor that can predict
mass regions of a video in latent
space. And so one of the other
tasks that we look at is action anticipation.
So here, typically, it's an established
benchmark. And the idea is, you know, given
a video, you have some kind of observation time.
You then have to predict what action is going
to happen one second into the future in the
video. One second is typically the
anticipation time used in these standardized benchmarks.
So what we do is we take our VJEPT encoder
and our VJEPT predictor, which are pre
trained, and then we freeze them. And then
we encode kind of our observation, the part of the video
that we do see, and we predict
the representations, you know, one second
into the future, And we take those and
we just train an action classification probe
on top. That given these
representations predicts, what action is taking place
in that representation. And that's
what we use for action anticipation. So here is
a video demonstrating the model. It's
actually quite interesting. Okay.
So model sees this, predicts, takes serial back,
Okay. Now
I should caveat okay, put cereal
bag into box. Yeah. It's quite
cool. It's it's actually not even that easy for a
human. To predict kind of what the next action
is gonna be. Just one caveat
about this video, the predictions are top five.
So this benchmark, you actually have to predict the top
five actions that are gonna take place.
And here, I'm only showing the kind of the
one from the top five that was predicted,
correctly. Okay? So
And, you know, the graph here on the right
is showing performance compared to previous,
benchmarks. So action anticipation
on the y axis you
have noun prediction. So here
an action is classified as a noun and a verb
pair. So typically,
people report
action performance for noun
prediction. So what object is
the person gonna interact with next?
And a verb, which is, you know, obviously, what is that
person gonna do with that object. So
those are typically reported separately. And then
the combined action, which is a noun
verb pair actually prediction,
is shown in the in the bubble here. I don't know if
it's fully I mean, it's a little pixelized.
But in short, towards the top
right of this graph is is good.
And the bubble size indicates, kind
of how well you do in terms of the combined
non verb pair prediction.
So I think even without seeing the exact numbers, you can
see v jappa two actually performs
significantly better than the previous state of the art
on this task. Which was a video,
language model fine tuned specifically
for epic kitchens. So it's quite interesting.
I would say even, you know, with this big
boost in performance that we get, there's still a lot of
headroom on this task. It's a very difficult task.
So there's still a lot of room for improvement here.
So And then the
other task we look at for evaluating the predictor
is intuitive physics. And this one is
really fun, quite interesting. It's inspired
from a lot of experiments, psychologists
and child development
scientists would do with children to understand
at what ages or what stages of their life
children have acquired basic intuitive
physics concepts. So as many of
us probably already know, you know,
children are born with very, very poor visual acuity.
And a lot of intuitive physics concepts such
as object permanence, shape consistency,
motion consistency, color consistency,
These are actually learned over the first
few months of a child's development.
And so these benchmarks are trying
to kind of test for similar things in machine
learning models, it's based on this violation of
expectation framework. So
the idea is, I'll just go
through the dataset. Or these datasets,
but they all kind of operate the same way. The idea is
you see a start of a video. So that's this kind
of shared beginning. So here is a ball.
It's traveling and a wall kind of comes up.
And now you have two possible endings
to the video. One
where the ball reappears. Okay. That makes sense
because it continues its trajectory. And
one where maybe I'll
wait for the wall to come up, but the ball disappears
and never reappears on the other side of the wall.
So they do these kinds of experiments with
children they kind of trick them
and they determine that when a child
is surprised then they've acquired
that concept. So for instance, if they
take an object, occlude it,
right, then they lift the
occluder, and the object is no longer there.
If the child is surprised, and you know, they track
this in lots of ways, then
they say, oh, they acquired this understanding
of object permanence because it violated
their expectation of what was gonna happen.
So we can use these similar kinds of
benchmarks to test our models and their
understanding of know, basic intuitive physics concepts.
So there's the intuitive physics dataset, grasp,
and inf level is a really cool one. Inf level is
not just, generated using a simulator,
but it's humans, you know, in the lab
doing essentially kind of
like magic tricks. That's how I think about
it at least, but maybe they cut the videos
and so I don't know exactly. But that's a cool
dataset. Very difficult and,
these datasets are actually quite old.
They've been around for a while. Infos
is from Emmanuel Dupu who works at FAIR.
I believe there's also a deep mind one as well that's quite
popular. So they've been around for a while, but
we're starting to see some progress on these benchmarks
using our models now, which is interesting.
One other thing to note is these datasets actually
have a very fine grained categorization
and breakdown of intuitive physics concepts.
So at the top of my head,
you know, the basic shape consistency, motion
consistency, color consistency, object permanence,
but there's, you know, a lot of categories.
And what we find is,
you know, our models actually perform well on some of these
categories, significantly better than the previous
state of the art. But some categories
that for instance involve collisions,
or deformation still have a lot of room for improvement.
Even gravity. Gravity is pretty good under our
model, gravity understanding. But,
there's definitely a lot of categories where there's
still a huge room for improvement. It shows these models are definitely
very far from perfect.
And so how we actually run
and test our models in this framework is
we take the start of the video We
encode it with the v jpepper encoder.
And then we ask the predictor to predict the representations
of the future of the video.
Okay? And so now, we have representations for the future
of the video, and what we do is we take these two
possible futures we encode
them with the video encoder. And
then we measure the error Which one
of these futures has higher prediction error
under our world model? And the
one that has higher prediction error is said to
be physically impossible. It's set to be the one
that violates the model's expectation.
So it's based on this, you do need these pairs,
but it's zero shot. We don't train on this data
set. And what we find is when we discriminate
between the two futures this way,
the model does definitely get surprised
when an object vanishes and doesn't reappear
on the other side of a wall for instance.
You know, we've also benchmarked,
LLMs on this, like video LLMs.
They all tend to perform actually quite poorly.
Maybe they'll, you know, they'll improve. And again, this is
a year old, but video alums
really struggled with these kinds of tasks.
Video generation models also really
struggled with these kinds of tasks.
So you can do something similar, but where maybe you
measure error in pixel space or maybe you
have some more intelligent kind of projection,
But, yeah, video prediction model struggles here. And so actually,
there's been some follow-up work from some
of our, and
who used VJEP
two to win a challenge at CVPR,
you know, last year. Essentially,
the challenge is measuring physical consistency
and physical understanding of video models.
And what they do is they use v Jeopardy two encoder
and predictor to provide a reward
signal to fine tune video generation models
to better kind of understand
physics and have less kind of physical violations.
But I think definitely there's still a lot of room to grow here.
And I don't know how I'm doing for
time. Okay.
So, got to the second part of
the talk really quick. Which is
maybe arguably the most interesting part, which is now learning
from robot interaction data.
And so here, we take our frozen v
jappa encoder. Unfortunately,
okay, perfect. We take our v jpepper encoder
we actually, we don't reuse the predictor
showed a few benchmarks of the predictor but unfortunately, that's kind
of a limitation of this work right now. We throw
away the predictor and we train a new kind of latent
dynamics model in the representation
space of our VJEP encoder. And we
trained that using sixty two hours of offline
unlabeled robot trajectories from the droid dataset.
So it's literally very little data. We
have no task information. We don't have any reward.
And then what we do is we take that model, put it on
a robot, with image goals and try and solve
tasks in the real world.
Now So the objective is as follows.
Really just a causal next frame prediction.
Given, you know, the starting frames of a video,
you encode those with the encoder. Condition
on a robot action, and predict the representation
of the next state. Going a bit fast for
time.
Okay. We use teacher forcing and a roll out loss
to live at teach the model to be better at
reusing its own predictions and running
autoggressively. And this
is the fun part, planning. So how do you actually
use this now to solve tasks on a
robot? Keep in mind, the model has no understanding
of kind of rewards, tasks,
and so on, or even goals really. So
we do is we take our current observation,
We encode it with our encoder. And
then what we do is
we simulate a sequence of actions with our
predictor. So here, we just use the cross entropy
method. So we just simulate trajectories from,
sequences of Gaussians. And we refine
them using the cross entropy method. And
at the end, we select the trajectory
that minimizes the l one distance between our final
predicted state and
the embedding of our goal image.
Okay? And that's the whole procedure.
Now so this is just an example. Here's a
start frame. Here's a goal frame. It's
actually quite subtle. Even for us, it's a bit hard to
determine what action the robot should take.
But essentially the action here is just moving towards
the camera along the depth axis.
And this is the energy landscape. So this is looking
at the error of the model as we simulate
actions in the delta x delta y plane.
Delta z, which is this up down motion here, we just fix
it to zero for, visualization
purposes. You can see the low energy
regions of the landscape, this kind of low this white
part, actually corresponds to the ground truth action
that leads you to your goal image. So that's a good sanity
check. It tells us that if we try and do planning,
with this model, you know, low energy
regions of the landscape actually correspond to actions that
lead us to our goal.
Okay. Some results. Cool.
We do some videos, pick and place,
two different, Franco
arms in two different labs, again, fully zero shot.
And just completely planning
from scratch. So there's no policy And so
on one of the limitations, we do have sub goals. So
these are the image sub goals. The first sub goal is grasp.
The second is you kind of see the arm is placed above
the shelf. And the third is it's placed.
But other than that, it's all kind of planning from scratch and
definitely something we wanna improve, integrate language goals.
There's no camera extrinsics. There's
no reward. And it's just from sixty
two hours of robot video from the droid
dataset. I think it just shows
really I mean, it's surprising that you can even do this
with just sixty two hours of robot video.
Without even conditioning on a task or a goal
or a reward. And it shows you really the power
of having good representations.
Now compare it to Cosmos,
video generation models,
For the sake of time, I'll skip this, but just saying
the video generation model is actually, if you
try and use this was Cosmos one. Cosmos
two was released then. There's been other models since.
But it's quite expensive to plan with these models.
And, you get lower success rate
across the the wide range of tasks.
And we also compared with, diffusion
policies, imitation learning at the time. So the
time Octo was the method that was out there and
supported image goals. Recently
we've evaluated the physical intelligence models and
the WAMS They perform
much better, but they still have their limitations.
But here, Octo, just fine tuning on DRIIDS with the
same exact amount of data, nowhere
near the same success rate as just
planning with a world model and spending inference time
compute.
And what you can do is also train a decoder So
you can make your predictions in Light and Space
and then train a pixel decoder to map
those predictions back to pixels. You
can actually visualize what your model
is predicting And so I believe
on the left here is the original video
On the right is the simulated rollout
from the world model. Again,
the decoder is trained just to decode the
representations, back to
pixels but the world model is doing the full kind of
action condition prediction.
So, in conclusion, I think representation
learning matters for world modeling. We should be asking ourselves,
what representation space should we predict in?
You know, based on Sergei's talk as well,
One of the reasons this matters is maybe we don't only
want one step prediction.
You can go beyond one step prediction with
hierarchy. So as you can learn hierarchical
representations of states, you know, this
one step prediction no longer really becomes
one step prediction. You can think about
incorporating something like successor features. So
there's work at, iCLEAR TD Jeppa
that essentially uses a Jeppa framework to learn
successor features. So that ties into the previous
talk. Does this mean VLAs
and language models and diffusion policies are
useless? Definitely not. You know, why
should we be planning from scratch? That doesn't make any
sense. I think maybe we should initialize our
planning with, policies.
And we also need a value function. Right? Clearly,
latent space, distance in
latent space is not gonna be a
really great metric for generalizing. So maybe
you know, you wanna learn goal condition value functions maybe
based on vision language models.
So I think these things sometimes
feel totally contradictory and it's either you're in one
camp or the other. But probably a lot
of these solutions come together in one way or another.
Even the latest kind of you know, pi 0.7
models, leverage world models, to generate kind
of sub goals. So and
then finally, you know, we wanna
learn better self supervised learning representations
and have ways to evaluate whether
these representations will be good for prediction
and planning. Not just for
downstream tasks. And, you know, finally,
obviously, we wanna use our world model to
create data for us that we can train on as well.
Okay. I think I'm out of time. Thank you. Awesome.
Let's thank our speaker
again.
So I think we probably have time for one really
quick question then. If, yeah,
Hey. Thank you for this great talk. So I'm
from a robotics background. Okay.
There are some information that is very critical
for robots that say how heavy the bag
is, which is visually you cannot tell.
We need something like a tactile sensors, torque sensors,
How do you think we can embed that information
into the Jupa framework so that
it can future benefit downstream manipulation
tasks? Yeah. That's a good question.
I think this goes in the general direction of wanting
to incorporate more modalities than just
video and vision. Vision is one. It's what
we started out with. But
I do think one of the challenges though
so it comes back to your representation
space. I think once you're learning
a world model in some kind of representation space,
your representations now can be agnostic.
They don't only have to be video representations. This
representation space could include
information about,
other kinds of sensors like tactile sensors,
you know, so maybe touch
Maybe there's lots of other data you wanna incorporate as well
in your representation space, but
off the top of my head, how I see this kind of fusing
is you got a representation space that fuses
some of these concepts together in this notion of state.
And then you do your regular world modeling as usual.
Now, the nice thing about, I
think, lots of these JEPA type of frameworks is
they're kind of modality agnostic. So here I talked about
video. But, you know, people
have used this for speech. People have used
this for time series data. People have used
this in a wide range of modalities. So I think what's promising
is when you have a learning method, that is kind
of modality agnostic, you can then
use it to learn representations,
of diverse kinds of, signals
including tactile, for instance, and learn to kind
of fuse representation space in which you can then do your
prediction and planning. Thank
you so much. Let's thank our
speaker again.
So our next speaker is, Michael Rabat,
who's a cofounder and VP of World
Models at AMI Labs. Michael's a
leading researcher in self supervised learning, representation
learning, and world models. Before AMI,
he was a researcher, leader at Meta
Fair. Also an associate,
industry member of Mila. His work focuses on
building AI systems that can learn robust representations
of the world planned through learned world
models, and ultimately act more reliably in
complex real world environments. That's thank Mike.
Testing. Hello. Alright. You very much.
So I hope you're all paying attention to
Mito's talk that just happened,
about V Jeppe two. I'm going
to try to pick up on some of what he was
talking about and talk about some sort
of extensions and and things that
come definitely builds on top of what Mida was
talking about just now. In particular, I'm gonna talk
a little bit about latent action models possible
extensions of the
VJETPA framework Mito was talking about, as well as going
beyond sample based planning like to
gradient based planning time permitting. We'll
see. I'll also try to see what we can do
for time. So just to, again,
recap and pick up the context from
the talk that Nido just gave, in the VJEPO
approach, we were aiming to leverage
actionless video to learn a world model in a sample efficient
manner. So the idea was we have
access to a large amount of observational
video, video that gives us state observations,
but no action information.
And then we leveraged a small
amount of this interaction data from from
robots Mito talked about. Only sixty two hours,
in order to train the action condition
world model that we could then use for planning
and deploy, to do very simple tasks
on a robot. Pick and place and and
things like this. So the
two things I wanna talk about today,
and again, also in the spirit of a workshop,
the way that Sergei said it, I think,
we'll try to talk at these in a
somewhat unpolished way, but hopefully to to get
some ideas out there. The first is to
ask this question of how could we maybe
get more take advantage of action
condition data more, not by actually
collecting more of it, course, we can do that too.
But also, are there ways we could try to infer
some sort of actions. Or maybe a latent
action model for some of the unlabeled data that we
have. That we can then use for training,
action condition model from the very beginning,
if possible. And then as
I mentioned, time permitting, I'll also
talk about a different planning method, maybe leveraging gradients
if we if we get a little bit of time there.
Alright. So the the first work is,
on action world models in the
wild. I wanna for sure give credit
to collaborators on this, and in particular, Contain
Garrido, who who led the work. As well as
Tushar and Nagarajan. Basile,
who might be here, who's presenting a
little bit later today.
Yeah, and and other coauthors. And this is work
was done before, at
fair and not at not at Amin.
So about learning latent action models,
I mentioned, the problem is that we have lots of state
observations, sequences of video,
What we would really like is lots of state action
trajectories. Where we know here's the observation
of what was happening in the world and also the action that
was taking place. And
so one approach to do this, if we had
an inverse dynamics
model, would be, you know, that inverse dynamics would say, okay,
given the state transition that occurred from
s t to s t plus one, infer
what that action was, a t, and then we
could use that
And the idea of a latent action
model often comes up as well. Latent
actions just mean that instead of trying to
well, instead of trying to work directly
in the, let's say, the raw action space,
of whatever embodiment we're thinking of,
let's embed these actions
into some general learned feature
space. So I'll say raw
actions were a t, a t plus one.
These these learned actions are gonna be my latence
z t z t plus one and so on.
And often, this kind of latent action approach is taken
if one wants to do things like leverage data
that's coming from multiple different embodiments,
different robot form factors, different
types of videos, egocentric where maybe
we know some information about camera poses and whatnot.
It also is used when you want to then
take a model and be able to use it across
multiple embodiments because you, you know, can hope
to map from that latent space back to
the concrete action space of the embodiment that you're
working with at any given point in time.
The figure on the right shows
pretty typical common setup for how all these
pieces might come together. And so,
what we're trying to do, and this might look somewhat similar
to the figures that Me too was showing too, hope
we can see some similarity there.
We have our state encoder
f here. You think of this as the v Jeopardy two encoder.
Actually, that's what I'll be using throughout this talk.
For the experiments I'll talk about later. That's
gonna be frozen. The same way that
Nida froze it for the v VJEPT two AC
model. We have our our
forward model, our world model, which
is trying to predict what's the next state condition
on previous state observations. And
in what Meito was you about at the end
there, a little bit quickly. But, in VJEPT two
a c, there we were conditioning on
directly on the action that was observed from that small
amount of robot data. Now, we're gonna condition
on some latent inferred
action z. How do we get that action?
Well, we have our inverse dynamics model
at the bottom here, g. And so that
model sees the same state up to time
t, and it also sees what happened at t
plus one. It's gonna take that information,
try to propose a learned latent,
and then feed that into our forward model for additional
conditioning to predict that next
latent state. You can already
see here there's potentially an issue in this
kind of a setup We have a causal
leak. Okay? What is a causal leak?
Well, our inverse dynamics model gets to observe
the future. But we want our forward model
to make predictions that are independent of the
future. And so, of course, there's a risk that
the inverse dynamics model just takes that
future state and essentially encodes that into our
latent, which it feeds as conditioning into the predictor.
It can cheat and it doesn't have to learn anything about
what's happening relative to the initial state.
And so to avoid that, we need to impose
some kind of regularization or conditioning
you know, constrain the capacity, create a bottleneck
on this latent variable, That's what I'm referring
to here is this is an additional
penalty regularization term e. And
so we're gonna talk about some of these different design
choices, First,
let me just mention, obviously, this idea of
inverse dynamics and learning latent
actions is not new. This is something there's
been quite a lot of prior work on.
I'll group it roughly into two categories.
In one category of work, it's
focused on learning discrete latence,
So, the type of regularization that
you impose is really to quantize or
discretize the latent space That's
the control that you have over the capacity.
The other class of methods that focus more
on continuous latence there
you need to come up with other kind of penalty
terms to to create your bottleneck on
that latent. I'll give you some examples in a
moment. One thing that has
been observed that I wanted to point out because it'll be relevant
to discussion right now, is,
previous work from Nicklin et al,
has observed that if you're trying to use
pixel level supervision to learn latent
actions, then it can be susceptible
to distractors depending on what types of videos
you're training on. Right? So so
for very simple videos, and and let me
let me actually before I jump into that,
let me say prior work in this
space often has focused primarily
on learning from fairly narrow or domain
specific data, which actually makes a lot of sense. Right?
We'll try to learn latent dynamics for
simple video games. Like, one one example you've
probably all seen was the Genie one model that
came a couple of years ago, which also
was learning latent dynamics from kind
of two d platformer games
so in that kind of a setting, you know, you expect
dynamics are fairly well correlated
with whatever actions that the the player
of the game was performing. Similar
in say, like, the, robot
well, manipulation videos that Nida was showing,
the scene itself is usually pretty static.
Objects on a table. It might be quite cluttered, but it's
still static. The only motion is coming
from the robot actions, moving the arm,
maybe picking something up. For the most part.
Navigation might be a little bit more complicated there.
You might think of, you know, an egocentric video
as somebody is walking through space.
But for a lot of the datasets that are available, even
for navigation, really the motion comes
only from the wearer itself. The rest of the surrounding
scene is fairly for the most part,
static. Okay. And so
of the questions we wanted to think about in this work was Right.
So we have video game data, things are fairly
simple. We have, you know, some of these robot
manipulation videos where again,
the environment is static except for the actions being
performed by the robot itself. I don't
have a third example here of a in the
wild video, but I want you to imagine something
that you would find wherever
you like to go watch videos, you know,
wherever whatever platform you like to use, or videos
that you might think of recording yourself. With
your phone, with smart glasses if you have them.
There probably things are gonna be a little bit more
complex. There's gonna be other agents
that are gonna be moving that you're not
you know, your egocentric self
or the camera holder
the camera recorder themselves, we're not, you know,
in direct control over, so we don't know their actions.
There might be other exogenous effects outside as well.
So for example, if you're taking
a video in a park and the wind blows
and the leaves on the tree rustle, well,
is that an action? You know, is
that something that we want our action variables to
to capture or, you know, what's gonna
happen? So in this work, we were looking
at this problem setting of what what can we
learn in terms of latent actions in in
the wild sort of as like a
broad experiment to understand what these these
latent action learning methods do learn,
there's no a priori embodiment.
Okay? We're not trying to condition on anything
in advance. We're just gonna throw in
the wild video at the model. It sounds crazy,
also thought it was crazy when Contain came to propose
it to me. It's like, are we gonna learn? What does
an action even mean in this context? I think the results were a little
bit surprising, and that's why I thought it'd be interesting to share with
you today. As
I mentioned earlier, so we also have
this causal leak issue that we need to to
solve one way or another. And so we
need to constrain the latent capacity in some
way. Through sparsity,
through noise, or through quantization. These are
the three most common techniques that come up in
the literature. Noise being,
so let you know, a denoising like VAE
type of of task. And
so the questions we wanted to try to understand are what
are the implications or sort of
effects of each of these different approaches
to constraining capacity?
And also, what do latent actions in the wild
start to correspond to? What do
they mean, when when there isn't necessarily
a reference embodiment?
Okay. We have this picture again of our latent
action setup. To be concrete,
I'm just gonna reiterate, think of this encoder as the v
jpeg two encoder for all the experiments that I will tell
you about today. We're gonna look
at these three different kinds of,
types of of
ways of controlling the capacity
And throughout, unless I say otherwise,
think of the following experimental setup.
So, have our frozen v j p
two encoder, and I'm going to train
simultaneously through back prop, my forward
model and my inverse dynamics model
changing the form of regularizer
that I'm imposing there, and also sweeping
for each of these, you can think of having a knob,
how much capacity
constraint do you want to impose. Right? So, for the noise,
how noisy do you want the denoising
task to be? How much are
you gonna crank up your l one penalty to try
to encourage sparsity?
And how big is the codebook that you're going to
use for quantization?
So now at the bottom so those
inverse and forward dynamics models are trained
on this YouTube temporal one b dataset.
The same thing Nido mentioned, was a significant
part of what was used to train VJEP
at two. And just to start,
let's ask what what are the
possible ranges of prediction error that I
can see? And I'm gonna measure error at this
point as just the l two distance in my learned
representation space.
I vary back and forth, that knob controlling
the amount of capacity, So
to give you some reference points here, the red
line corresponds to what if I try
to make predictions without any conditioning at
all? Alright? So this would be like constraining
any of these things so tightly that
my latency is essentially always a constant,
so it gives no additional information to that forward
model. Right? In that case, I'm just
making predictions based on the states that I observed up
till now, but I probably can't make very good
predictions, and so that's why this is quite high. It's around
point five. On the
other side, I could say what
if I have no constraints on the capacity
of my model? I let my latence capture
as much information as we can squeeze into those
values. And so that's quite a bit
lower. But might not be exactly what we wanna
do because of this causal leak. We'll come back to
that in a moment. And you can see
with both the sparse and noisy
types of conditioning, I can sweep pretty
well across that range. In
the case of the sparse models, I can even get some
prediction errors that are better than if
I put no constraints by adding some constraints,
which is be interesting as well.
But with the dense models, I think the main
takeaway here is that discrete latent
struggle with the complex scenes that we're looking at
in the wild. Think they've they've shown success
in other settings where the the data that the
latent action model was being trained on was in
a more constrained domain, But as you go outside of
that domain, where the controls aren't necessarily
discrete or easily discretized,
then we start to lose a lot of the the expressive
power in that latent space.
So Next obvious question
that you might wonder is what do our learned latent
actions capture? In particular,
am I how much should I worry about my latent
really encoding the future through that causal
leak? So to test that, what we can do is
the following experiment. We're gonna take a video
we're gonna make a very sharp scene
change. Alright? And so
then basically what I'm
saying is that the past gives
me no information about the future.
I'm taking clips from two
completely separate videos, splicing them together.
And so, the only way that
my, forward model could make
predictions in that setting is if
the latent is leaking the causal information about
the future frames. Otherwise, I should really
expect to see a big spike in the prediction
error when that happens.
So we can look at does that does that
error increase relative to the error I would
have gotten in if I was using my latent
to predict forward in time. Does this make sense?
We're gonna look Again, I'll show you these kinds of experiments
now where we look across the different ways
that we're imposing some regularization constraint,
and also we basically switch between two
settings, whether I let the model have low capacity
or high capacity. Here you can see,
when the model is
constrained more tightly so when the capacity
is lower, you know, so the starting off
point is gonna be different for all of the models
when there is no change. That's
because of what we saw in the previous slide that these different
forms of constraining capacity kind
of cause
different kinds of different amounts of errors. But
we can see that in all cases, there
is some meaningful jump
when we'd make these splices. Okay. So that's reassuring.
We can't be completely encoding
future frame.
And that there's less of a jump
when we give our model a lot of capacity.
Numbers tell you one part of the story. I think
also it helps to look at some qualitative
examples. One
example here, so this
is my ground truth setup. My splice
happens between this game generated scene of
a ball flying through the air
to a person standing on a rooftop
you know, with clouds, and interestingly,
the skyline kind of lines up between these two
images. So, if we have the high
capacity setting, you can see that,
when we decode back to pixels, I should have mentioned
also similar to some of the visualizations that
Mitra showed, we're making our predictions
in that latent v Jeopardy two space, but
we train a very simple vision
transformer model to decode back to pixels
Not trying to make pretty pictures, but just something
that we can see what information
is captured by those latents. So when we
give our model our latents a lot of capacity,
it actually is essentially trying to
fill in what that scene looked like.
It's a vision transformer, so it's not too surprising
things were petrified, so you see some sort of
blocking artifacts, similar to what you might get
from compression. If we were to give even more
capacity, then this would really it should
approach we're seeing in the prediction Up
to the the ceiling
that each of the two representations allow
us reconstruct pixel wise. They're not
designed for that. So may not actually be
there. As we increase the capacity
though, it's interesting we start to see
no longer are we completely transitioning the scene,
but we are trying to capture, you know, replace
the ball, a person.
So this is the kind of thing that the latent is
starting to latch onto, like, how did that
scene content change in this
particular way? It didn't need to change as
much about the background, per se.
Again, qualitative examples.
Another question we can ask is,
how do latence transfer? And we can think
of this in a sort of cycle consistency setup.
Now, we'll do the following.
I'll take the beginning of one video, I
will infer the latent actions from
that video. And I'm only
gonna carry over the actions, not the context.
To a different video. So I'll switch to a different
initial context and apply those latent
actions to the video to make predictions
about what would happen if I made those actions
take place in this other video.
Then, I will repeat the same thing. I'll take the
new video that I I predicted,
apply my inverse dynamics model again,
to try to recur recover what were the
the latent dynamics
in this new setup.
Plug those into a predictor that gets the same
initial frames that I started from.
And see how well you know, if I was able to
transfer these latent dynamics from one video
to the next, how much can I recover and essentially
this prediction should look as if
I were doing the same prediction on the original video?
Does it make sense? Cycle consistency
setup. So
So, sorry, before I show the qualitative
examples, again, we can look at this. Now, we're
taking our forward and inverse dynamics models that were
trained on one dataset, the YouTube temporal
one p, We're gonna evaluate this by
grabbing pairs of videos,
in two different data sets. So, in one case,
I'll grab pairs of videos from Kinetics
see how well I can transfer and get back. And
the other case from Recon Kinetics, again,
like Mido mentioned, that one is more
appearance based recognition of activities,
Recon is, egocentric video, somebody
navigating through an environment.
And so, the original here shows you what is
this LPIPs, now perceptual loss,
if I just try to predict
the video from its own latent
without doing the cycle consistency, transfer
is when I do this cycle consistency
and try to come back. And so you can see
there is some increase in the area.
We do lose some information by going
through this transfer, but it's not a huge amount.
It's not as if we were going back to like,
complete random or something. And I think it
helps to look also at a few qualitative
examples here. The interest
of time, I might just show you one, but happy to show you others
offline. In this case, we've got a source
video. It's a person walking to the
left across the screen.
The first transfer we're gonna transfer to
it from is now this game generated video, actually,
from the intfizz dataset that Nido
mentioned. There's a ball flying through
the air. We splice at this point in
time and now what I'm doing is on the top you see
what are the predictions I get if I directly apply
the late the inferred latent actions
back to this original video itself.
Here's what happens if I apply those inferred latent
actions to this video starting from this
context. Right? There's a person moving
to the left, for the rest of the senior,
so it thinks, okay, that corresponds to some motion
moving to the left, and then we start to see
the ball actually move back to the left. It
goes off the screen, and then, you
know, there's no more motion at the end of this video.
And so when we now run our inverse dynamics
model on this middle row,
try to apply it back to the original context
from our source video we see that
for these frames, we're able to recover the notion
that person is or
you know, main object in the foreground is moving to the left.
Until a point, and then of course,
now the person is basically stuck at the same spot
because there was no more ball on the screen, there's no
more motion, So I guess there's no more latent actions
to infer to push them further.
So in the interest of time, let me skip over
a couple of things here. Maybe let me
not skip over this one because it's also somewhat
interesting. So you can also look qualitatively
at what happens, try to understand in these scenarios
where there's a big mismatch between
videos that you're trying to transfer between.
So in this case, we start with that same per same video of
a person walking to the left, and that we're gonna
transfer it to a video where there are two people standing
statically in the initial context.
So when at the point where we transfer,
right, the motion was happening more on the right
hand side a little bit
unclear in the video, but it does appear that the
person on the right is the one that starts to move
a little bit more. Both of the people sort of turn
to the right, neither of them moves a great deal.
But you know, you could think of this as
roughly animating the person on the right
the other hand, it becomes much more clear if at the point where
we do this splice, I time shifted
my original source video a little bit so that
person was already little bit further to the left,
closer to the person standing on the left.
In which case, in the updated
video now on this transfer, it's the person on the left
that's moving. And the person on the right
stays static. And so what this seems to suggest
is that without any clear embodiment,
we haven't set an advance what kind of
actions we should be learning. Latent
actions of this form appear to capture
more spatially localized
transformations relative to the camera's perspective.
We can use these latents for control.
Again, how am I doing on time? I don't know. Okay.
Alright. Good. We can use these
latencies for control in the following way now. So I've
learned my my
latent forward
model the p that can be conditioned
on these learned latent actions,
I'm gonna take again a small data set
now I have state observations and the
concrete actions for the embodiment that I care about.
And I'm gonna train what we're gonna call here
an action controller. So this controller
takes in some context of what
was happening from the video feed, as
well as the action and is
gonna predict the latent. And we train this just
by regressing to the latent that we can get
through our inverse dynamics model from the same the same
data. We're gonna
take the same model that we the latent dynamics
that we trained on YouTube temporal one v, and now
we're gonna train embodiment
specific controllers for two different data sets.
One is the same droid, data set
from before, a single robot arm trying
to manipulate objects. In this case, we're gonna look at
very simple tasks where goal
move the arm to a specific location.
Recon, as I mentioned, is a navigation dataset,
somebody walking through the environment. A
bit harder because now it's not just about the movement
of the person, but every time they move,
there's something potentially new. Imagine when
you turn your head, new information that's coming
into the field of view that was exogenous
to the action itself. You just know that need
to fill in something new there.
What we see again, now as we sweep
this knob allowing us to control the capacity
of our latence, we get these curves
going back and forth for each of the types of
regularizations that we considered in the study.
And what you see is that interestingly
for JOYD, the gray dash line here is
a reference. Tells you what is the performance on
this planning task? What is the error
when I try to move the arm to specific location?
Using the v j p two a c model that Vito was
talking about. And actually there's an improved
model that we have since that worked by Basile. If
he's here, you can ask him about the details of
that. If you go to his poster later, I think
he'll he'll be giving a talk too.
That does quite better. And so what we see though
is that we're not reaching the absolute
best performance we know we can get if we train a specialized
model for that particular embodiment.
On the other hand, we're actually not doing too
far. By using this general latent
learned latent space. Which I think is also
quite interesting. And similar conclusion holds for the navigation
dataset.
So Let me
jump here and rather than read you the
takeaways, let me mention, you know,
I think you're summarizing some of the points that are already
made. In terms of there are some obvious
limitations and plenty of work that could be done
to extend this a bit further. One
is so far, we've been
assuming static information constraints. Right? We
our regularization don't turn the
knob during the video. Even though you might imagine
that as a video or as a scene
changes over time, it might become more or less complex,
and you might need different regularization That
might be something to think about in the future.
We were planning those examples
I went over quickly on the previous slide,
planning in the action space of the embodiment. So
again, running the cross entropy method, where
the search takes place the actual
embodiment specific action space. You might wonder,
could we do planning in the learned latent space
instead? It's a lot
harder because you might do planning, and your planner
might tell you to take latent actions that don't
have a good mapping back to the action
space of the actual body that you're working with. So I
think trying to bridge between these
is also something important to take a look at.
We could try to do end to end, you know,
training without freezing our encoder. I think there's a lot
of other natural extensions to be thinking about
in terms of imposing very specific
constraints, factorizations in this learned
latent space, say, to separate out
you know, actions due to
the ego versus stuff happening in the environment
and whatnot. But lots of interesting work to do from
here. If I have like
one minute, I'll try to say,
one other quick blurb about planning gradient
based planning for world models.
The approach that Mito talked about and that
is commonly used with a lot of inference time
planning for world models is something like the cross
entropy method, which is essentially a random
sampling or random search technique. A little
bit like Monte Carlo tree search, but now for continuous,
action spaces. And we know that our
forward role model is differentiable, so we would like to
do some kind of gradient based planning.
Reason why I wanted to give a pitch oops. I
don't say that. In the next slide.
So what are some of the challenges with gradient based
planning? In a nutshell, for many tasks
that we wanna perform, we the space
that we're gonna be optimizing in is non
convex. Right? You might need to actually move
away from your target if you need to go around an obstacle.
Actually get to where you're going.
The loss landscape consequently tends to be
not very well behaved, Not only is
it non convex, but you know, this is the
loss landscape induced by a learned neural network that
wasn't necessarily trained to be smooth, so it could be quite non smooth.
What we would like is something smoother and at the
same time something amenable to to optimization.
Doing direct gradient descent really does not work
when you're trying to do this. Right? And the problem really
is the way to think of it as an optimization
problem is I wanna optimize over actions,
to bring my state after t steps
as close as possible to the goal, where that state after
t steps is just what happens after
I repeatedly apply my forward dynamics
model. I start at my initial state, take my
initial action that brings me to my state s
one, take action one, and so on and so forth.
Okay? So
the reason why I wanted to give a quick plug for this
is because, the first author, Michael, who did
great work on this during his internship,
last year, unfortunately, he was supposed to be here to
present this work as a poster, and then I could have just
pointed you to him to go learn more. But
for visa issues, he was unfortunately not able
to make it. So encourage you still
to go and take a look at the paper. The
gist of the idea is we wanna decompose
this planning objective function in a way.
Gonna introduce intermediate virtual states.
Order to do that. I won't go through all
the details, but but we introduce these
intermediate virtual states and then we, in
enforce a sort of relaxed dynamics
through pair wise consistency. So now
I'm gonna say that my
if I start at state t and I take an
action a t,
my forward model would tell me I need to go somewhere.
Ideally, that somewhere should be s t plus
one, but I might let there be a little bit of
slack. I won't force those two to be the same, at
least not initially. Initial state
is given to me. My goal is fixed. Everything
else now we can optimize over.
The practical benefit here, which is really interesting, is
if you try to do this gradient
descent on just the the concatenated
model, sorry, the concatenation of
t forward steps essentially have you run
into the same problem you run into in recurrent
neural networks or otherwise. You're you're backpropagating
through time, you can get exploding vanishing
gradients. It's also a very challenging problem for that
reason.
Benefits that we have here now is that we've
essentially decomposed the problem in a way so
that the model evaluations are parallel
across time. They're they're decoupled.
And so, that allows me to paralyze
this implementation very very nicely.
There are failure modes. So there's
local minimum and saddle points in the state space
now. I've introduced to Slack. Way
to get around that is to add some noise. Can
look in the paper for more details exactly what that
means. Same thing is that the the
gradients can be somewhat sensitive, and so
what we do there, I'll just describe it in this figure
here. Right? The top shows you this kind
of serial planning approach where you're optimizing
over all actions at once. In the paralyzed
planning, what we're doing now is we're saying, I've got my
initial state, I'm gonna optimize over this
action, forward models tells me, okay, what would be the
state that I get to? I'm
gonna impose some cost to try
to pull what the forward model tells
me Is there close to this
other state as one, hypothetical state as one
that I would like to get to, I'm gonna be
optimizing over when I'm doing this
optimization routine. So this is trying to say these two can't
get too large. The other cost I'm
going to impose is I always wanna try
to encourage the model to make some progress.
And so I'm gonna add a cost that says,
whenever I'm moving, should be closer
to the goal ideally than it was before.
The final method that we get is more complicated and
I'll refer you back to the paper for that.
It ends up being several steps of this paralyzed
planning approach in this more relaxed setting
Occasionally with a few steps of the
serial it order
to sort of resynchronize things. The
interesting thing I think is, you know, it's it's not the end by
any means, but it gives us an interesting direction for
how to try to get towards more gradient
based planning trading off know, much
faster maybe much
more efficient planning that we can do then.
Let me just
stop here. You for your attention.
And maybe happy to take a question or two if there's time.
Awesome. Thanks again, Mike. So we have
time for two questions.
For the great talk. I was
wondering I guess,
you might end up when you are doing
the planning, to anchor encounter
situations that you have never seen or that are not part
of the dataset. So, what is
the bet here? Are you betting on generalization?
Or would you come up with another strategy to
mitigate this effect? A
great a great question. So what you're saying essentially
is you might end up taking
actions that bring you to states that your forward
model has not seen before. And, yeah,
this is a very common problem when doing planning with
world models. Not
something that we've directly addressed in this work, so it's more
of a question of the the quality of your world model, but
I think it could be addressed through this planning
approach. By adding some constraints that
essentially penalize the model for moving outside
of some sort of known distribution.
Often I'll also add, often we're gonna
be running this in a sort of a closed loop
manner So we'll plan out several steps, but we'll
only take one or two. That gives us the opportunity
to see how close was the predicted state I
thought I was going to get to. To where I actually
got to. That also can let the model slow
down if it's kind of getting off track.
Yeah. Thank you. That
was a nice talk. I had a question about this last
line of work. Is it related to MPPI and
trajectory based optimization? Which is
very common in robotics? So MPPI
is much much more like cross
entropy. The method of starting with random
sampling, essentially Here, there's, the randomness
comes in in terms of noise that we add,
the states in order to perturb them. There is
some randomization. But I think
it's different otherwise. We're not maintaining
a distribution over these states. Otherwise
But in general, I mean, that community
they have continuous states. They have condition continual
actions. Often, they assume the world model is known,
but, like, you're assuming it's known in this line of
work. The planning problem for continuous control
is super well studied. Yep.
So borrow whatever the
soda is from that community? Our experience
so far has been those methods are quite effective
if you're doing your planning in a relatively low
dimensional space. But we're also
interested in potentially doing planning in much higher
dimensional state spaces. That's where
because they're sampling based, sort of
crystallizationality starts to kick in. Yeah.
Cool. Thank you. So I think, we might
take the rest of the questions okay.
Yeah. So let's thank Mike again for
a really cool talk.
Hello?
Hello? Can you hear us okay?
Yeah. I saw a note saying say
something. From Snai Lab. But
I guess it's okay now. Yeah. Yeah. We're
all good now. Thank you.
Yeah.
Everyone. Thanks for joining us again for the next speaker
session. We're joined by Jiajun
Woo. Who's assistant professor of computer
science at Stanford University. And
by courtesy, assistant professor of psychology.
Jad Joon's research bridges computer vision, machine
learning, robotics, and cognitive science with a particular
focus on how AI systems can understand
three d scenes reason about physical
objects, and dynamics, and build richer
models of the world. Before
Stanford, he was a visiting faculty researcher
at Google Research and he received his PhD
from MIT. Let's thank
Okay. Great. Yeah. Thank you for having me.
Let me share screen.
Does it work?
Okay. Yeah.
So nice to be here. Sorry. I couldn't be there in person.
It's just really a bit too far. So and
can't really have enough time for travel.
So nice to be here to give
the talk at this world modeling workshop.
I'm gonna talk about how we can understand because I work
on computer vision. I'm gonna talk about how
we can understand the visual world,
through you know, of course, we want to use all these
data driven methods. The foundation models has
been trained on
the Internet data. But also at the
same time, you know, the world is not just, like,
there's something that's underlying there in the
physical world. Right? Just like you know, there's spatial
continuity or there's self similarity
as in, as in attention methods,
There is something that's underlying the physical world,
which we call these kind of physical intrinsics.
And we'd like to explore how we can
combine or integrate data driven
methods, like foundation models and their
intersection in their how they could interact,
with these underlying physical properties of the
So that's what we say, understanding visual worlds
through physical intrinsics.
Okay. So we see pictures. We
see, like, a of a lion, for example.
And then we understand that,
there's, underlying physical wall there, underlying
physical properties like object has geometries
and textures and materials.
And they may move they may move. The process of taking
these underlying physical properties into
render the pixels is you know, simulation or rendering.
And, the goal of our a lot of things that we're
doing is know, we're trying to derender
invert that process, right, to get ideally a distribution
of these physical object property from visual
data. So
the issue or the challenge here is, you know,
unlike and videos or language where we
have so many annotations, We really don't have annotations
on these intermediate representations.
So there the question is, you know, how can we actually solve
this problem without having annotations
on these inter on these, physical
properties that we care about? So
the first idea is, you know, we can take
these, it's the first idea
is while we don't have annotations on
these, physical object properties, you know, we
do have some kind of knowledge about how they're
supposed to interact with each other. Right? So we
can actually use them intermediate
representation. Think about an encoder decoder frame
framework, like an auto encoder. Then you have
all these raw data. You can encode it
into these spherical objects, where which
you care about you don't have
annotations for. But then you put them together,
with you know, we call this, like, differential
simulation or rendering. So you can
take these underlying simulation, physical properties
You can rerender or resimulate them, and
think about how they may compose
and reconstruct the visual input. Or
some sensory operations that didn't even have to be visual.
Right? So then although you don't have super visions on
the intermediate representations, you can use
this reconstruction loss as the self suit version.
So that, you know, you can think about it as
having smart devices. You can actually
get these underlying properties that you care about
for free, including of the geometries and
their dynamics and stuff like that.
So during training, you can train in a self
supervised way on large connection of Internet videos
and data, And during testing, you know,
you can even just take the first half and you can go from a
single image and try to a lot of things out of it.
Right. So
we started exploring this idea since a few years ago,
and the first example actually a very nice
example we did is we try to learn images
from a single image. In any case of a single
image, we have a bouquet of 50 different roses.
And we ask, you know, why are these objects look kind of
similar to each other? But we they're different,
but we know that they actually belong to the same object category.
Right? So we realized, you know, okay. They
all make they're all just different realizations of
a role, of the of the category roles. Well,
I can give you something I can show you something else like a
and you realize that would be a different object. So
what does this name of rows really indicate?
And our observation is the fact that they share
the same name is an outcome
of they actually have an
underlying shared distribution of their intrinsics.
And there's underlying distribution of object geometries
and texture, which you'll try to model. Or try
to discover. But then,
once you every instance, every object you're seeing
here, you can think about it as a sample from that distribution.
And then you put that into a certain poles and
there's certain lighting conditions. And that's why you realize
all these roses look kind of slightly different.
Right? So by taking that assumption,
modeling this kind of a forward process about
oh, how the sampled object geometries
and textures works like avidos,
can be put through a differential simulation framework
that integrates these sample geometries and textures
with lighting and poses going to differential rendering.
And by enforcing the fact that the final
outcome, you know, in some sense, this is a reconstruction,
is similar to your
operations in a single image. You know, you can
force these similarities in different ways. And back then,
we just use a discriminator. Right?
And it allows the system to actually learn
the underlying distribution of object
geometries and textures and materials and verbals.
And allow you to actually do so much even just by
learning from a single image. So what you can
do is you can go from a single image and
then you can render roses from different viewpoints
under different lighting conditions, as in the second
two bottom row. And also, you can
simple different sample from the distribution
so that you can get multiple instances of
roses that has different geometries. You
feel like, oh, the color here is not best. You know, first,
this is done like almost four years ago
now. But second, everything we're
doing here is learning from a single image. Right? There's no.
We don't even use any pre trained models. We're training
models from scratch just from one
single image. You can see that we can actually get so
much from so little. Right? Of course,
now you can use protein diffusion models and stuff like that, and
that would make things a lot better.
So this was done by Ying Shi, my PhD student.
And since then we have done a few
explorations, extensions You know,
one is we can go from a single object categories to
multiple object categories. So instead of training on a single image,
we train on Internet scale of animals.
And here, we train on Internet scale of images and
videos of 100 different categories of,
quadruplets. So you
can see that we can have one model
that is able to train on these images of the quarter paths.
And during testing, you can go from a single
image to to reconstruct the geometries
and textures and materials of these animals
and you know, so just
one model that works on 100 different object
categories without assuming annotations to any
of them. And you'd also discover, actually, we
call this the skeletal structures or
the form of these animals. So
we call this a lot of paper, a learning three d form of the
web. And this was done by my PhD
student, Zijang, and Eiyu, who was back then my
postdoc and now assistant professor at Cambridge.
Okay.
So
for this kind of a paradigm, you know, for a while,
we feel like, oh, yeah. It's kind of very interesting that we
can do actually really require better very
little supervision, and we can do a lot, you know,
about getting properties of our
objects. But as I'll say as I'll
say later, later we realize that
there's also some constraints or issues that you may have
with this kind of a
pipeline. But most recently,
we realized know, even with this kind of a simple and
possibly somewhat constraining pipeline, you can still
are more potential to discover.
So one thing that we have been doing very recently is
how can we go from static objects to
to dynamic objects. So before we have been
saying, okay. We can discover geometries and
textures and materials of these single objects.
And, you can make it work on many, many
different object categories. You can sort of discover
the form or the skeletal structure, but you're
not really trying to capture capture for example,
you know the skeleton of the animal, but you're not really
trying to capture what are possible ways that these animals
can move. So in this most recent
work, we're trying to go from static to dynamic
objects so that we not only want to discover,
like, the hierarchical structure of the multiple parts within a
single object, but also possible ways that a
single object can deform. You know, in
this work, which is led by Chen, who is my current PhD
student, and, called neuro object kinematics,
Our goal is to take a single three d objects
and try to discover this thing we call
as, underlying, you know, kinematic space of the
objects. Right? So you can encode the objects
into a latent representations that captures
its kinematic space, which is, like, the possible
base a and d form. You can sample from this
latent distribution. Now you're not getting different geometries
or textures but you're getting the different ways
that objects can can can deform and
can behave. You know, you can open the lid, you can close
the lid for this for this box.
And the way we do it is surprisingly
similar and simple. It's it's still like a
encoder decoder framework, and you can see that it's actually
just going from the simple framework. You actually get really get a
lot of it. So the idea
is, you know, you have a conditional match, which is like
a set of objects. You have a ground
truth deformation field. Which you can get
by, you know, training, you have a collection
of objects and possibly some of
their deformations. They're mostly synthetic.
But You can set it into a conditional
VAE that try to encode this deformation
into a latent distribution. Right?
And at the same time, you have a separate
conditional encoder that just only take the conditional
match, which is set of objects that encoder into
also a distribution. You know, because during testing,
during inference, you wouldn't have the ground truth deformation
of the object. Right? You only have a
steady mesh. So this is, like, your inference.
But then during training, you train both models, and then
you have two loss functions The first loss function is
you deform, you decode
this latent distribution, and you want this, reconstructed
deformation fields to be close to
the to the ground
truth. So this is like a reconstruction loss.
And the second loss is you have this,
regulation, KL divergence that
minimize the distribution that it output of
the conditional encoder. And the VAEs. Right?
So during testing, you only have the top half,
and you can encode it. You can still sample
from this latent distribution, which has been trained
to approximate the possible distribution of the deformation
of the optics. You can sample from the deformation,
and then you sample from the distribution
get a deformed hot spot deformation of object. Right,
doing test the image from a static mesh.
It turned out that this model is actually also very, very
general. It works on many different object categories. You
can go from
setting objects. Like, this is a
office scene. Right? You can see the single model. Is
able to turn steady objects into,
possibly interactable objects by capturing
the possible ways that it can be deformed.
And this is a different scene of, I think,
a bathroom.
You can see that we can model how the tap,
can be turned you
know, the the
the laundry machine can be opened, toilet can
be opened, and stuff like that. Okay.
So I'm gonna skip this.
This is a kitchen scene.
But people may say, okay. Then here, every object
is kind of a perfectly model. Right? Synthetic.
So every object is perfect. So so, of course, if
you train a lot of these kind of perfect matches,
at least you should be able to generate some other
perfect matches. But what about in the real world?
Right? So in the real world, so so we tested
our generation by actually having
this as one of our authors, a student,
who was trying to use an iPhone to do three d
scanning in the room. You can use iPhone, right,
has this kind of a now this VR toolkit that
allows you to actually have a three d scanning of
the room, but the quality is not very high. As you'll
see here, after the skin, you can get these kind of
very bumpy meshes. But it turns out the model
also, you know, while being trained on some purely cellular
data, also generalizes to real world
and can capture the possible way that these
objects like, you know, microwaves and stuff like that can
be deformed so all the
other can see artifacts here are the output of the iPhone.
Right? So this is not our problem. But despite
you're working with these kind of meshes
of relatively low quality, the system is
able to generalize and model imagine
how these objects can be interacting with. So, of
course, next step is we think about how
this, reason possible interaction
can be useful for, you know, robotics.
And this is a different scene of
office. Again, you scan office with an
iPhone, you get a message, which is not very high quality.
For the laptops, swivel chairs, monitors.
And the model is able to generalize and
predict how these objects can be interacted with
Okay. So this is idea one,
right, with about how these intrinsic can
be used as a indirect biases for self sufficed
So you have supervision in the middle, but you can
model, you know, sometimes through new networks, sometimes
through differentiable simulation. By
assuming you you have some knowledge about
how these object properties are supposed to interact
with each other. That mostly is
reconstruction loss. Can actually get the properties you care about for
free. But it it comes with
a number of challenges. You know, there really is is
because you you have to assume you have the simulation. Although
the simulation can be in your network, or
it can be differential simulations, you know, it
still come with a lot of constraints because
it has to be differential. Right? But there are a lot of things that
we don't really know how to make differential. And
second, it has to be pretty accurate, but there are a lot of simulations
that are not very accurate enough you know, because of, you
know, let's say, complex fluid dynamics that we
can't really simulate them very accurately.
Or maybe we we are able to actually simulate them
pretty accurately, but they're very slow. We're
putting them into the training loop so that we also
require simulator to be very efficient. Right?
So all these constraints they put together, then now eventually
maybe they're all solvable. But right now, you
know, you realize that idea seems to be only working
on relatively simple scenarios. Right? Single
object, clean background, and stuff like that.
So how can we actually generalize it a bit
better? And this is also
a time that, of course, these data driven models like,
video foundation models and the vision language models
are getting so much better. So we thought, you know,
instead of just having intrinsic biases
for self supervised learning, is it possible
maybe for us to leverage a bit more of these
foundation models, which you can assume they're like this giant
framework that has already implicit in
all these encoding and decoding for you. But if they
can capture and generate beautiful videos, they
must have learned some about object geometries
and motions. And if this is your target, these are things
that still discover. It's a separate question about whether you
wanna discover them or not. But assuming this is still
something you wanna discover, how can you
get as much out of it as possible by
distilling foundation models? Right?
So we have been work doing a few works in
this direction. So
I'm going to just, very quickly highlight
some examples. I think due to time constraints,
probably wouldn't have time to go into the details. But
also by Chen, you know,
he did this follow-up to our rose paper
a sense I want to discover what really belongs
to the Roles of its intrinsics. It's including
its geometries, textures, materials, but also
a very important part of the roles
is, you know, any enemy objects is
their lifespan. Right? So you can see how the rolls
will grow and will wilt. And,
in terms of pattern formation, this will be a generalization
of our earlier framework on modeling steady
roses. But I think in this work,
approach we took are totally different. You know, we have
a little bit complicated mechanism about how
we can distill from vision language models and
also image of the diffusion models to try to
get other geometries, textures, and materials in its
lifespan so that you can see it from different viewpoints.
Under different lighting conditions, but also over, a flight
span. At different time
points as well. Yeah. And also,
it's not only applicable to roses. You can model other
dynamic objects such as the bread being
baked. And you can see you know,
you can the bread at different process
of the at different time timestamp of
the baking process. Under
different lighting conditions, see it from different viewpoints
and stuff like that. Yeah.
So most recently, also led by Chen,
and also some other collaborators, we have
extended this framework not only just steal
these dynamic objects, but also,
the possible interactions of multiple objects.
So for and we also added a bit of language conditioning
so that you can go from a steady scene and not only
to to predict how objects will move,
and their their kinematic sequences,
but you also try to model the possible
kinematic interactions of multiple objects, such
as a robot arm and a block. You
can say going from a static scene,
you have a you have a robot arm
and a block, you can have
a text prompt that say, when you now see
a robot arm picking up a brick, So
we're able to distill possible kinematic sequences
of both the robot arm and the brick
so that you can see the
picking up process. Some sense, they could give you,
like, free training data. Right? Free. It's like don't even have
to collect demonstrations because you're just sitting demonstrations
from these pretty deep rooted models. But
the things you're just seeing is actually a state sequence.
What you can directly use for imitation learning. There's
no action at all, but there's it's just the state sequences.
And here's a different example. By
destination. You can in
from a steady mesh of, the basketball,
and then you can see, okay, the text prompt
is the basketball hits the rim and bounces
away, and you can see the interactions between
the basketball and the and the target.
Hello. I think maybe Zoom
sharing is bit let me see
if I can
Yeah. I think I changed the settings so that
videos hopefully now looks a little smoother.
So
And here's a different example of
a cat, jumped on
a cushion. Right? You can go from a static scene
and to still state sequences and see how the objects
may interact with each other.
And for this work, we actually later did explore
how they be useful for robot manipulation.
So we can go from a static scene of a
human and, piece of cloth and
say, okay. Can we generate, possible
sequence of the robot floating across?
And it can actually generate,
sequence state sequences like that, and you can actually extract
dense trajectory for the object motion and use
it as guidance for imitation learning
so that the robot can follow the state sequences that
allows, the objects to be,
deforming the same way. Right? So you can see
on the right, there's actually a real robot. So you can see
this is like hallucinated demo that allows
robot to learn from for free.
So the robot can learn to afford the cost as
well.
And here's a different example. Of
how such situation of possible human object interactions
of, like, closing a laptop can be
used as demonstrations for the robot to perform the same
task.
Yeah. So this is done by Yanzhou who
has incoming Stanford PhD student and Kartik who
is a master student at Stanford as well. I think he's going
to do a PhD student at Berkeley.
Okay. So finally, let
me talk a little bit about how we can model these
kinematic sequences so we can go from, you know,
this is like everything we talk about has been kinematic
since it's like stay sequences. It's like hospital
objects can deform and they can move but it
is not dynamic in the sense it's not responding
to actions. You know, so so it only gets
state sequences. So we want to
really also model dynamics in the sense that we can now
do action condition dynamic prediction So you
get a three d object. You're not only predicting the how
how how would it look like if the robot is trying
to pick up the block, But also, you know, how the block
is supposed to behave if there's, like, actions
put on it. Right? If I push the block, what's gonna happen and
stuff like that?
Yeah. So problem we wanna solve here is you have a
set of scenes, but then you want to make it interactive.
In the interactive in the sense that you can apply different types of
actions, like you poke the different parts of the flower,
and you get a different output.
Right? So this is our model output.
And here, it
can be also interacting many different ways.
So this work was done a bit earlier, and
it was kind of a also kind of simple. So
I think it's a nice example to illustrate how this decision
can be done. Later, we have much more complicated
mechanism, but it's a simple example about how this
is possible. So the biggest challenge
here is once you really pursue photocopier optics,
you know, to action condition predictions, you will need
physical object properties like stiffness. But unfortunately,
it's probably very difficult because if you randomize
line them, and it turns out the object, you know, is
not homogeneous. A different possible object had
different physical properties. So if we randomly assign some
heuristics, it's not gonna look as good.
Right. So in this work, which is led by
Cohen and my PhD student, and Tian, who
is a PhD student at MIT,
we did something that's very simple. That is how much we can
get out of these video models of our physical
properties. You have these three d representations. You can
project into your image. You can send this image
into video generation model. You can an ITV model
that you get a reference video. The reference v
video is supposed to look very realistic.
But it's just a video. At the same time, you
can have a physics field, which in this case is like stiffness
field or Young's modulus field, which you try to
add twice. You can let it go through a differential
simulation, and it's gonna give you
some simulated video As I said, if
your estimation of figure properties is not very accurate,
then the simulated videos are also not going
to look very realistic. But
now you do have a reference view, so
you can actually compare it to you. You can compute the differences
even just directly in the pixel space. You
can back propagate the loss to update your
estimation of the pixel. So Right?
So this is an extremely simple pipeline actually
allows you to directly extract
meaningful physical properties from a video diffusion
model that has been pretrained. And again, this
was two years ago, and so now, later, we have much better
video diffusion models. Have much better decision
techniques, including some for some of work that
I showed prior. So But this
is, I think, a simple demonstration about how
extraction of these clinical copies can be done.
Through these kind of more or less similar decision pipelines.
And here we have some more results,
you know, I think the differential simulation pipeline
we use here is particularly good for
soft bodies, who have more results on soft bodies, including
the flowers, plants,
hats, cables, and stuff like that. Yeah.
Yeah. So later,
we also extended a framework, led by
Yuan and Cohen, who are my PhD students.
So that we model not only soft bodies, but also fluid
fields so that we can go from a single video
and we can try to reconstruct its geometry,
appearance, also a Fiddick field. In this
case, the Fiddick is velocity. It's no longer
there's no YAMCS module as for for for
for gas, but there's a velocity field.
And then we can render the fluid field
from different viewpoints, and we can also predict,
you know, what's gonna happen with,
external perturbations, like if there's a wind coming
from left.
Including most recently, we also extended this
kind of framework to model interfacial dynamics
between liquid and, and bubbles, so
gas and liquid. So you can model we
can go from the video You can up
reconstruct the appearance. You can see it from different
viewpoints. You can also try to model the
interfacial velocities, between the
bubbles and the liquid.
Okay. So finally,
you know, we have this idea of is it
possible for us to integrate everything?
Right? Because, you know, we've been talking about soft bodies,
rigid bodies, flowers, liquid, and
stuff like that. But the real world is really
complex. You know, there are, like, objects of different states
of matter that you got interacting with each
other. Granular objects, liquid,
rigid bodies, and stuff like that. So is that possible
for us to have one integrated
system that go from a static image
and you can turn it into three d. You can
apply different types of actions. You can do action condition
predictions of objects in different matter. There's rigid bodies,
soft bodies, liquid, and stuff like that. So how
can we do that? Right?
So in this work, which was now the half
a year ago, and half year ago is a long time
and a lot of things would have changed. So
but we sort of implemented it and we have
a follow-up too. In this work that was done half
a year ago, we were able to turn a static
image into interactable three d scenes
that you can apply different types of actions.
You can, yeah, you can, see how the
honey is actually dropping on the cake.
You can see what happens if there's a wane and the
hat is gonna go away.
You can see the interaction
between the movement of
the soft bodies like the mushroom and
the smoke.
And what's gonna happen if you push down, like,
a one gas? And the glass
is gonna break? So
Right.
So the way we do that is still you know, we try to
as I said, there are two different programs. One is to have
simulator in a loop, but it has some problems. And we sort
of already said, and it's actually very difficult
to have perfect simulation. And
second, I think, you know, if you have
if your input is static image, then
you don't really have a full state information. Right? State estimation
problem itself is very, very difficult. You
know, we spend actually quite some time talking about how you
can even just get a Young's modulus from an image.
Or from a from a from a static scene, right, by decision.
So having a full state estimation is also very
difficult. But there are some good things about
simulator is it sort of supports action condition predictions
for free. And
video models are, in some sense, the different
types of word models, but they're very complementary
because it's very general. It can
it has very strong visual parts that can complete
observations, and it can deal with things that are
missing informations, occlusions, and everything.
But it doesn't directly take actions as input.
Right? The actions that video models can take as
input, in some sense, as what we've seen before, is
you can take language as input, You can say language
as actions, and I can I want to, catch
you jump on a cushion? You can
take maybe simple navigational commands as input
like going forward, backward, turn f or right.
But it's very difficult to take specific,
you know, I would say, very fine grain
actions at input, which are required for robotics, for example.
Because you simply just don't have that much data. And eventually,
maybe this will also be solvable. But right now, there's
you just don't really have enough fine grained
data for for fine grained actions.
So our idea is is it possible for us to sort of
together a two so we have a hybrid generative
simulators. So we
can say, you know, we said there are two paradigms. In the second paradigm, we're trying
to distill these physical properties.
Out of video foundation models. But now we're trying
to put them back in the sense that they're not
only decision targets, but they also serve
as ways that you can interact with these foundation
models. So right now, they're like the interface you distill these
physical properties from these video models, but
again, you use them as interface to make
your video models or any kind of generation models
much more controllable, right, so that they can
behaving in ways you want. You can change physical properties.
You can do action condition predictions, you
can do counterfactual reasoning, you can do all these things like.
So the idea here in this paper is you have
a single image, and you want to let
build this kind of a hybrid Jensen simulator that put
together a physical simulator a video
generation method. You can first reconstruct
the image into three d, which will be imperfect,
There'll be a lot of, like, missing information
and occlusions. But even
with this imperfectly reconstructed three d
scene, can let it go through a physical submission, and
and it will give you some coarse results.
Right? You can see, oh, the smoke is coming up, if
there's a wind, You can see a lot of visual artifacts
as well as physical artifacts.
So in some sense, it's like intuitive physics which
is not very accurate. But you can
use these intuitive physics as guidance
to produce, for example, a generated video
And the video is supposed to look a lot more realistic.
Right? Here, you can see the video looks much better.
But the video itself doesn't give you the underlying
physical state representations. So
finally, you can re optimize the underlying
physical representations approximate these
videos or sometimes even multi view videos.
That allows you to have the best of both worlds,
a sense that first, get steel
because it's output of it. You have to maintain a
four d representation. You can move around.
Can see things in four d. You can change your cameras. You can do
action condition predictions. But also,
because this has been optimized against the output
of video generation methods, they're supposed to look
a lot more realistic. So this is like you really
get the best of both worlds as you can see in the top right. You
know, I can see how the wind is coming up. It
interferes with the shoes. It's visually realistic. It's
physically possible. And it's supposed
to be a lot more general too. So now here
you can see the interaction between, like, rigid
bodies within each other, granular objects,
soft bodies, cloths, and rigid
bodies interacting with guests. You know.
And you support action condition predictions like going from
the same static scene so you can apply different actions
and see, you know, same scene how it's going to respond
to a different actions.
So this was done by my PhD student, Zijan,
in COVID as well.
And most recently, we have been
trying to even further improve the process
by thinking about, you know, by having a physical simulator
in the loop is still kind of very heavy. So
and these kind of optimization really takes a long
time. So it's not possible for us to even simply get
rid of that final activation step?
So that we use physical simulation as guidance
but then to use it to condition video
generation methods, nowadays, with things like self forcing,
you can make these video generation methods a lot
faster so that we can actually do action
condition predictions for generating
videos and sometimes multiple videos.
At a much higher closer real time actually
has 13 frame per second, so which is basically real
time. Right? So here's a demo.
That we can go from a static scene. You can say, what
are the actions you would like to apply? And
you can see the system in basically real time
generates possible ways that the object can be interacting
with. Like,
As well as here's a different scene.
You can see how the objects can be generated
turning to three d. And, actually, into
yeah. The physics simulation turning into three d
produce possible ways that the object can be interacting
with. And eventually, you have close to real time
generation of a video of the interaction
output. So this opens a lot
of different possibilities, such as you can do in
close to real time, the possible ways that a robot can interact
with objects and the outcomes. And this is, like, different type
of, like, word models, and then
out we're not really taking actions with output.
So it's not like a word action model. It's an action condition
real time action condition
video generation methods that now
we're actually actually exploring
applications for robotics. Okay.
So I think I'm out of time. So I'll just wrap up by
saying you know, we have been thinking
a lot about how we can
model the physical world. And, of course, you want to use
these very powerful data driven methods.
But we also want to think about, you know,
what are the structures that you need?
You know, it's not I think it's more less and
less about the structures can be useful
by building them into the systems. But it's really I think
it's more about humans, you know, how the structure can be useful
for humans humans For us,
to predict or for the robots to predict
a reason what's
gonna happen and to interact with
these foundation models. Right? If we can only interact with
these foundation models with language, that seems
very limited. So if you can have a lot of
different ways of interacting with these
foundation models, maybe based on physics, It can
also support a lot of these kind of kind of factual reasoning
that opens a lot of possibilities.
Right? So we're trying to do a visual understanding of word modeling
based on this universal verbatim, and causal.
I think causal is really important because it allows you to do
different types of predictive models and
counterfactual reasoning. So based on this convolutional, universal,
and perpendicular principles, and
can be teaching linear foundation models so that you can use
reading the wild data. And we can
integrate synthetic data as needed because synthetic
data is actually also generated by these code
principles. So that's how physical simulators work.
And it give you, as I said, interpretability
of, you know, what properties you're interacting with
and controllability for both video generation and
eventually for wall interaction. And
has a lot of applications for robotics in there.
Thank you. Okay.
So in the interest of time, I think we'll just take one
question before we move on to the next speaker. If someone
wants to
somehow I cannot hear you. One second.
Can you hear me okay now?
Hello?
Can you hear now? Yes.
Now it works. Yeah.
Can you hear us now?
Yes. Yes.
Okeydoke then. I guess we
can move on to
Yeah. We can thank our speaker and
yeah. Thank you. Great. Yeah. Thank you. Bye
bye. Thank you.
Okay. So it's my pleasure to introduce our
next speaker, Kevin Murphy, who's a
principal scientist at Google DeepMind. Kevin's
a leading researcher in probabilistic machine learning,
Bayesian modeling, and artificial intelligence
more generally. And is widely known for his
influential textbooks, including machine learning and probabilistic
perspective, and probabilistic machine learning.
His work spans generative models, reinforcement
learning, robotics, Bayesian inference, and world
models with a longstanding focus on building
AI systems that can learn
reason, and make decisions under
uncertainty. That's, welcome, Kevin.
Hello, everyone.
For the introduction. So, I'm gonna talk
about code
synthesis for agentic decision making.
There's gonna be no images in this talk.
It's pretty different from a lot of the talks
we've heard. That are focused more on robotics
and embodied AI. And I'm quite interested in those things
but I'm just not gonna talk about them today.
So I'm gonna mostly focus on symbolic
and textural environments. And
the primary motivation for
looking at code synthesis so
my my my driving goal is I wanna have agents
that can learn quickly in new environments
from very little data. Preferably,
you know, self generated data.
But maybe it's spoon fed to
them, but it's small sample size.
Because we know, like, if you have enough data
and you have a good simulator, you know, RL can get
superhuman But where does that
simulator come from? That's sort of the big question. So
my there's two hypotheses
we explore in this work. One is that to
be sample efficient in decision making in a
new environment, you need to learn models.
And if we wanna learn the model itself,
a sample efficient manner, we need strong
priors. And so we're gonna leverage
code synthesis which
LLMs can do because they've seen a lot of prior
data And code is quite good
for representing certain kinds of world models.
Okay. So that's sort of the pitch. So this is joint
work with many people Carla Wenzelkin
is in the audience. He's a co author,
and it was led by Wolfgang Larrick, who's
back in Mountain View.
Okay.
Okay. So, the I'll maybe watch the
time. Do I have until 02:05?
K. So, the standard approach, here's
a few standard approaches to using LLMs
for decision making. Right? So you have the
environment, It emits
observation, The LLM
about it. Emits an action,
the action's taken in the environment and repeats.
So this is just the LLM as policy
approach. Okay? Pretty standard. Now
another thing you can do is you
can say, I don't wanna have an LMM
in my inner loop. It's too slow. So
what I'm gonna do in an offline setting, I'm gonna
collect some trajectories. Maybe they're
given to me by a human expert or
a random explorer or maybe I self
generate them. And then I'm gonna try to fit
some kind of model to that data.
Or I'm gonna learn a policy on that data.
And then, once I've learned
this policy, that's just a mapping from state to action.
I deploy that. So the LLM is used
in an offline setting to do function
induction, and then it's thrown away.
Okay? So that makes it faster at runtime.
So this has been explored a lot. Coder's policy
works very well.
We're gonna approach take a
different approach. So we're also gonna consider
this offline setting where we're given a small
number of offline trajectories. And we're
gonna feed them into the LLM. And we're gonna ask
it to generate a function But in this case,
the function is not a policy. It's
a world model. So what is a world model in this
talk so, a world model
is an action condition state transition
distribution. Okay? So that's sort of the
classic definition.
And if the states are partially observed, we'll also
need an observation model. So like
in a POMDP. Okay? So we're gonna,
magically learn that. I'll explain how we
do that. And this function will be represented
in Python code. And
then once we have it, what do we do with it? Well, we
do runtime decision planning. So
we do MCTS. So we're mostly gonna look at game
playing. One player and two player
games. And, MCTS
is sort of a standard way to do planning in these
discrete action settings. But
And I a little asterisk I added after hearing
Sergei's talk. So the these are, like, classical,
one step ahead,
millisecond by millisecond world models.
I know we need temporal abstraction I've
worked on that too. I just not
talk about it today. These are turn taking
games. Right? So it's reasonable to focus on
single single tick. The second
approach I'll talk about later in the talk
actually keeps the LLM
in the decision making loop. But it
adds a code based harness around it
to try to improve its performance. So
it's rather than throwing LMMAs away completely,
we do some sort of hybrid of code and LLM.
So that's the auto harness work that I'll talk about later.
Okay. So why
use walled models Why
not just use the LLM as a policy?
Well, the problem is that, I mean LLMs
can be slow like I mentioned. But also they're
not necessarily very good as policies.
It depends on how familiar the
environment is with to the, to the
pre training set. In particular, in multiplayer
adversarial games, you will rapidly go
out of distribution because you have to respond to
the other player and they're gonna drive you into into
a part of state space that you've never seen. So
these are very non stationary environments. And
the LLMs start going off policy very quickly,
and they're pretty bad. As players.
Even in familiar games like chess,
So and of course, you can
use, you can fine tune the LLM using RL,
but that's really slow. So,
okay. So we don't wanna use the LLM as a raw
policy. We could use it to synthesize
a code based policy. And that
will be much faster, of course, because we're just running Python
code in the inner loop. And that can
work well for simple environments. And in fact, we've done
that. But for multiplayer games,
again, the issue is that,
any sort of policy learning thing
will struggle in a very non stationery
environment when you're when you have an adversary, you need think
strategically. So it's very hard to distill
all of that look ahead search into a parametric
function even if it's a code function. Right?
So you need to do test time reasoning.
So we will in fact be learning policies
to help we're gonna do tree search, MCTS,
We will use a policy to help guide the search.
We're gonna do runtime, test time
thinking. So that's the
sketch here at the bottom. Okay. So that's
why we're, focusing on warm models is
to get better performance in adversarial
settings in particular. And and,
improve sample efficiency. So how
do we do it? So we're gonna have a bunch of
trajectories. Let's say, think about like a
100 rollouts of a game. And we're also
gonna get a text description of the
game that will describe the rules in
more or less detail. Obviously,
in the limit and then we're gonna feed that
into an oracle that will learn a transition
model that's represented as python code. And I'll
explain this induction algorithm
in a minute. So you can think of
two extreme cases. Right? Suppose there's
no data and there's only text. This is just text
to code generation. Well studied problem.
Right? The other extreme is there's no text. It's
just trajectories. This is world model learning.
Also well studied. So why do we do
both? Well, there's a couple of
reasons
First of all, you know, language
can provide a source
of information that's maybe easier
to acquire than experimental rollouts.
It might already exist in the definition of a game
or something. And you can also do
sort of consistency checks, so you can induce a model
given text and induce one given trajectories
and they should be mutually consistent. And
then you can ask the LLM to describe its gameplay
and check that it matches. So you can do
this sort of three way symmetry consistency
check. We we didn't do in this
paper but one could and
and that's sort of future work.
Okay. So how are we going to learn this
function? So you can imagine,
this is just we could use black box
optimization. Right? Anything. Bayes
Opt, random search. And
whatever you like, genetic algorithms, If
you think about it, I mean, these things have been done for decades.
You just write down a black box score,
And in our case, the scoring function
will be how many, transitions in
the empirical data did you correctly predict under
your model. So we're assuming deterministic
models. Stochasticity
enters via the action. We're gonna have a chart. This
is standard in game theory. I'll have a picture later.
But in game theory, you have a deterministic
causal world model in the sense of Judah Pearl, and
all your stochasticity is
lifted outside of the environment
outside of the world model. It is injected from outside
coming from a chance player, also called nature. Right?
And that is your source of entropy.
So the model is when you marginalize that out, you
get a stochastic model. But the backbone's deterministic.
So you can check equality. And we're gonna
be using initially, at least symbolic
world models. So this is literally
element wise equality. So you
could do that. The problem is, like, if you just get a scalar
feedback signal, it's really, really inefficient
to learn. And this is why RL sucks. Basically.
So and it's so un it's so
needlessly inefficient. I
think Andrei Kaparthy said, this is like
drinking supervision through a straw.
Right? Like, why would you just look at one
number? Why don't you look at what the player actually
did? And look at the predictions and look
at the reality and look at where the errors occurred,
not just how many errors occurred. So
you can represent your feedback
in text form, and then you can use these sort
of text gradient based methods
So, for example, you know,
in let's say tic tac toe, this is the world state
This is the action that you take and this is what you
expect to see. Right? And you can render this in
some form like a JSON structure.
So way we represent our score function is a
set of assertions. And we can
The numerical score is the number of assertions
that fail. Which we wanna minimize.
But when an assertion fails, we can just use
the Python compiler or run time
environment to give us feedback on which
assertions fail. And then, we know not just
where how many mistakes, but
which mistakes And then you just feed that into the context
of your LLM optimizer, and
magic happens. Right? It
can actually look at the information and
learn much, much more efficiently than pure
black box optimization. Okay. So
how do we do the,
this text based optimization? There
are many ways you can do this. We didn't
innovate here. We just leveraged prior work.
So the main method we used is called REX.
From this paper by Tangerel. And the
idea is it's it's tree search through the space of
programs. So a node is a partial program.
And the score the value of the node is like its
score. And we're trying to improve it. Right?
So we use Thompson sampling to pick a node
from this tree that will solve the explore exploit
trade off. And then once we sample
a node, then we feed it into our LLM
based improver like
many of other people do, So you just use
this function. You roll it out of the environment.
You collect some data. You compare it to the,
it compares accuracy. Then you have
a critic that scores it. This is the unit test
I just showed you. You feed all that signal back
into the LMM. And you say, hey,
please, LLM, Make yourself better. And
then you get a new function out, f prime's stick
it back in the tree. And then you repeat.
Rits and repeat. So this is pretty standard.
You could use, like a population based
search. Like alpha evolve. So this
is a slide I took from one of my colleagues.
It's the same kind of idea. Right? You get
a scale of feedback, scalar number,
and some text feedback. Give it in the LLM,
and the LLM does some sort of mutation thing.
In this case, it's like a population whereas
our approach is like a tree based search.
Initial experiments show
we seem to find the tree stuff to be faster
than the alpha evolve.
So that's what we went with. But doesn't really
matter. So anyway, there's
some magic algorithm
that will take trajectories and text
prompts or the description and then
spit out a function And we can measure how
accurate that function is on the training data.
And in these, so
we have in this paper, we have
five sets of perfect information or
fully observed games. Three
of them you might have heard of, Backgammon, Connect four,
and Tic Tac Toe. And then there are two
novel variants that we create that are sort
of mildly out of distribution.
So generalized tic tac toe, I think, has a larger
board. And generalized chess changes
some of the rules. So this is just
just to make sure the LLM hasn't
memorized everything already. Because in the limit, you might
imagine, hey, we're playing backgammon. It says,
okay, I got it. I can take it from here.
It doesn't do any learning. It's just memorized it.
Right? In fact, it doesn't do that.
Like, it doesn't zero shot the code. Maybe the new models
do. But it can get pretty close. So
had to test it without a distribution game as
well. Anyway, it's able to learn.
It perfectly fits all the training data that
and then the key thing is, okay. How well does it generalize
to predictions on novel data and it generalizes
pretty well this is an offline
test set and then you can check its
prediction as it as it's used in deployment time as
well. And it doesn't take too many LLM
calls to learn these. It's a pretty simple environment.
Okay. So we've got our world model. Now what
do we do? We just drop it into MCTS
and and and turn the crank.
So for those who don't know MCTS, so you're searching
through state space. And so,
there's a standard algorithm where you pick
your current root node you choose some
successes to expand, you simulate
forwards using your world model, and then you
end up at a leaf and then you have to estimate
the value of getting to that leaf, which will be a
not usually a fully end of game, but some
some depth down. And, this
can be done with Monte Carlo rollouts from the leaf or
using a value function. We also learn a
value function using similar methods.
And then you propagate that information back up the
tree and that tells you the value of doing the
action at that root node. Just
pretty computationally expensive You really
wouldn't wanna do MCTS on top of an
LLM. It'll just burn your budget.
But it's fine to do it on top of a piece of Python
code. So it's, you
know, it's pretty efficient. And you could
do, like, SMC if you want a parallel version of this.
Oh, yeah. I mentioned in passing, we also learn
a value function So rather than so we don't need
to do these monicolor rollouts at the end.
With just TD and, or supervised
learning. And we also learn a policy
using standard policy improvement methods
which guides this Instead of just randomly exploring
actions at each node. We use the policy to propose
a set of actions. And then the tree
the search algorithm is essentially a test
time improvement operator. That gives you
lift over the base policy.
Okay. So, we did a little
bake off. So I was showing here the accuracy
of the world model. What we ultimately care
about is the performance of the player. So,
these are two player games. So we consider
three settings. So one is when you
compete just versus an LLM
policy. So we're always and we
have these five games. So green means we're always winning.
The other is when we're, against a
a win by forfeit Oh, this is interesting. So
here, the LLM doesn't even know the rules.
The LLM loses because and and this will be important for
later. The this is Gemini 2.5
pro. So it doesn't even know the rules
of backgammon. So it just takes
illegal legal moves and dies in pretty
much instantly. So, we just win
by default. So that's not so interesting,
but it's interesting for later in the talk.
Obviously, we'd beat a random player most
interesting thing is this middle section.
So we compare essentially to an oracle
which is MCTS that has access to the
ground truth world model. So the true
simulator. Right? The the actual game
which is an open spiel And,
we can actually match it Sometimes we
even beat it. But we're basically
learn wall model is, you know, competitive with the
true wall model. As viewed through the
eyes of the induced behavior.
Okay. So that was a warm up. Like, that
that's pretty easy because it's kinda like supervised
learning. Right, in symbolic space. With
a black box function optimizer.
What when it gets cool is when we have
partially observed multiplayer games.
So think like poker or something.
So this is a graphical model to show what's
going on. So these are the states which
is, you know, it's a vector of
primitives. Right? It's structured. Like
the the hands that all the players have in poker,
And these are the actions of the different players. So
a zero is the chance player, like the dealer.
And then a one is a player one, and,
I'm player Sorry. The
indices here are time steps, but there's gonna
be multiple players And
then, when a player takes an action, it
changes the state of the world including their private
hands and, you know, the public
shared deck. Then there's an observation that's generated
which is it could either be private to them
like the dealer gives them a card and they see it.
So they get private observations. Or
it could be common knowledge when everyone sees it as
I placed on the table in the middle. Okay.
So what's private and what's observed depends
on the game. It's like part of the definition. In
any case, so this is a multi agent POMDP.
Okay. So what we wanna do is we wanna
learn this beast. Just from observation
streams without seeing the hidden state.
So there are gonna be three scenarios we're
gonna consider. So, so far, in part
one of the talk, we saw the state and we saw the actions.
And we fit this the world model and that was like
supervised learning. Just minimize
the next step prediction error. And at
runtime, what we did is we saw the states
and we saw all
the previous actions and we just,
chose decided what to do next. Right?
So it's fully observed input. Okay. So now
we're gonna move to this partially observed world.
But it's so hard we're gonna break it into two steps.
So in the open deck learning
scenario, we're gonna see,
my so index I superfix
Sorry. Is that? The
thing upstairs? Super script?
Super script I is the
index for me, player number I.
And downstairs are time indices. So
I'm gonna see trajectory I is I'm gonna
see my observation stream
my action stream, I'm gonna get privileged
information and see the true world state as well.
So this is like playing poker when you see everyone's
hands. Right? So this is what
you often do when you're learning you're teaching someone a new
game. Just to make it easy. This is
now fully observed. And so we can
basically use exactly the
same machinery as before We learn the
world model in exactly the same way.
So predict new s given old s.
And now we also learn an observation model
that maps from the hidden state to the observed state. And that's
just another supervised learning problem. That we
solve with tree search. Okay?
And then at test time, but
it's interesting, because at test time, we
don't want to assume we have access to the true
world state. Because that's not the nature of the
game. We only see your own personal
observations. So that means we have to
learn one more function, which you call an inference function.
Which what it does is it takes my personal observation
stream and it imputes the
actions of all the players since
the beginning of time. Even if I didn't see
them. Including the chance player, which is all the
entropy in the game. Right? In general,
this is a inverse problem. It's ill posed. There
might be many action sequences
that are consistent with the data. But I I
only have to find one of them.
And then, once I've imputed
all of these a nodes, they become visible
nodes in my graphical model. And
since the backbone is deterministic
transition model, I can just roll
forwards deterministically and then I
can predict what I expect
to see. Right? So
this is very much in the sort of utopel causal
model. Scenario. Where all
your stochasticities upstairs, like the twin world
stuff, those those who know about causality,
sort of figure out what the hidden causes are
then you can do counterfactual experiments. Right?
So I can predict what I I expect to see
And then, I can use that as a loss function
Yeah. So, here we go. Make a new loss function.
It's a bit more complicated now. I'm gonna impute
all the missing actions. I'm gonna
roll forward in the hidden space,
and, estimate what
the state should be. Then I'm
gonna push my late my inferred state through
the observation model and check that it reproduces
my observations. So I'm
fitting three functions, IF and M,
and I'm doing it by checking,
that the states match. So in the
open deck setting, I can check the
state transition model directly. I can
check that states map the observation directly.
And then this is indirectly checking the inference
function. Through this sort of cycle consistency
setting. Okay? So that's
the OpenDeck setting. So in that
setting, if we
we consider five different games, these are
five imperfect information games.
Three of them you'll know, bargaining, l'Duc Poker, and
gin rummy. And two are brand new games
made for this paper that are out of distribution
So Quadranto and Hand of War.
And on the training set, you know, it's working pretty
well. Doesn't work so well on gin rummy.
And on the test set, it's starting to you
know, flake a little bit. This is a hard game.
For various reasons. And you can see, like, we set
a cap of 500 LLLM calls.
It just can't explain the data
with with the prior it has and the
it could be that the trajectories weren't interesting
enough. That's future work is to,
like, have do online
learning and have a teacher try to teach
in an efficient way, but we didn't get to that Anyway,
so it's working, but it's starting to crack a little
bit. But this is
like the quality of the model. What we care
about is the quality of the player. So in
the imperfect information setting, we
don't see the ground truth. We don't want action to perform.
So what we do is we infer the hidden
state and we, by drawing a sample
from our posterior over hidden states, and then
we just do MCTS with this
posterior sample. So this is called information set
MCTS. It's a standard method.
And in the usually in the literature, they assume
a wild model is known like in AlphaGo.
And then they'll assume a perfect Bayesian
inference algorithm so the posterior will be exact
And then you can prove that this does the right thing. It's like
Bayes optimal. But now we're setting we don't know the model. We
don't know the inference function. So everything's just
approximate. Nevertheless,
it works okay in
some cases.
I'm not going to try to read too much into these
patterns. But we get,
three wins, one draw and one lose.
Okay. Relative to other strong
players. So not as easy
as the OpenDeck setting oh, sorry, the fully observed
setting. Okay.
And now, the final, the
final act is we we rip off
the training wheels. And now all you see is
observations. And you never see the
hidden state. And this is obviously what most people are interested
in. Right? So you can think about So
the way we tackle it is a generative
model. Right? So that you can think about it like an
auto encoder. I see my observations.
I encode them into hidden state. And
then I recreate my observations.
And I check that the recreations match the
truth. Just like autoencoders.
Reconstruction loss But it's reconstruction
loss via a model that has a
very special form So it has,
an inference model that
goes the ink is an encoder. It has a dynamics
model and it has a decoder. It's kinda
like Jepper. Except we're doing it
in except for
two big differences, three differences,
is symbolic. The functions
are code. There's no back prop.
And, and it's a generative model. And
and with in this case, because it's symbolic,
we use zero one loss like I showed before with
the unit tests. So here's the This is how
we do the unit tests in the closed deck scenario.
It's kinda like the open deck scenario
except we can't check for a quality in in hidden
state space because we never see the states. We don't know
what they are. Right? So we do give it a
helping hand. I think it's lost in the notation, but
we do give it the initial hidden state. And that
sort of defines the symbols of the game.
So you you and also the prior text
says we're playing poker. So it's free
to invent anything at once.
So it might know that players have
hands and cards. But it doesn't
know anything about strategy or move board
positions it can invent any concept at
once, whatever the code does. We never
check if it's valid because what's valid
anyway There's only usefulness. Right?
As the French philosophers would say, it's just utility.
Maybe that's English you philosophers. Anyway,
we just check that, it represents
what we see. All we can possibly check.
And then of course, so this
we're drawing a single sample You can show
this as like a lower bounds on the log marginal
likelihood. So it's like a Monte Carlo elbow.
And But we don't
strictly optimize with respect to that. We optimize
with respect to the Monte Carlo approximation.
In terms of the model performance,
it works, you know, in terms of fitting the data, it
works you know, three times out
of five. Four times out of five, arguably.
But it's not generalizing that well
so it's really starting to
creek. Then if you use it with information,
say MCTS, you know, we're waiting
two times out of five. So it's you
know, it's it's a much much harder problem and and it's starting
to to break. But, anyway, that's
as far as we got with that line of work.
So I'm gonna switch gears a bit now.
So I thought, you know,
I think it's an interesting line of work.
But it has a few problems. We really wanted
to go beyond these board games and card games. They're kind of
boring. We wanna do you
know, text adventure games and negotiation
games and ultimately like three d video games.
Real time simulation games and all of the cool stuff
that people actually enjoy playing. And
it's really hard to model those things, to
write down a world model, let alone to learn a world
model. Obviously, there is a world model. If you think about
three d video games, that's what
these games video the the the
companies create. Right? They use Unity, there
is a model. We know what the model is. But
it's really hard to reverse engineer that from data.
Especially in a sample efficient way.
And it's not a few lines of Python code. Right?
It's like hundreds of thousands of c code.
So, modeling everything just seems
hopeless for certainly for
text games and even for these visual games. And,
you know, overkill. Like, I don't
really, even as World Mobile's workshop, can
shoot me later in the panel I don't
think that's boiling the ocean. I don't think we need
to. For good decision making.
So, you know, we could just use the LLM as a policy.
Right? Why not? That avoids
all this well modeled stuff. Maybe it's implicitly
a world model, as Sergei was saying earlier. But
one issue with policies, I mean, they're slow like I
said before. But also they're not very good players,
especially in adversarial games. And
sometimes, they don't even play legal moves. Like I
showed you results earlier on backgammon, which is very
simple. And even chess, there's there's like a
billion examples of chess on the web.
And Gemini at least 2.5
pro was still making illegal moves. If you look at the
casual competition, like that's why it's always
losing. It's because it just it takes an illegal
move and instantly dies. So
what we wanted to do is to
try to improve You're given an
LMM policy how can you make it better? Well, you could fine
tune it with RL. That's expensive. You could use a
bigger model maybe you can't afford
that. Or you can build a little harness
on top to improve it. So a harness
is just any piece of code that you stick on top of
the NLLM to make it it better. That
code could be another LML. It could be a hierarchical
controller. You know, think about Claude Code. What is
Claude Code? Is this a bunch of code,
Python code or Java, whatever, TypeScript
code written on top of the core LLM. So
that's a harness. Right? So we wanna learn that
harness. Now, what we do in this work
is like a baby step. The harness that
we learn is gonna be very simple.
We're gonna learn it
using the black box optimization method I described
before, tree search. And then what we're gonna
do is we're gonna wrap the LLM
in the loving embrace of this harness and make it work
better. So specifically,
specifically, what we're gonna do the following.
We're gonna give the LLM the current
observation history and say, pick an
action that you think is good. And then
we're gonna ask our harness saying,
hey, do you think that was a good move or not?
So the harness is like a second opinion. And here
we're just not trying to assess whether
it was strategically good, but merely
is it a valid move or is it gonna
is it illegal? Is it instantly gonna
kill you? And so, a validity
checker, you can think of as like a partial world model.
It's only predicting one feat one feature about
the next day. Which is
did you die or not? Seems like
the most important thing to learn. Right? You can learn
that very quickly from from supervised
learning. Right? If you take actions in the
world, and, and you die,
because you did an illegal action, you've
got instantaneous feedback. There's no delayed
reward. So you just stick that in your
replay buffer and you do this code synthesis
story. And it's like supervised learning again. But
it's like a very weak supervisory target.
Anyway, suppose the Hana says,
bad idea. That's an illegal move.
Then you just iterate and you keep trying
until you either find a valid move or
you run out of turns. And if you run
out of turns, you pick a random move or you die, whatever.
So that's one eyed incarnation. There are many other
ways, of course, of making harnesses. Right?
But this is like the simplest thing you can do.
So And the way we learn this function
is exactly the same previous
work. So I won't go into it.
It's just that the scoring function instead
of checking that you predict the next state, you
just predict whether you die or not. Right? Was
it a valid move or not? But it's it's That's
observed in the data, so it's straightforward.
Okay. So,
even though this is very, very simple, it
works quite well and
we tried on a 150 different games from
Textarena. So basically, every
game on Text Arena except for some that were
sort of open world
negotiation games where the action space is unbounded.
So these all the games we consider all
have finite action spaces. They might
be multisymble. Right? They're not they're like strings
of variable length, but they might be
like in this tic tac toes you know,
it's represented
You know, this here is like a little string that might be
multi token. Right? But they're not arbitrary
conversations because they're very hard to evaluate.
Anyway, so we took a 150 games from
Text Arena and we made them harder by
actually removing the
the some of the rules from the prompt.
The rules usually tell you what's legal or not.
And then it's kind of trivial. We removed
that and we force the agent to discover
what's allowed or not. And this is like a
proxy for an agent that has to
go into some new environment to figure out how to use
tools without, like, die electrocuting
itself. So, or at
least you're allowed to do that but not many times.
You do learn from feedback so you have to fail a few
times. But hopefully, you learn very quickly.
So, anyway, there's a wide variety of games. You can see
that they're pretty rich. Really
pretty hard to model using pure Python
code. And,
anyway, we can take a week base model
like Flash and stick the harness on top
It becomes a perfect player. It makes no illegal
moves. And then it starts
outperforming So it certainly beats vanilla 2.5
flash, but it will also beat 2.5 pro
And, you do
enough work, you can beat GPT 5.2
high reasoning as well with this approach. This is
with Flash. So it's like, hundreds
of times cheaper.
So, and then the final thing I'll show is a
little demo that, Xing Wa was the first
author of this code auto harness
work So he put together this demo
recently. So what you're visualizing
is an LMM chess player on the left.
And every time it makes an illegal move, you
see big red x. And that feedback
is sent in. So here, we're learning the the function
online. It's not offline anymore. You
That feedback is sent into the, the
harness learning algorithm.
And it's synthesizing code on the fly,
And then, it uses that code to
filter out illegal moves and then you just continue.
And you can see that the illegal move rate, like, rapidly
drops to zero. So it stops making
illegal moves. You know, whether it's playing good or not
is up to the LLM, but it's at least not wasting
time on things that are illegal. So
Okay. So last slide.
So these are the standard approaches of using LLMs.
And I just presented two alternative ways.
Both of which perform code synthesis. So one
it generates a world model and then we do MCTS.
Oh, I forgot to mention in this paper,
this is at the main conference. With the
world model, we do MCTS
for planning at runtime. We also did work
with model based RL where we learn a policy
offline using Dyna. Just so it's
just like, you know,
the dreamer line of work except our world model is
code. Instead of a neural net.
But it's it's in the diner family.
And that's a lot faster at runtime because you don't
need to do search. So that works fine for
single player games and grid games. But
for multiplayer adversarial games, it's really hard to learn
a policy. That's why AlphaGo does MCTS.
And then the new work I presented
at the bottom the code that we synthesize is
a harness. So it improves the LLM
rather than replaces the LLM.
Okay. Thank you.
So we have time for a few questions. If anyone
so actually, I had one which was
regarding the, when you add the harness on
top then you learn a computer program, which effectively,
like, filters through the
outputs. I know
some people in my lab who research,
like, inductive logic programming. And I
kind of sense like the
the the rules guess, that
where it says this is an illegal move. This is an illegal
move. Could see that being a
case where the model could potentially
learn very kind of granular rules that are
more specific in instances of
much broader rules. And I was wondering if you
noticed did it kind of generalize itself naturally
where, say, in chess, it would say,
don't move your knight forward. But instead,
the rule at learns is if you're in this square that
I saw And yeah,
ahead of that. Tend to evolve? Yeah. Right. Right. So
this is actually a key question. So what's stopping this
f being a lookup table that just patches? It's like,
If something goes wrong, you memorize it, never do that again.
Not very useful. So there are two things.
The sort of the implicit
prior that the l o m wants to generate sort
of simple code. Not look up tables. We don't
explicitly penalize that, but we could. There's
other work by other people that penalizes
code complexity. Other thing which I think is probably
more useful is we have a holdout set. Test
set. So we do the induction on
a subset of the data and then
we do cross validation. We make sure you fit something.
You predict that validity move.
Bit. On holdout data.
So it that would penalize overfitting.
Michael? Hello. Hi, Kevin. Thanks.
Great talk. I was curious,
do you have any intuition about what made gin
rummy so much harder for
for the model? And does that what insights do
we get from that? So the
question was what makes gin and rummy harder?
I can't speak to that because I didn't
look into the I I don't know Jim
Rami well and you really have to pour
into the the traces to get
intuition. And I wasn't the first author of this so I
didn't get my hands dirty enough. Carter's in
the room. Do you have any comments? Do you know?
Come to the mic.
Alright. Mic comes to you even better.
So gin rummy was the most complex of the
games in terms of, like, the rollout links
and the state complexity, so I I assume
that's why. Don't have specific
reasons beyond that.
Cool. Thank you.
So let's thank Kevin again for an extremely interesting
talk.
Our next speaker is Frederic
Sala. Assistant professor of
the computer science at University of Western
Medicine. A chief scientist
of snorkel, So
Frazer yeah.
FLAS research team is
focused more about the data centric
AI, the foundation models
and automated machine learning. And
efficient machine learning systems. So
he leads Spark lab
at UW Medicine.
Where his group study how to build
more reliable, scalable, and
day efficient AI system. He will
give a fifteen minutes
industry demo talk. Let's welcome.
How about now? Okay. Much better.
Usually, I'm loud enough that this whole room will hear
me anyway, but let's use the mic.
So starting over, I'm here on behalf of
Snorkel AI, which is one of the sponsors for this
awesome workshop. Thanks so much for the organizers.
It's been amazing so far.
Not really gonna give a demo. It's really just
more of an opportunity for us to kinda plug
this new initiative that we have it's
called the Open Benchmarks Grant Program and
it's something that we've launched recently.
Basically, if folks are interested in building
benchmarks with us, we'd love to support you.
Especially within world models. So
I'll spend just a couple of minutes on kind of what Snorkel
is and what we do. There's this huge
captive audience, so maybe this is the right time for
me to you know, do a full detailed history
of snorkel, but I'll maybe skip that.
So basically, we started off working in
accelerating labeling and annotation in particular.
And there is really a world modeling angle
to this as well. So we really think
the right way to do this is not just
by doing manual labeling, but thinking
about how to extract insights from experts
kind of know exactly what to do when you ask them to
annotate an image. The way that we've
really done this is to encode all these insights
into programs that we call labeling functions here on
the left. And then kind of figure out which ones are good,
which ones are bad, and end up
aggregating them into what is a really powerful program
that can easily do annotation at scale.
So this label model thing in the middle is that, and
some of the techniques we used are actually pretty
similar to what Kevin described in this great talk.
So the key question for us is always, you know, what basic
fundamental principles do people like labelers
use to annotate at one point we actually
went ahead and did things like head tracking. We put
cameras on people's heads to look at exactly
what they were focusing on when they were trying to label images,
for example. More recently, we're
really doing a lot more work on building data for
Frontier Lab, and I'll describe that in a second.
In terms of world models, what we're interested
in basically is this kind of flywheel. So
we wanna know what kind of high quality and rich
and complex data and data trajectories
are gonna help improve the development of
world models and then kind of vice
versa we use world models to improve
generation of high quality data? You know, the
kind of stuff that we'll use to train our language models and
foundation models. So one thing that
we've been thinking about recently is just this kind
of increasing gap between
how we build up our models, our agents, our systems,
and how easy it is to evaluate them. And
our take basically is that development
has gotten smoother and smoother and
easier but measurement has actually gotten
harder. So it's increasingly difficult
to really be able to evaluate all the things that we build.
And of course, if we really want to deploy all
these amazing new developments, we have to close
this gap And the way that we're thinking
about this is that you can't really just take
a single approach. You have to do something very
multifaceted. We are very strong believers
that you have to actually go in the field and kind of work
with real deployments, real production,
and figure out how well our systems are working there.
At the same time, we think you have to try every technique,
really, But the one that I wanted to mention
is open benchmarks. So we really
do think that have to get a lot more new
diverse open benchmarks for measuring the capabilities
of our system. And our agents.
So that's what we're focused on in this very short
talk. So this is the Open Benchmark
Grant Initiative. It's this recent commitment that
we've made this is something that Snorkel is doing also
with a bunch of collaborators, so Hugging Face,
PrimeIntellect together and a bunch of other folks.
What we'd like to do basically is to hear from
people who have interesting ideas
for doing benchmarking, for agents,
for world models, and other things,
and we'll help support you So that could mean
things like helping you compete It could mean
things like helping you with data resources and
access to experts that know particular
domains. It could also mean things like just collaborating
on a research basis as well. So
at the end of the talk, I'll have a slide with
the link for this. If you're interested, we'd love to hear from
you. So kind of moving forward,
we've we've gotten actually a bunch of different,
applications that have been super interesting and we've
really started thinking about, you know, how do you
subdivide? How do you characterize all
these awesome new benchmarks? We
think kind of this nice free
part access is the way to do it. So things
like tracking how complex environments are,
you know, the horizon of autonomy for agents, and
and things like output complexity.
Alright. So I don't wanna miss this chance to also kind
of generally describe Snorkel's mission, and I
won't take super long. Basically, we want to safely
define and advance the frontier of
AI with expert data development.
This means things like supporting these open
research and benchmark initiatives that I mentioned,
It means producing data and environments for
It also means like working with enterprises and
doing deployments there, for example.
Just a couple of slides also on kind of what really
inspires us We think that things are
getting more complex, of course, and the
agentic data stack for all the things that we
now do, reinforcement learning, evals, capability
development, these things are getting both very complex
but also very domain specific.
So kind of meeting this shift compared to what we
had to do in the past means that you also need this
very sophisticated type of approach.
We have to combine data centric AI advancements
with expert knowledge, and that's really what we
focus on. Just very briefly,
we deliver expert data for Frontier AI.
So we have this huge expert network
that we work with. Care a lot about quality. We care a
lot about diversity. We care about complexity,
we think world models are something that's gonna help
us kind of in all of these different areas.
We've worked with tons of different experts, so one of the
fun things that we do is really get into all kinds of interesting
and fun domains, maybe beyond the standard ones
that we often typically see in
benchmarking. We use a bunch of different tools,
programmatic controls, and things like that to make sure our
data is very high quality. And of course, we
do things like really track real distributions
for data as well. And
finally, we can do basically scale our expertise.
Our big thesis is that we'll always need human
domain expertise, but we'll have to combine it
with models with scalability and so forth.
So I'll end there, but if you have a benchmark idea,
please reach out. We'd love to talk to you.
If anything cool comes up also as a result of the
workshop, we'd love to chat more. Thank
you.
Thank you very much for the talk. And,
there is any question, but I
guess it's not Maybe you can,
if you are interested in our sponsor with
Snoglio AI, you can email direct to
Fred. After the conference.
And, thank you again And
the next session will be the panel discussion,
and the panel will be moderated
by Kevin Murphy. And,
the panel member will be the
Sarah, Kevin,
and also, Shen Gu.
And also
fabric.
And also our, AMI
cofounder, Michael Rabbit. So,
maybe we can have some seat
and, bring some seat to the
stage
Alright. Well, we're gonna Hello. We can see you
now. Oh, you're remote.
Hi, Shane. We just started.
Maybe we'll do introduction to Shank. Can
you start? Can you hear us?
Sure. Yeah. I'll be kinda giving talk
after this panel discussion. I'm a senior staff
research scientist at Google DeepMind.
I worked on, so
classics of general modeling to
reinforce money into robotics and most
recently just working on the reasoning in
the large language models and then the video
models.
Cool. Michael?
Hi, everyone. My name is Mike Gravatt. I'm
a cofounder and VP of World Models at
AMI Labs. And
also obviously interested in world models, how
we learn them, also how we can use
them for things like policy
improvement and planning and what not.
Hi. I'm Sara. I'm a
principal research manager at Microsoft. Research.
I'm also doing war model
very originally. In this room.
But mainly interested in building role models for
entertainment. Instead of
API.
Hey, folks. And I just introduced myself, but I'm Fred
Salla. An assistant professor at University of
Wisconsin Madison. I'm also chief scientist of
Snorkel AI. I am mostly interested in
data centric AI, data efficient learning,
foundation model learning, and so on.
So I was sent some
questions that to start the
pump rolling. The ball rolling.
I thought we could
discuss. So, one of them is what
distinguishes a useful world model from
a strong generative model or simulator? So I think
this has been touched on already today, but
like, we could contrast a
serious goals where the goal
is to generate games that
people play and they need to look nice
and be fun, as opposed and Microsoft's
on the other end of the spectrum, where it's like,
no. You never look at the pixels. The agent doesn't
look at the pixels. You you compress them as quickly
as possible. And I'm not sure where Fred sits. And I don't know
where I'm very curious to hear Shane's opinion. So
let's just go around the room. Maybe
Michael, you wanna we'll start with Shane. Because
you're furthest. Did you hear
the question? Yeah. I heard
this. So you mean, like, what constitutes a used for
word model? Yeah. Like,
the the visit like, do we wanna generate
let let's we wanna generate pixels
or do we just wanna generate latence?
Do we need to generate pixels If we're
doing agents opposed to human entertainment?
Op opine. Yeah. So I
kinda touched on my presentation, but I feel,
know, like, world model is kind of be
on just, like, an action condition video model.
So I find,
my kinda definition is kinda more cross to
pretty much what's the model that's
that's required for, like, model based reinforcement learning.
To me, that's kinda what sort of, like,
what origin kinda defined.
Love of the kind of the next model, work model.
And I think that could be, in terms,
like, you know, what representation that should be kinda modeling
at. Whether it's, like, pixels.
It can be, like, symbols.
That's really kinda up to the to the need.
That's kind of what my definition.
Thing I may kinda add is the, the causality.
I think it's pretty important as aspect of
kinda defining the word model. And then you
weigh the time of like, error of time kinda
gives that. I don't know if that answer your question,
but I'd like to hear other people's thoughts.
I guess I'll agree with a lot of what Shane said. I
guess for me, like, generative models purpose
is fundamentally maybe different than a world model.
So I think of a generative model as something well, I'll get
a nice sample. Right? It might be high fidelity. It might look
good, etcetera, and that might be really what I wanna have.
For a world model, I'm really thinking about, you know, looking
at plausible futures, making good decisions, and things
like that. Means I don't necessarily need the
level of fidelity, and maybe that's not really a
useful thing. So we have fundamentally somewhat
different purposes between strong generative models
and good world models.
I guess on our side, it's a bit different.
We see world models as well, not only something
that we can use for planning, but also something that we can
for entertainment. And
when we are thinking of entertainment, we want something
that's very beautiful. That
looks good. So our side,
that is something that is yeah, kind of
crucial. When we're bidding our models.
However, if we're thinking about yeah,
building a model for, let's say, robotics,
we don't need to have very high visuals. We just
need to know what's happening next.
Thanks.
I'll just say I agree with the way that you framed it at
the beginning, Kevin. I think it really depends on
can take a step back and say, you know, the term world model
is definitely overloaded and that it means
different things depending on who you're talking to. But
think at the end of the day, it depends on what is the
application that you're going to be using it to
solve. I don't think the most sake, people are
doing a world model for the sake of just having a world
model. So in my
particular case, I'm interested in using it to control
things that are in the physical world, in which case I think
it's important that more important that
it understands physics and maybe semantics of a scene
than pixel level details
of the texture of the carpet or something like that.
So let let me make it spicier.
I'll I'll echo Jorgen Schmidthuber
this morning was saying we should even
if we just wanna do agent design, we
should be doing generative models that actually do model every
single spec of texture on
the carpet. Because that might be
important. Maybe it's you
know, poison. Right? We
don't know what's useful. And in the limit,
we should explain everything.
Thoughts? If you have
the compute and the capacity to
do it, maybe that's what
you wanna do. I think
you wanna be a bit more efficient,
and not boil several oceans
and, I mean, my take on
it is I think for most hacks maybe for
that one particular tale task, you do
care about exact texture of the carpet, but I
think for the majority of things, you
know, we as humans
are unlike it's unlikely that we're trying to memorize every
single detail. This room, we're gonna remember
certain specific aspects.
Will remember that we talked about certain parts of the
carpet, and maybe we'll remember what that looked like because
attention was drawn to that for this specific moment in
time when it was relevant. But I guess
for most tasks, we can get away with abstracting
away lot of the irrelevant details. And so having
representations that are able to do that or models that are
able to do that to me seems like in the
long run, it's gonna be more efficient and a
much more reasonable way to
both learn and act in the world, but also
happy to be you know,
you can try to convince me otherwise.
I would tend to agree that
it's probably overkill to model everything that
there is yeah, our
research is very centered around how can we make things
more efficient and less expensive.
So that angle of
throwing everything we can at the model to see what it can make
make up. Make up of seems to be
kind of brute forcing it. And
I would find it more interesting to see to
try to understand what are the relevant components
that we need to learn and to understand rather than
just yeah, praying that the model
gets it right.
Yeah. I'll plus one, everyone's side. I mean,
I think in the limit, this may or may not be
true, but we're not really in the limit.
Right? So, like, how efficient we can make things
matters a great deal. And for that reason,
yeah, I think, like, the model everything angle is
gonna be especially challenging. I think, especially
in our experience when we work with things like enterprise
environments, for example, Right? They're enormously complex.
If we wanna get down to the last detail,
then really being able to model that is gonna get extremely
difficult, so we really do need these abstractions.
Shane, do you have anything to say?
Oh, we can't hear you now.
Yeah. If you're the Fodor learning has always
been the tension of predict everything.
Kind of where we just can scale.
Versus sort of manual attention is kinda
what you need. You know? Kinda engineer
feature on that. One point
I definitely do wanna add is that by
predicting everything, you're kind of making the
sort of the the training data much more diverse.
Much more easy to kinda, like,
fill. And then it could also kinda iterate over
for performance. To me,
the one turning point was really the bill too.
The b o two model, I think it was, like, announced
a year and a half ago. They already had
amazing physics. And I think when I look into it,
something that really changes that,
the is it really high high
resolution kind of video prediction. So
to me, like, when you really predict,
video at high resolution,
cannot fall around. You cannot have a sort of,
you know, good enough looking stuff as in, like,
early kind of video models. So
predicting everything in picks
one is that it can really enforce the model to
learn importance in, like, physics consistency.
Because if it breaks, then,
you know, it'll cut a a lot more loss.
And, also, you're gonna make,
the data much more, easy
to just process, but, like, a generalist model.
So I, you know,
I'm in the Google
DeepMind frontier labs, so I'm on more the predict
everything sort of I think doctor
Schmittover stuff stuff.
Good. We have a diversity of opinions. It makes
it more interesting. I'll just pitch my 2¢,
which is that you we should
learn from everything. Data
is precious. But at runtime, we don't
have to model the full we we need
context specific models, right, for decision making.
That are task dependent. But
they're derived from a general model. Like,
of of everything. And you can do synthesis on the
fly. Anyway,
oh, I guess I am supposed to answer my own question.
So, that's alright. Let me go
back to the the
font of entropy.
Okay. What are the most current
critical current bottlenecks
Is it data, scale, compute, abstraction,
causality, robustness? I will I
will add one more to the mix. Which
is temporal abstraction. We're always
talking about one step model. Sergei was the only
speaker who addressed that. And talked about
jumpy models. And Jorgen mentioned it
But like we all know we need it. No one
seems to be doing it except for Sergey and
of course, Jorgensen and everything.
So you mentioned hierarchy.
Would you like to say what you're doing?
Yeah. Sure. I I do think actually that's probably one of the
biggest bottlenecks.
Whether and I think how you think of it
could be through temporal then abstraction.
Sorry. Yeah. Abstraction of temporal dynamics
in successive representations or something similar
to what Sergei was talking about.
It also maybe ties into memory.
How we bring memory into these systems to
have them keep track of some state over
time, not just based
on the immediate observations. Being
able to recall, So but I think
that definitely one of the biggest bottlenecks right
now. I
agree. And just to add
to that,
one of the reasons why it's probably a bottleneck
is
the problems are not necessarily very well
defined. So we need to be a little bit more creative,
come up with good benchmarks. So hopefully, some
people can think of good benchmarks that way.
Also probably involves data that we don't necessarily
have in great volumes. If you wanna
talk about long horizon tasks,
we don't always collect that
sort of data. At least not so
far. So I think that's also part of the
bottleneck. Let me stop there.
I would say some of the big bottlenecks we have
are around data.
At the moment to to be able to model
a space pretty well, we need to essentially
have footage of every possible angle and every
possible view that there is in the model and
and in a the environment. And
collecting data like that in very large
environment is very expensive.
So finding ways to you said, obstruct
things and make
it faster to learn models. With
fewer examples is would
be really helpful.
Memory is a big one.
How we can model very long context and measure that
the model remembers everything that's happened, I
don't know, hours
is super important. And thing I
will add is also inference speed.
To people to be able
to use models on their phone, we're
we're talking about real time models, but this is
always on very powerful GPUs.
So quite far away from being able
to run-in some device.
Yeah. I'll I'll agree with everyone so far. I I
don't think there's necessarily a dominance like
bottleneck. For us, of course, we also
care a lot about data. So that's where we see a lot of the
bottlenecks come into play. Play. And I I especially
think it has to do with data collection mechanisms.
Right? So in a lot of different domains, really,
you can't do interventions and really
interesting trajectories. You're just doing observational
data collection. And you're doing it in ways
that are often kind of very biased. Right? You're not
really tracking what's the real distribution, but
rather, you know, whatever was convenient collect data from.
So, really, that gives you something that's not super useful
necessarily, and that makes, like, really
actually quality data become a pretty big bottleneck.
Shane? I said the top
bottleneck is the capital allocation.
So right now, right now,
ODA ODA, basically, they're, like, resource.
Are kinda going to the, say, the AI coding agents
because that's kinda where know, AI coding
agents are kinda automating, like, a lot of the white collar kinda
works. So a lot of the, like, money,
compute, and top talents are
basically kinda looking to that. Word
model, I think the robotics is still kinda
far out in the future. And then entertainment
also has its own sort of industrial
kind of barriers. But I do feel
from about four years ago that we do have a
tons of data. We have tons
of patents that we can, mobilize.
But the reality is right now, the sort
of the skating general modeling side is very
dominated by of what, you know,
what the Wall Street kinda semi commodity kinda
see as capital allocation. So So one
kinda, like, small point is like that. Of
in my talk, I'll talk about, you know, like,
how to how to learn causality, you know, and how
to get the cause really diverse data.
Example, for training, I'll talk about how
to minimize distribution shift and those kind of
technical stuff, but just to add a new
stuff to there. I think all the pieces
there. Data, compute,
architecture, it's just our prioritization
right now is more on the AI coding, and
that's has been slowing down, I think, the word
modeling than, what it should be.
I think you're leaking information
about private competition than GDM.
Never mind. I have another
question. To what degree do
you guys think LLMs
already are world models
And, for example, think about
a shopping agent that is clicking around on Amazon.
Right? I don't know if I click
a button what I'm gonna see next. Right?
If I do a search, I'm buying, I don't
know, an umbrella and I type that in the search
window and I hit enter, I expect
the next page to have umbrellas on it
somewhere. And if it shows me
sunglasses, I probably made a typo. Right?
So I have some expectations, but they're
is like a successor feature, but it's very
abstract. And most of the rest is
unpredictable. But it doesn't stop me. I click on
the thing. And maybe my prediction is
wrong, but I can very quickly adapt
So I see it's sunglasses, and then
not only realize I made a mistake, but realize
that probably I mistyped and I
can correct myself and continue. Right?
And this is like so,
LMM agents kinda do that. I mean, I look at Claude Coad's
thinking traces. It'll do stuff, and it says,
oops. I forgot to in import OS.
Then it will go back and do it and try again. And
it's like, these are persistent little things. Right?
And they will find the hacks in your reward function.
So and that's all model free,
or is it not? I mean, are they
doing modeling under the hood?
Okay. I'll go for it.
I mean, my opinion is that they
if if I don't know. I mean,
not hedge. Let me just say I don't think I don't
believe that they do have a world model. I think
there's actually been work in the literature,
not by me, but by several others,
looking into this question. There is some literature that says
that they do build a world model. I think there are some early
work training
LLM style transformer models on traces of
the game Othello, which people
claimed that the world model learned the
the physics what were valid moves, which is interesting.
But I guess you saw that they don't do this
on their own. You need to put a good harness around it. So
I think that's an interesting takeaway once you make
the world more complex. There's
also a nice paper from, John
Kleinberg and some collaborators of his
again, a couple years ago, they asked this
question, in a similar way. If you train,
another way to think of a world model is that you're learning a
map of the world. And so if you were
to train on traces of trajectories through the
world, you might hope that the model would be able
to recognize what are valid transitions, where
where you can get from one block to the next. And
so they took a bunch of traces
of taxis driving through New York,
tried to see how well the model could
learn the map of New York, and it comes
nowhere close to it. So it also was kind of
another way of providing evidencing that
world, LLMs on their own do not learn
kind of internal world model. Now I think the
way you posed the question is more about
world knowledge as opposed to a
world model. So anyways,
let me pass it to others if others have
an opinion. I still think it's far
LLM are definitely not my area of expertise.
I might say something dumb, but
my feeling is that now that
they're not a war model, truly for thinking of
something that's pure text.
I feel like you need to see a lot more of the
world to get a good modeling and
understanding of what's happening.
I do see in my interaction with LLM that they can
tend to get stuck in a circle, which is not
something that happens when when have a good
understanding of the world and how things are going. Like,
you remember what happened, then you know that you
should not repeat what you've done in the past.
Yeah.
Yeah. I guess there's really two questions here. One is basic
the LLMs that we have today, are they world
models? And even if they're not,
you know, is it possible by the same methodology
to produce world models via LLMs if you
scaled something up or changed something in the design?
I agree that I don't think they are world models today,
and I don't have a very strong philosophical position
on what counts and what doesn't, but they screw
up too often in just the ways we've described. So
them to be world models. I'm much more sort of,
you know, unsure about whether we do
to build LLMs cannot produce a world model. And I
think that's a pretty interesting question.
If I could add something okay before we could pass
it over to Shane too. But,
I I do wanna I did wanna say, I I do think
obviously, LLMs and codec agents are very useful
for some things. Right? So they're
there is that. As a world
model, still don't think so. And one other example
just to give, failure mode
that was
but I think it accurately
reflects where language fails to capture certain
aspects of the physical world, is the
following one. You know, somebody prompted they prompted
all of the state of the art world models at the time.
This was a few months ago. Asking the following
question, I wanna take my car to get
it washed, The car wash is about 500
meters down the road. Should I walk or
should I drive?
And every element of time,
said, like definitively, oh, it's only 500
meters away. It would be much more efficient if
you just walk. Right? Which is not maybe the most
useful thing if you wanna get your car washed.
More recent models might hedge a
little bit and say, well, it kinda depends on what the weather
is outside. But I think it's
still says that there's something missing about kind of
common sense understanding of how the world works in these
models. Will it ever get there?
Again, I don't know how much data and how much
how much training we need to get there. So
yeah. But maybe Shane has a different opinion.
Yeah. So as someone working on the OMs, I definitely
think the OMs have more models.
But, basically, kinda video models,
have a sort of a better edge because they can use the
error of time. Essentially, the only sort of reliable
signal for the causality is kinda
time right now. So the so it's kinda auto regress
the video modeling. He has sort of unfair
advantage of being able to use that extremely
high quality signal. But, you
know, like, the LMs are I I I assume
I sort of, like, we we
also miss causation a lot
with, kinda correlation.
And I have a four year old daughter,
and then she she tells me about her world model
in the language. And she tells me,
you know, this has happened because of this, this has happened
because of this. Eighty percent are hallucinations.
But, she is definitely kinda building
her world model. And to me, it's not like a
binary, kinda zero one. It's more
like a gradual process. I'll kinda talk about
it, but essentially, the better we can predict
the world, you're just in hurry kinda build the the
true sort of causal program of the world.
So, hopefully, like, it's it's
more like incremental process, and I definitely see
the OMs as a very important
part of, what's gonna be, say, the omni import
model. Yeah.
Yeah. No. I agree with that perspective. I
mean, I I view world
moles, their predictive distributions about
the future but they
they they're only useful if they're compact
and know, efficiently computable.
And abstractive and you learn
them by induction from examples, and many of them
will be wrong, but you learn them iteratively. And I
think if you train on the web, it's just a
IID sample of a from a mixture distribution
from all kinds of sources. So it's
really hard to model causality. But in video, it's
it's coming from one camera, maybe even a single
person, And so it's it's
it's it's cleaner data in that respect, although it has
low signal to noise. But I think when we start
getting agenetic traces and training on them,
and, like, dialogues from individuals,
Now we can model the data generating process
because we know who which actor caused
which action stream, and it's very long,
and it's temporally coherent, and it
has you know, latent concepts there
and it's not some random soup from the
web. Right? So I'm actually pretty
optimistic we will make progress on this.
Anyway, enough bantering. Let me open up
to the audience. There must be questions
you guys have for this
esteemed panel. Or maybe just other people in the room.
Hi. Maybe introduce yourself
first when you start. Okay.
My name is Michael Katz. I'm from ABM.
I come from different community. I come from
classical planning community.
And can you hear
me? So I come from a classical
planning community. And lots
lots of things that you mentioned here
speak speak to me. Because we
are dealing with the same things and
we have developed
tools
that work on the same things. And
I was wondering whether
you think there is a place
for some sort of
symbolic models
like, s world models,
symbolic tools, and
so on. In
the current
research and tools that are being developed.
Well, if you saw my talk, then
I'm sorry. I didn't. You didn't? I just
gave a talk which were you might have liked
it, which was very much on symbolic
world models. The difficult
thing about them is
if the symbols aren't observed and you
induce them from raw data, then it's the symbol
to signal problem. Right? Sorry. Signal to symbol problem.
Which we haven't really solved. I mean, VLMs do it, but they're
cheap because they use human labels. So, like, unsupervised
object discovery never really
worked. Right? All the good old stuff from ML
that we did in the eighties and nineties, it doesn't really
work So we just cheat by using
weak forms of supervision or strong sort of forms.
For the symbols. But,
the other thing is these those moles are quite fragile
because they only met model a subset
of the problem. But that makes
them efficient. So I think it's a trade off.
Like, I think if we talk about fidelity,
it's okay to have an imperfect model if it's
a lot faster. Better sometimes
to be cheap and fast than slow
and good. Right? So but there
are not a lot of symbol symbol loving
people who come to ICLAR, I think.
But anyone else have opinions?
Shane, you're laughing. Go ahead.
No. No. No. I no. I think I I I want
like, all the communities to be kind of
involving, I think, world model. I feel the
kind of world model is, is where it
should be kind of very inclusive. I definitely
kinda love kinda more symbolic,
community to kinda be part of it.
Something maybe I can we can kinda say is that if you can really
kinda express in symbols, one is that you can do
a very kinda easy verification by the OEMs, which
is, LMs, all kind of programs.
So, essentially, if you if you, you know, if you're
represent everything in the video, it's very hard to run the,
kind of verification. But, if you can
represent everything in this kinda, like, SVG kind
of symbols and stuff, you can easily do
that. So I really like this sort of, kinda
going between the pixels. Kinda row signals
to the symbols.
And I think there's definitely a a big room
for the community. In the world modeling.
Right. So for benchmarks, for instance,
if you start from the symbolic
description, it's easier to
to work with them to
to generate the benchmarks. Right?
Because you have the verification, as you say,
and you can generate
like, video representation, text
representation. So on.
From that.
I I just want to give another
comment on whether l
m's are word models or not.
If I may. We have a paper actually
in this conference that presents
a dataset that starts
from the symbolic and describes
these these questions
to the language model. Asking
here is the state. What are the actual what
what are the actual that you can apply
in the state? Here is the state. Here is an
action. What is the
effect of applying an action in that How
will the state change and so on?
And let no. The the
word the language models are not there yet.
Alright. We'll take the next question. Thank you.
Hey, everyone. Thanks for the panel. My name is
Aishwarya, and a PhD student
at Stanford. I come from more of a
reinforcement learning perspective over
here. Studied reinforcement learning for maybe
like, eight or nine years now. And we
have kind of two camps. Right?
Model based RL and model free
RL. And I'm kind of
curious to get your opinion on
how you see world models in settings
where data is sparse. Right,
where you have very few datasets.
At least in reinforcement learning, we've kind of come to the
conclusion that YouTube model
free RL in this case So
I've seen a lot of hype around world models for use in
settings like health care and education where we might
not have that much data. What do you think are
the limitations of this use?
It's a tough one.
So, yeah, we've been we've been trying to think of how we
can reduce our data requirement
Sorry. We've been trying to think of how we can
reduce our data requirements as much
as possible. And at the moment,
we're exploring data pipelines, so maybe
we can start from a few pictures of our place
and then use existing tools to
kind of simulate this environment. So kind of
yep, generating the data that we need to train the
model in a way.
This is very much not solved
in a work in progress but yeah, we are exploring
ways to to work with
partial knowledge of the
space. Also, something I think
at least for the visual types of
our models, something I think that has a lot of potential
is leveraging three d representations.
Working with pure video footage is quite
wasteful. And I think if we have more
information about the geometry of the space, then we
can be a lot more data efficient as well.
Cannot I can add something.
So even with that kind of limited data,
I think something that's really kinda important
is from this predicting
the why from x, what are all
the other variables or information
that's gonna be part of this kind of causal
program that predict the why?
And you can get that from
for example, you can,
some sort of kind of vision models, kind of specialist
model, or large language models that can
sort of analyze kind of video and then sort
of, give you much more information. So I
call it, like, dark knowledge, kind
of referencing kinda Jeff Fenton's
kinda word. And, also, you can even
use reinforcement to kinda find it.
So if you wanna predict why from x,
so and then you kinda search for,
like, z variables that can better
predict the y. You can can optimize
an object using RL. So you can also kinda search
for this kind of dark knowledge. In
that way. So but I I see it's a very important question,
which is, like, have a very limited data that
we can, use for prediction to run one
model. What are, like, all the tools we can,
and we should use kind of everything to,
get as much data and get at this, like, dark
knowledge of prediction.
Maybe the one thing I would add is, I think I agree
with all that was said.
Thing I would add is least in my experience,
when trying to learn a policy in a data
scarce sort of setting,
Depends on the type of data you're learning from, but
if you can transform that into
a more useful representation
for the sake of learning, something that disentangles
variables or otherwise captures the right structure
for the problem. It can make learning the policy
more efficient as well. And I think that's maybe one connection
between some of the things that we're discussing workshop today
terms of how
the same time as trying to learn to act in the world.
So there might be some connections there as well.
Just I'll say one thing.
So there is theory work showing that it's more sample
efficient to learn a world model than a policy.
I can't remember the reference, but you can email
me if you if you wanna know.
Also, it's usually
easier to put informative priors on models and policies.
So that was one of the motivations for
this work I talked about
So, you can share can learn
a model from a world model from data from
any source. Right? Any any
expert does its policy independent.
And often has, like, some grounding in
physics. And you might know a lot about a
problem before you even
try to tackle it. Whereas policies need
you need to think about how to play
well, right, or how to act optimally
and that that can be harder to learn from data
alone. So, if you don't have a lot of data, I would do model
based. But just regularize it and
put a strong prior there. Okay.
We'll move to the oh, sorry. Did you wanna follow-up?
No. I just thanks. Okay.
Alright. Thank you. Thank you for the panel.
I'm Crave from Oxford. I wanted to
actually, ask about Shane's
on resource allocation. I think it's,
really interesting point that you made that's, oh, yeah, like,
coding agents now are taking away
all the all the resources because, yeah,
stealing white collar jobs actually
does pay a lot better than stealing blue collar jobs, so why not do that?
I'm just, like, thinking that if we are really interested in
world models, why not just, piggyback?
The new wave of of good
coding agents like now writing good
code or even like a full report story. Like, you
can just write an ephemeral world model
that can you just, like, throw out as soon as your hypothesis
is invalidated. And I think
Kevin's work is, like, going into a really nice direction where
you just say that, oh, yeah. Like, you can
start, distilling
all the knowledge from these models into code
and work symbolically long as
the symbolic representation works. And since
now having a symbolic code is actually
really cheap to get because of the coding agents, because
there's just like a wave that is coming.
Like, that's that's a vacuum. That's not like a
a deliberate decision on
where resources are allocated. Why why
not just work on not the perfect world
models, but ephemeral world
models? That can be just discarded
as soon as your hypothesis is in backdate.
Yeah. So so first of all, Kevin and
others, you know, I look at, you know, OpenAI
accounts for the store team and stuff, so I'm just kinda guessing
the resource allocation from there. Nothing
about the Google DeepMind.
The Of course. Inter I I I
think the idea is kinda
perfect. Because, like, I think
yes. I I totally agree. I think this sort
of extremely kinda exponential
rise in the AI coding tool. Can really
kinda benefit the word modeling and then can
really kinda bring that sort of symbolic
kind of side to add the kind of code execution even
kinda simulate you know, kind of physics simulators kinda
backing this kind of game. I think that's very,
very excited exciting direction. And I
think the reason is that you
really have a internal representation access
to the causal program of the
word model, then you can you can generate pretty
much all the diverse interventions,
causally kind of grounded interventions of those kind
of data is much, much richer
than the data in the wild. So
I'll actually kinda have
some of this in my talk, but, essentially, you can really
intervene. You you can basically kinda do just,
like, in interventions to kinda infer the causal
graph, which can really kinda help learn
better word models. So I think it's a very exciting direction.
Yeah.
Awesome. Thank you.
Just one quick comment on the capital being
assigned somewhere else. I feel
sometimes having fewer resources can be a good
way to be more creative on the research
you're doing and trying to do things
maybe in a smarter and different way other than treading
at scale and and see what happens.
So I do see this as
I'll I'll
add one thing too. I mean, I think it's a really fundamentally interesting
question because you have to ask yourself, like, how much can you
express as code? Depending on the kind of
domains and tasks that you're looking at. These
are things we've tried with things like, can you programmatically
distill a foundation model into some
giant program? Because, of course, then indeed, you
can generate all the causal interventions you want
You can even go and really understand everything.
But I think there are some interesting limits there as well
you get into, you know, million lines of code
type of programs. Awesome. It's
worth clarifying that agenda coding doesn't necessarily
mean generating code. Right? It could be just
just manipulating tools. It's really
in context learning is the magic. Right?
Plus tool use. And then code is just
a fancy tool. Anyway. Right.
Okay. Next.
Hello, everyone. I'm from
University. From China. Yeah.
I have a question that, in
order to build a world
model, could our standard robot can
do planning? And should we
what kind of learning
program should we primarily
rely on the self supervised learning or
the reinforcement learning.
I think at this moment in time,
I would say it's pretty
clear self supervised learning.
My opinion. I mean, I think I think reinforcement
learning has a role to play. We want ultimately
learn policies. But acting in
the world for a lot of the applications, at least
that I find interesting, acting acting
in a simulator doesn't get you to what you
wanna go for real world. Acting
in the real world is expensive. Either
because it's dangerous or you can
break something, you can damage, hurt somebody.
And so
yeah, I think as much as we can
take advantage of whatever other
data is available out there, for self supervised
learning, it seems like just we should
be doing that. But I'm sure others have
other opinions.
Shane, why don't you tell us your your journey? Because
you used to be a big RL guy. Oh.
Hold on a self supervised learning. Forget
about RL. No. No.
By essentially RO, just by the formulation
of the equation, is
just much more simple, inefficient
than so for supervised running.
So I kinda say reinforcement learning,
this kinda online
self distillation, kinda like learning and that's,
only use that when when you when that's, like, the
only thing you can do. I would say
self supervised learning is definitely, like, most to kinda
push. And only when there's a bottleneck,
you can switch to RL.
I I I have a bit of dev. I know.
RL has, like, a lot more,
sort of, like, artifacts, but I I can
kinda go more in-depth later.
I have some to follow-up.
Yeah. We know we all know that the reinforcement learning
is low efficiency.
Yeah. Low efficiency. But,
subsequent learning it has
made a great success in
language that I am, But
in visual,
the the language can express itself but
can visual
express itself? Can we use
Visual to understand Visual Yeah.
I think notice the self serve self serve
learning is mostly is
single modality. Yeah. So I have this question.
Yeah. Yeah. So so just to add, I I'm not
denying the RO. In fact, my talk, we're
gonna talk about, like, why ours is kinda
important. Essentially, like, yeah,
like, even, for example, take the hallucination
Right? Like, why do LOMs hallucinate? And
then why humans have, like, you know, less
kind of, like, unreasonable hallucination? It because
we know, like, we we live in the world. You know? We are
basically online learning agents. So when
we kinda say something, when we I,
for example, forget, you know, my boss,
you know, I you know, like, birthday and
stuff, maybe, you know, that'll affect my job and stuff.
So essentially, the there are
consequences to, to
kind of tokens we say. And those we can
kind of those are much more
not much more, but, like, could be more efficient
to terms like online learning. Than
just, like, through, like, unweighted, self
supervised data. So so
I actually touched on this topic in my, next talk
after this panel.
Cool. So we have three more questioners,
and we have five minutes. Thank you. We
have three minutes.
Six minutes. Great. Two minutes per person. Okay.
Go. Roughly.
Amortized. Thank
you. So
you started the discussion asking,
are we what what's better? I totally learn from
pixels or from presentations and
all of this? And, do we learn
everything or not everything? But
when we say, learn everything, like,
we go down to quantum mechanics because
we know that you know, to build a model
of a quantum mechanical system, you need the compute
equivalent to the quantum mechanical system.
So it's impossible. Right? So
essentially the answer is no. We're obviously learning
something more more higher. But on other
on the other hand,
we as humans I think,
Mike, you said that
humans don't,
remember everything.
And that's an important distinction
distinction from perceive everything. I
can see the carpet. I can see you.
I can see everything. But
I remember this in an hour?
Most likely not everything. But I
can see everything. Right? So I guess the question
is, not do we perceive
everything question is where do we lose the information?
So and in this sense,
I'm curious, like, what
is the difference between approaches I
mean, why is it is it actually
that different? Like, do we
look at pixels or do we
do we, look at, latence?
Because essentially, like okay.
Our receiver has, capacity
x, then we reduce this to
capacity like x, prime blah
blah blah blah blah. So reduce reduce reduce. It's a
question of how do we
focus our attention and we are in
this chain. We lose. And I
I think the the actual question is
how do we make this a like, attention,
like, more, modulated?
I mean, what's what's your opinion on this?
And, like, how can we get to a true foundational
world model? That can do a lot
of things? And
change in real time from
remembering you know, carpet
floor to to the person
next to me.
Start, I guess. I mean, I I think it actually comes back
to this idea of hierarchy. And needing to be
able to learn across multiple time scales, multiple
spatial scales, and and
translate between those representations as well.
Like you said, you know, we we don't observe
quantum. Mechanics or
quantum level things. We know that they're there. Like,
how did we get there? Well, through actually a process
of inquiry and trying to understand and
then come up with better models ourselves to understand the
world, don't yet have models that
are anywhere close to doing that. Formulating
hypotheses, developing
their own ways of measuring in order to to
go further. But you could imagine at
some at some point, having some sort
of agentic
system that does that with a world model inside that
it's constantly trying to refine and improve.
Okay.
I can give the computer vision perspective
that we learn
from video only, what we what we're only seeing is just
a flat image of everything being on the same plane.
And until we see
events happen in three d, there's no evidence
of this object is disentangled
from this one. The wormholes are
also essentially learning transition from
point a to point b, but they don't really
know learn anything about the absolute position
and what's exactly disposition. We just know how
to go from a to b. So
I think to get this level of
in-depth understanding of this of the
space, and knowing what is important to remember.
You need to have a better internal representation.
What's happening in the world and what matters.
Hi. I'm Yu Chou. I'm interested
in building
generalist robots. Can help humans
in the real world. And I
was wondering whether you think,
like, it's explicit world models
will be required as the fastest
way to building generous robots
because because we see a
lot of cool demos from for
example, physical
intelligence that just builds VLAs that can
do impressive things.
Thanks.
I agree. I I I do believe
the world models are gonna be pretty essential. I think what
we want actually is you know,
systems that can generalize
You're you're gonna bring it home the first
day you're gonna open the box, the robot's gonna come out and it's
gonna be in an environment it's never seen before.
Right? Might be somewhat similar to others,
it seemed, but might ask it to do
things, you know, maybe
like my socks folded
socks folded. So I might ask
it to do things differently. We want if
we really want systems to be able
to help people in the way that they wanna be
helped, and
and generalize in that way. I think having a
world model is actually really useful as a
way to transfer. You don't wanna have to
demonstrate I don't wanna have to demonstrate a 100 times
how I'd like something done a robot,
let alone a thousand times, but for it to learn from
demonstrations. Having a world
model hopefully helps us to get there.
We'll take one last question, I think, and then we need to
wrap. Hi. Stefano
Martinian. I'm a professor at NYU. I have a question
for Kevin. Have you thought about
the analogies between symbolic world models
and the process of scientific discovery?
Where mathematics is the harness
of the observations that we make and
our action is our measurements
and we cooperate with others. So we're multiplayers
in a way. It's not adversarial. But it's
cooperative. Like, if you thought about how we could
take type of frameworks to
develop models for autonomous
experimentation and and and autonomous
research. Yes. Let's talk
afterwards. This is this
is bull's eye of my interest these days.
Okay. Great. Okay. I think we'll wrap that.
You very much for the panel discussion, and,
thanks a lot for our panelist.
And, we are going to the next session.
The talk from Shingu. Shen, you can
still live here.
Okay. Great. In case,
sorry, in case some of our new attendees
come to, the room, I will
introduce you again. Like, Shing Gu
is from, Google DeepMind.
He's a senior staff research scientist
and, he's currently worked on Gemini
thinking. And, he was,
he was the senior
researcher on the chatbot team
at OpenAI. A founding member
of Google Brain Robotics. And,
he's known for influence work on
sample efficient reinforcement learning, and
gumball softmax. Zero shot, the
chain of thought, the prompting, and the self
improving reasoning systems.
And, let's welcome to Xin. And
his talk title will be the world of
war models.
Okay. Thank you very much for the invites.
For following the doctor Schmidt Huber sort
of new joke, I I'm Shane.
Chinese name is Shi Xiong, and should actually
represent the world I think
I was destined to give its talk on the war
model workshop.
Quick profile. I'm gonna a Japan born
Chinese Canadian PhD from Munich in Germany
in The US, so lots of places.
I just wanna take this time to congratulate my manager,
Tim Leder Craft, for just getting the IQRE test
time award. Also I work with
kinda. My goal is basically kind of two.
One is to to achieve AGI. So
anything that's and I
think AGI is almost kinda like
gentle modeling, work modeling. So that's
up. But the other is also
I wanna ensure that humanity stays empowered
post AGI. So as my side hustle,
I also say brought some Altman to
meet the prime minister of Japan. I just
recently brought Shane Legg and the post Asia
research team of Google DeepMind
attend the Davos of Japan. To really kinda
meet the political leaders. I can talk
about why this, kinda, like, connects
to world modeling. Later.
Before I start, I wanna kinda talk about
sort of the the phrase world model definitely has a, like,
tension. I really like
Schmidt Huber's, sort of
like papers. In fact, when I start my
research in 2012, my first paper that I read was
Schmitt Huber's paper on cosine, this kind
of evolution strategies. And
but also, you know, just
endramatic, another really big giant in
his field of AI, he also kinda said, you know,
really, you know, this kinda word term, word model
will actually confuse the community a lot.
That we already already have this dynamics model
in control theorist in 1960
talk about it. I highly encourage you to
watch not only just Schmidt Huber's This
Morning's pretty amazing talk, but
also, say, Jitendra's kind
of talk just to get more diverse
perspective to expand the word of, word modeling.
For me, I like to take kinda middle ground.
So when I look at doctor Schmidt Hoover's
writing, a lot of it is really
model based RO kind of terminology and those kinda
like really planning is like essential part of it.
So I basically defined the warped model as pretty
much the model in model based
And, the reason I cannot
less interested in this kinda action condition
video modeling, or, I mean,
definitely the driving force for the war model community,
but I think it's also more than that.
So and it's because, like, you know, before, say, 2018,
so, like, famous what model paper that termed
it, there were already, you know, a lot
of action condition video prediction
models. And, you know, they weren't, you know,
I'll argue some of those domains are actually
much harder than the kind of, like, one's demo
in 2018 paper.
And most recently, I think
people associate water model with, this
kind of like very old or aggressive
control model, video model like, Genie's
three. But
in this talk, I basically wanna
say the world model is recurrent beyond computer vision
and video modeling. I'll start
by the original you know, just the intelligence and how
world model is the core fit, and then
talk about the two aspect of it, predictions through
machine learning and predictions through
empowerment. Now explain those later.
Great. So first, define intelligence.
So, you know,
I I read Shang Lech's paper or watch
this kind of broadcast, maybe, like, ten years ago
or, like, eight or nine years ago.
But I I highly encourage you to take a look at
his 2007 paper, production,
definition of intelligence, and also
watch his talk from fourteen years ago
of the new metric called measuring intelligence,
which somehow only has
seven k views. But really,
like, there are a lot of definition for
intelligence, and then we kinda got too
long about it. But, essentially,
he, in his 2007 paper, he basically,
like, formulated the intrusions in
the passive environment. So he basically just
the passive observer of the world. Or if your
intelligence in the active environment, you can
act in the world. So what's the best
intelligence in the past environment? That's
basically the sort of one of induction. I can explain
later. But it's essentially
he mentioned the intelligence's ability of expropriatory
compression. Basically prediction.
It's basically to infer what's
that. So example is, for example, you have a
sequence prediction problem. The sequence
is generated from a program. So And
if you can predict the
next token or maybe the middle token,
of a program of a higher length or
complexity then, you have a higher intelligence.
It's very natural. It's defined as c test in
1998. The
other is kinda what Shane Legg talked in this
paper, which basically connected this and adds
some aural component. And he very
defined inclusions as agent's ability
to achieve goals in various environments.
This is a direct inspiration for DeepMind's
sort of our benchmark suites,
like a game environment, and, of course, the
OpenAI kinda gym as well.
I define intelligence.
Following this kinda shingling stuff by using warm
water terminology. So I define
intelligence as prediction. It's very natural.
So there are basically two ways of maximizing
prediction. So One is passive,
which is you fit your world model to the world.
This is the machine learning. This is gentle
modeling. The other thing is
you fit the world to your warped model.
And I can explain what this means. This is basically
empowerment RO. Essentially, you
can use water model to define conditions.
So predictions through MO. So
what is the best word model? So,
there's this kinda idea of, like, induction machines. So
assume this word is is is
written as a program of the hierarchy
or whatever. And,
we have a we have a program. We have a causal
program that generate the data.
So the best word model
is that given the data you observe in the world,
infer the program, infer the actual causal
program. That is the best board model.
So, you know, what?
And and
I I won't I may be abusing
some of the sort of rigor in academia,
but I I really like the sort of mode of induction
as a way to kinda explain it. But, essentially,
already talk about the best prediction as in frame the shortest
program to reproduce the data. So what
this means is that maximizing prediction,
which is just, you know, just law,
is gonna maximize the understanding
which is equivalent to inferring
the causal program of a phenomenon.
And, I think there was a very nice discussion
about how science is like that. So
scientific discoveries IQ tests,
moments, deep learning grokking,
physics phase transition. I think a lot of it
have this some kind of flavor. And before
the GPT one or before the GPT
two or GPT three, was
already this open hour sentiment neuron 2017
from Ida Siskaba. So
we already talked about, you know, if you just predict the next
word the Amazon review, the
neuron basically learned the the sentiments. You basically
learned the causality, gonna cause a program
of sentiment analysis. And,
of, obviously, you generate this kind of
video, naturally understands a lot
of this kind of what it means for
this kind of emotion.
So from this angle, I wanna
talk about, you know, what we can do. Right? So this maximized
motivation. So in this kind of passive
environment, say you're just stuck in your couch and you
just observing world, how can mostly
intelligence?
If you want if you if you learn a true
causal model, that by definition probably
means that you achieve all digitized
It's not just fitting your training data, it's fitting your
test data as well. Perfectly.
And, but the one issue is the non
spurious non causal spurious
data biases. So this is a 2019
paper, Merit Risk Recognization.
Which basically talk a lot about this, and then this is
kinda where I learned from. But
essentially, for example, if you look at the natural data,
in the world, it has a lot of spurious correlation. It's not
causal. A cow, cows
are often in the grass. Have
a cow that's in desert. You have a cow that the
in the, in the, architect.
So so essentially, the the MO
is very easy. It's just gonna pass the MO,
can very easily pick out this conspiracy
correlation. And in fact, interesting, if you work
on any kind of frontier model or like,
trained large engine model so that a lot
of time you basically just confiding the spurious
correlation. You have some bias in your,
say, SFD mixtures You have
some sort of in the in the aural mixture.
That can cause a lot of things. And for example,
very simple examples are like verbose
over robustity, or sarcophancy.
You can also definitely check out the lower
representational literature like independent component analysis,
VAE, contrasted learning, error of time, etcetera.
I added this slide because of the discussion
panel, but, essentially, the one
way to to really get this, how can you really get
the cause of your diverse data? And
one way is you in the real world,
right, you cannot
put a cow in the, you know, porta oil. I mean, you can photoshop
in that, and you can use nanobanana stuff.
But you you can also, you
know, create a program. So, you know, this is like a
tweet from nano research so I kinda liked
it. So I just like mentioned example here.
Just just like a simple example. But, essentially,
if you can write a program, right, you
can basically you can control the causal
graph of the world. And then you can use, you know,
Nanobana and stuff. It just kinda render to
the real image. Use that as a sort of
very, causally diverse
high signal kind of training data for predictive learning.
Another thing you want to know in this,
passive environment is that sure. You you
your passive you can,
for example, pass him on the couch, but he can pick
which YouTube video you're gonna watch. Right?
So there's still a bit of active
learning that you can do here.
And one is, the way you can
kinda see is one way to kinda
show why it's important is this dagger.
So training the word model
or imitation learning is actually
mathematical equivalent And they both
suffer from this,
compounding train test distribution shift.
Of, which basically you will incur,
you know, of t squared kinda error in prediction.
By the way, this is the first paper I recommend you to read.
For why you need RL
on top of self supervised learning or predictive
learning. Before you reading Sartan Bartel.
You should definitely read Sartan Bartel, but this is the first
paper I recommend you reading. So
But, essentially, to crack that, essentially, you
kinda mix, your
sort of, like, you you actually be
kind of fine. You know? Like, you don't
don't just throw out your own, in your pure
work model and do planning, but or to
for training, but you basically, like,
roll out in the mix of the real world and
then the your fed a world model.
And then so essentially, structure prediction
and then just, like, online learning is pretty,
equivalent. I have a kind of paper that talk
about sort of, you know, why you know,
basically, like, you can write all those imitation learning
objective get the versions of minimization,
and then, like, only thing that's different is the the
some of, like, like, where you take
the safe marginal and then there's
that. But essentially, like,
okay. Short story, minimize the distribution
shifts, and compounding the distribution shift.
The third way you can the thing you
can do is still active learning,
but you basically kinda use
so so we're not like Dagger. Right? We're not like Damas
Dagger. But we basically
search for YouTube video that can maximize
our information gain. Right?
So we have our own predictive world. We have our world
model. And then it can be
a a forward world model, inverse world model.
This describe difference later. But
essentially, you can use RL to
find the state of the maximizing information gain.
And there are a lot of, papers,
from sort of that use this
to incentivize exploration in, like,
a sort of rewards bars, RO back in, you
know, good old thousand sixteen,
two thousand seventeen days. And,
of course, there are people who connected that to
sort of performing physics
fermentation experimentation
active experimentation by the
AI to maximize information. So there are,
kind of good papers like that.
And I think the story about this
right? The reason I kinda said self
supervised learning is so powerful is that you
never wanna underestimate
this feature one model to the world.
Paradigm. It's so powerful.
Right? You know, the image generation, I
think, is the my favorite thing I like because it's so
easy to kinda put it. You don't have this, like, you know,
kind of video things. But just by looking
at, you know, where the video version model where it kinda
gets right, You can really kinda see
just by just by this kind of predictive training,
there there's so much that you can kinda cram into the
model and that a lot of it is we're kinda getting to, but I
call, you know, sort of model of induction or sort of true
understanding the causality of the image generation.
Pretty precisely.
Back in 2022, it's
pretty much like when I felt everything
about AGI is kind of doable.
There's the time that we wrote this paper called a large one
in model of their shelf reasoninger. Which
is basically we just added a lesson step by step. I think this
is the best sort of,
you know, innovation or, like, impact
per innovation
impact per min maximal impact, minimal
innovation kind of stuff paper that
put out the NERFs.
And also, you know, I was looking at the
so the imagine video during fusion back
then, and it had a lot
of artifacts. The resolution was very poor, but I think
I'm pretty sure that it's gonna gonna come.
And then 2025,
I know, the video model was scanned. So
this is also a paper we put up, like, a few months
ago. But essentially, the video model
itself already has a pretty strong reasoning
capabilities. In whether it's bidirectional
or regressive.
And it can just, like, do
a lot of, these are just
kind of prompting video models. But you can kind of feel the
intelligence. Right? You can feel the intelligence
in this kind of video models.
And this is only gonna start
as I mentioned, you know, there's, different
can be able a lot more capital one talent that can be allocated
for the word modeling.
Okay. So
predictions for impairment. I haven't defined
impairment, but I'll do it soon.
So the
second is you can fit the world to your work
model. So what does this mean?
This is a tweet. I think this went viral, like,
a few days ago. I
don't know if you and if you play Porti Market, I don't.
But, there's a guy
who basically plays, weather bets, you know, just
the temperature, And he basically went
up to to the, temperature measuring station,
input the dryer, to it, increase
temperature, poof, when, you know,
there's a 40 k dollars. So this
is a very,
you know, it's a very trendy recent
example. You fit the world to your world model.
What does it mean mathematically?
There's a famous sort of impartment paper from
that in Polanyi then Shaquiao was
found and brought into deep learning community.
Essentially, the impairment is
this maximization of the
mutual information between your actions
and the future state of the world.
So mathematically, you can kinda write in
this sort of, like, arrow environment ish thing.
I'll kinda explain a bit later, but essentially, like, you
know, z is know, I I basically
just mass you know, this is the definition of free
will. My mind, must not call the definition of free
will. But essentially, you have a z, which
is sort of like, the different option you can
take. And then you,
and depend on this, you're gonna act in the world.
Right? And you're gonna arrive at some
kind of state, the future. So if you're maximizing
information of that, and the funny thing is
this single equation captured
a previous one, which is the feature world mode of the world,
If you maximize this, if you write down version of
lower bounds, and then you maximize
this respect to the
the the the queue. Sort
of the sort of, you know, s given
z. So, you know, if you do this free will auction,
arrive at this world. You basically get
the standard word modeling.
And if you do the the other way,
if you optimize the policy that's part
of this defining, you know, what world
is gonna give them the free will, then you're
gonna, know, arrive at
this. It's gonna fit the world to the world model.
Kind of thing. And this, you can all only optimize through
RL.
Okay.
Paper, which is kind of very show emparmments
as a goal based RL. So if you kinda write this
emparmments stuff in the other way, sort
of like in in terms of freewill,
then you can actually kind of recover exactly
the generalization of the go go condition reinforcement
objective. It's basically go condition
reinforcement you run the representation
of the action space. So that's pretty much the goal conditionary
force modeling. The action space is defined as same
as some, like, state measurements.
You know, for example, you know, what's the x y coordinate you wanna
get? If you're learning that representation,
you basically kind of derive imparted. So go
waste reinforced mining, is
also the definition of that shingles,
paper. Shingles sort of
age, sort of
definition includes this kinda, like,
kinda goal based, stuff.
And I'll kinda talk about, like, inverse world
model. So I noticed probably I'm kinda, like,
running short a bit on time. I don't leave a bit
of time for the question and answer. But,
essentially, the you know, there's
a forward model and then there's a
inverse word model. The reason I use pi
and q, I'll connect explain later, it'll become clear
later. Right? And then if you're
familiar with robotics, you know, inverse kinematics,
visual surveying, a lot of, you know, kind of testing
to that. But
inverse world model provides a different way of
doing planning or the reward maximization.
So if you only have a forward model,
right, I mean, sure, you you can have some differentiable
stuff, but but in general,
you're basically doing shooting. You're basically sampling
actions then you're running out.
Then you can figure out which should I create I
led to it. Constraint for this is that
you you you can only
you you know, roll out using the
word model. Word model has to be oversatisfied.
But the other way is a direct collocation. So,
essentially, if you use a implicit
word model, what you're doing is you're
authorizing for the states. You're authorizing for the
states maximize the reward
subject to those states had to satisfy dynamics.
And if you do it, it's basically a constraint
optimization objective. You're basically putting
live rhino multiplier on top of that. So you can
relax dynamics.
You can break the world. You can break the world
you maximize objective. So what does it mean?
Right? So for example, this is
a paper that we wrote in 2022
of trying to do, this sort of assembly.
So this is, you know, this is a hard task. This is
a kind of fun thing, but we're mostly using shooting
basins. Methods. We're using PPO. We're using, you
know, just kinda forward, you know, MPPI kind
of stuff. And it's very, very hard.
It takes, like, billions
billions of environment steps. To
even learn with a lot of simplification we can
put in the environment.
For example, this is a 2012
paper by Igor Mordash, whom
I corroborated for the previous paper.
But he had this paper based on direct
location. So by relaxing
the dynamics or the word model,
you can solve the task and then fix the
physics. One kind
of analogy is like auto regressive video
generation. Where, you know, every frame has to be conditional
or bidirectional below diffusion.
We can kinda see kind of breaks the video, and
then you kind of gradually sort of, you know,
like, fix the video. So
this is very powerful. For example,
this kinda like having this humanoid
to stand up. This is a very contact rich task.
I was, like, insanely impressed when I saw
this.
Or this kinda in hand manipulation,
which is a very Heidi dexterous
task, which is very kinda hard to optimize
if you don't relax physics.
So So, you know, there's that.
Okay. Back to the notation.
So we know the inverse water model is very
powerful. I
will kinda explain how it connects to that.
So, essentially, if you look at
this, right, looks
like a policy function. It's like it getting the action
given the, you know, the future
state. Just like a q function. You know?
So for example, the the goal condition
q function and thanks to
Kevin who mentioned the buzzword, the the temporary
abstracted word, essentially,
this is a 2018 paper, but essentially
go condition q function. Sure.
If I only have q function for single task, that
doesn't know too much. It's way
below in the information compared to what model.
But if you look at the goal condition q function,
if your q function is defined by so the
reward that basically tells you after
how many steps, it's gonna what's
the distance between your state you reach
then the goal state you provide. If you learn a
q function for that, actually as
powerful, in fact, is more general than
the word model. A single step word model.
So it's basically implicit
temporary abstracted word model.
And then for this training, you can use this kind of
high resound variable and trick. For this, like, this herd
trick.
And you can use this to do planning.
So in this paper for kind of simple environments,
rebase did the planning using q
function.
Another kind of thing that connects
the decision transformer. So decision
transformer is a is
also a inverse word model. And,
how it's gonna train is it will
take and and we have this paper
in 2000, '22
that basically generalized decision transformer because,
original transformer, yeah, again, just a single
reward skater. But this is basically
kind of making in general, right, like, anything.
Essentially, what you have is that you have a
causal we have a policy that's basically a
causal transformer. Because
policy is causal, war modus causal. But you
also have a sort of
anti causal aggregator that basically
take any kind of future
information. So, again, you can illustrate condition on
any future you agree. If you do
that behavioral crawling, and you can have a arbitrary
bottleneck. Right? A bottleneck can be just like
a single state, which reduce the goal
condition reinforcement learning, goal condition
behavioral crawling, and that's
So, essentially, like, you know,
decision transformer, a much more model.
I haven't done planning with it. You know?
Essentially, that you can do planning using
this formulation, the drug location.
Haven't done that, but
essentially, model is a causal predictor.
Decision transformer, is
a anti causal predictor. So
I'll say, we're not really losing much
if you're trying this kind of, like, general
decision transformer. And I actually
even wrote the hindsight terms rephrase, the July mind trick
to flip the causality.
That's like old tweet.
And this is my bitter lesson. You know, back in
thousand nineteen, there's a Corey called Corey Lynch.
Yeah. He he is the one who basically taught me the bitter
lesson as our researcher.
This is probably the most natural
deactivation policy I saw in 2019.
There's no model free
model based ROC match this. And
it was only just hindsight
behavior crawling. It's a hindsight just hindsight behavior
crawling, respect to goal
condition objective. And
then the, basically, the decision transformer,
and then recently, right, there's this, like,
Jay, by the way, you know,
Pete Florence. He he's also ex colleague from
Google Brain. He writes a kind of bitter
bitter sort of, taste, but he basically said go
somewhere important and label some of your
tools. He's basically talking,
shouldn't follow too much of that. I think
it's fair. You know, we should have many different views.
And I
and then we have, you know, kinda like
essentially, you know right now, I think
I I don't know if there are, you know, exactly
decision I don't know all the details, but
I think it's very close to that.
So still, I think this, like, game is gonna happening.
Okay. Great. Thank you very much.
So my recommendation, think about word models.
Intelligence is predict the world, but also
realize your world. Prediction
ML can benefit from costly diverse data,
minimize the insurance shift in fusion gathering,
Prediction by environments is go waste to a r l as a
representation running and goal based value function,
decision transfer, inverse forward models.
Inverse word models could be more powerful
than word models. And then you should definitely
think about what's the post stage IVR do you
want? And fit the world to your world model.
Great. Thank you very much.
Okay. So we have time for two questions, I think.
We move on to the next session.
Yeah. So one thing that I, that was
really interesting was when you were talking about the
idea of, fitting
the world to your model, which seems like a
a kind of a fascinating idea. And I
guess I had two questions related to that. One was
if you're doing something like that and you need to, like
you said, fix the dynamics after the fact,
does this sort of enter into a sort of iterative
loop where I relax my dynamics I
learn a policy that's actually solvable with
those dynamics, and then
I sort of fix my dynamics and then
relearn my policy Yeah. Guess,
first
Yeah. Yeah. So in fact, like, you don't
need to fix your dynamics. You know? If you're
extremely powerful, then you can
have a very twisted world model that's very different
from the natural distribution of the world, So
we can do a lot of action to,
change that. That's actually kind of more of
the kind of go what the goal condition, the
RO, and stuff is kinda like doing. It's basically
learning to to to be
a power in the controlling dynamics of the world.
Yeah. I think you're kind of talking is, like, this kind of,
like, intuitive loop of
you know, the know, basically like
relaxing the word model and then correcting
it. Yeah. So, like, that that's a very powerful
sort of optimization objective. So even
when we if you do kind of model free RL,
I think even some of something like that kind of
idea could be useful. Thank you.
And, yeah, one more. I guess,
was, earlier on you were talking about,
I guess, like, causal structure in
in data when you're learning world models. And
I was wondering if this
idea of, like, relaxing the world model that you're using
so that it's not actually following the full dynamics
is sort of fundamentally incompatible with
capturing causal dynamics. In
your underlying system, or is there some way to kind of
bridge them together?
Sorry. Could you repeat it again?
Yeah. So if, if I'm trying to
like, causal structure in the dynamics of my world
model, is this idea of,
relaxing the dynamics so that I can solve
the task more, just sort of fundamentally
incompatible with doing causal discovery or
is it kind of something that you can maybe
bridge the two together by iterating on
the process kind of similar to what we were saying before?
Yeah. So to me, this is like inverse word model.
Right? It's pretty much like the inference. Like,
it's sort of like given, you know,
you know, given the given sort of kind
of feature, kind of state of the world, I
what's the causal steps we can take to reach that?
I I seem to learn it's almost kind of
representation learning, but I
essentially to
you know, to to learn, like, a good causal
word model, you kinda need this,
like, causally diverse data.
From, like, a different
places. And to learn, like, a very good to
learn to do this kind of causal inference well, right,
like, inverse word model well,
then yeah. I think you or you're clearly gonna
need similar kind of mixture
of data. There was, like, a lot of
a few paper and things written before
about sort of, like, is the anti causal
prediction better than causal prediction direction?
You know, which one can, you know, lead to better
representation learning, but I think there's no
full consensus there. So,
but, yeah, I think there's a a lot of stuff to,
a lot of analogy there. Yeah.
Great. Yep.
Thank you very much.
You're able to smart screen?
Hi, Hau. Can you hear us? Oh,
yes. Yes. Yeah. We're just
setting up the visuals on this end, so we
we'll be ready to go in a sec.
Okay.
Cool. So happy to introduce our last speaker for
the day, is Hao Hsu. Who's a distinguished
professor at Fudan University and dean of the Fudan
Institute of General Intelligence.
Howe is leading researcher in embodied
AI, three d vision, robotic and
physical world modeling. Before Fudan, he
was ten year associate professor at UC
San Diego where he directed the
Embodied Intelligence Lab. His work
has had broad impact through systems and database
datasets such as ShapeNet,
PointNet, Sapien, and ManyScale.
So it's advancing how AI systems perceive,
simulate, and act in the physical world.
Please, join me in welcoming Hau.
Thank you very much for the introduction.
And thank you everyone for being here.
The title of the talk is The Evolution
of Physical Understanding.
The question that Motive is the one
on the screen. What happens
if I push this in the regime
I haven't trained on?
Now the question is going to come back several
times today. And the answer I will
suggest, is something
we, as the field, have been
quietly avoiding.
K. So we are
at a strange moment in our field.
Two very different kinds of systems are
now both being called world
models. On the left,
geometric reconstruction like DASTR three
r, master three r,
VGGTT, three d g s, RM,
including my own work, like
one, two, three, four, five, mesh RIM, and
including the industrial,
work at WERLabs. This gives you
the words the world's structure and
fidelity unimaginable five
years ago. On the
right, on generative simulation
like SARA Cosmos, or Vue.
And this will give you the world's appearance
and that they are stunning.
So both are remarkable and both
deserve a place on this
stage.
But here's the awkward truth.
The Bose can render
beautiful appearances
but neither can answer this. So
what happens
if I push the same glass
with twice the force.
The word twice is doing real work
in that question. Of course, a
video model can show you a glass breaking is
seen plenty. But it
can't tell you what the performance
does to the same class because
it doesn't have a force variable in the
first place. It only had frames.
And a geometric reconstruction give you
perfect the mesh of the glass
but it could tell you whether twice the force
fractures it or just
slice it across the table. The
same scene, the same hand pushing,
but a different push. And
neither paradigm answers that.
So I want to, suggest
something stronger than we'll figure it out. And
my view is that this isn't an
engineering gap and it's a structural one.
A parallel causal hierarchy, I think, already
gave us the language for twenty five years
ago. We just haven't pointed out
at ourselves yet. K?
So before
we go to prod, I want to start,
much further back. Like 1979.
James Gibson
in the ecological approach to visual perception
says we must
perceive in order to move.
But we must also move
in order to proceed.
So the interesting structural fact
about a sentence is the word also.
Perception isn't a one way pipeline that produces
its representations. It's locked
into a loop with action.
And the most of what we now call world
models optimize the first half
of that loop. But the
hard work is the second half.
The part that says perception only earns its
repetitions by acting
in a world.
K. Let's
get specific. So
The phrase world model has come to mean
three different things, actually. And
to live at different levels of how
much they are really learning about
the world. So
type a, generative simulator,
like SARA Cosmos Vue,
and, for example, also vJAPA,
on passive video, So mathematically,
it's about p of observation
given a condition, and this is
passive observation. The model has watched a lot
of video, It has not
yeah, a lot of but it but it's there's
no intervention. And there's also
the type b That's the action condition
predictor. This is where, like, Dreamer, the
TDMPC family from,
my lab our
homewt, which is at this ICLR,
vJAPA two and Cine all
live. So they predict an s a
date under your action.
And, mathematically, that's about
p over the net z, given the current z,
and, well, in language,
that's two z. Or do a or some
kind of an action. And this is a real
intervention learning. Or
it's locally in an environment. And
within the training regime. So I also want
to, be very precise about that.
So they've done something and
they're but they are not just the
watching.
And there's a type c. That's the cross regime
structure.
It has the same dual action, but
now it well, you
hear by, cross regime,
you'll have to extrapolate to a
regime that you didn't train on.
Like new mass scales
Hello?
Okay. Okay. It might be some network problem.
Okay. Like, new contact
mechanics, new articulation,
This is the open frontier. And to get
here, we need structural,
physical priors. And without them,
you don't get c no matter
how much data
So that's the talking one sentence.
Well, b is real progress,
but c is what we we
still don't have and sum
started to struggle with it. And
going from b to c requires
structure not just the compute,
not just the more data.
Okay. So here's
why I don't think this is only a machine
learning problem. Well,
because three
completely independent fields like, three communities
that mostly don't talk to each other,
have walked into the same picture.
Like, the pill kit started
from watching the children,
the infants, and cognitive neuroscientists
are just from brain imaging
and evolutionary biologists started
from comparing species. And then all of
them set out to draw the same up, but then ended
up here.
So, here, let me show you one
of, like, kind of a general picture. So
four layers. Now layer one, that's
about the perception. It's recognizing
what's in front of you. Well, in
our brain, that's the ventral stream of the visual
cortex. In a baby, this
comes online it first has very
much. Like tracing tracking
the face and like distinguishing the
mother And the evolution, we trace
it all the way back to the comparing.
Once I is evolved, this layer becomes
a possible So every animal with
eyes has it, and this universal layer,
And there comes the second layer, which is
the space. So this is,
like, where things are relative to you
relative to each other. So
in our brain, the dorsal system,
stream, the dorsal stream,
the intraperipheral, surface
corresponds to the understanding of the space.
And in Bay Bay, this closed in
around three to six months. When you start
to rating, things. And
the spatial attention comes online. So
in evolution, every
vertebrate, a fish navigating a coral reef,
is actually solving the layer two. That's
still common. And today, people like to call it, like,
space a spatial analysis.
And then there's, one more layer.
And this is the one I really
want you to look at. So notice
that the neural substrate has sifted,
That's the,
anterior iPS plus the promoter cortex.
We are already
in the motor territory now, not
only the visual territory. And
in big a bit, this actually comes online between
three and a half and
topmost. In Spelch's classic
looking time experiments,
That's like the period when the infants
stare longer when
a hidden object appears to pass through the wall.
So, like, the
infant's physical expectation has
been violated If that happens,
then you can read that violation in
the eyes of the big b. And
here on Lushan, only Chorus
and Great Apes the ability
Like the pros, the bend wires into
hooks and the chimps like stones.
For cracking us.
So this layer is actually very rare.
And it's actually very hard to gather.
And that's the one believe,
like, the real world model
should target that.
And then I would say, like, there's
STALL, like, another layer that's the called the layer forward.
It was the behavior layer. So
that corresponds to, like, multistep planning.
Like, chaining actions in time.
That in our human brain is about, like,
the the promoter cortex, the m one,
and the cerebellum.
So if you're, you know,
unrelated the developmental psychology,
That's about, like, eight to twenty four months in
babies. So the first,
about, like, walking ability and then the stacking
and then about, like, like, like, assembling. And
you see there's a curricula. So So
the permit, survival
expansion is what let these layers go up.
So now
for the neural localization
here, this not a subtle
effect. Fisher at all, it
published this, finding in PNAS 2016.
And they actually ask the humans to make intuitive
physical judgments.
Like will a stack
of blocks fail? Right?
No. Which way will this
tower's tip? And the
like, the same time, imaged
the brain of the person performing or answering the
the or performing the task. Or answering
questions. So the region that lit
up was the premotor cortex.
And not the visual cortex. So somehow, it's
about, like, the physical understanding that's,
like, in our brains, a
lip is a special, region,
and it's like, lips where you plan to act.
Not really just to, like, where you see.
Okay. So here, I wanna say,
like, like, the physical understanding
is not just a expansion
of perception. It's the foundation of a
behavior And I think, like, having a certain
the sense of of of separating the four layers
of intelligence help us,
perhaps, to think about the structure
problem.
Okay. So I just don't
want to make a claim here. Hopefully,
people will agree If there's
no understanding, there's no real
generalization,
And also, a set
second statement that if
you don't talk about, like, interaction,
you don't talk
about understanding in a full scale.
So that's the spine of this talk.
And you'll see, like,
let me make it concrete.
So the reason I think this is right framing
is that watched the four different research communities
walk into the same wall and, actually,
that also aligns with my own research
experiences. Like, although the work I've done.
For example, like, the geometrical structure
the video generation, and the action
condition, the latent dynamics learning, And,
also, I want to mention the BLA, which
has been very popular
these these days.
So they use different tools that
have different data, and
they actually also have different cultures, but they're converging.
On the same open question. And
let me go through them, including
routes I work on and locate a question where
I think it actually lives.
So the route one, geometric reconstruction.
And this is a lineage
I have been part of for, like,
fifteen years. From the
work like ShapeNet, Poincet,
to more recently work
like Mesharam, I've been working
on that. So whatever I'm
about to say next, I'm actually
also, talking about, like, my own work too.
So And here is what I think
is true. And
so, this route delivers
the geometry, but it does not direct directly
deliver the Fiddics. Now imagine
the strongest geometric reconstruction
kind. A robot stands
in a in a perfectly reconstructed
kitchen and it knows every surface
post So it does not know what
is heavy and what shutters at
a touch. Or what bends.
So a basic stops at layer two,
or, like, the spatial intelligence layer of
hierarchy I just showed you. And that's
not really a failure. Route
was just never aimed at the layer three.
And I think I don't think it would be fair
to judge it a goal it didn't set.
And then the route two
mentioned, like, the the the generative video, like,
the SARAC Cosmos video. And
these models actually learn
the p of a video given that text. They don't
learn the p of a video given certain
do action. Well,
so the practical consequence is exactly
what we saw the second slice.
The when the video model produces
a clip of, glass shattering,
it is sampling from, like, video test
tends to follow the prompt. But not predicting
this physical system under this Boris,
So the big pixels are beautiful and prompt
is satisfied, but there's actually no
real false variable inside the model.
Or at least I I I
do not quite believe that
or, you know, I don't see
sufficient evidence that, internally, the
model actually does
have left precise location
for the force or say, like, the concept of force
has really emerged. So push
the same glass with twice the force, and you don't
get an answer. Just get a different
sample for the same prompt distribution.
So now the
empirical evidence is
is not really ambiguous. Like, for
the phase world. Field world,
that's like a a work published
at last year's IKEA, was designed
exactly to test this So they
trained on video generation model on
physical scenes and stress test them in distribution,
out of distribution. So for the in distribution
result, they this in near perfect
prediction. But for the out of distribution,
the physical regularities don't merely
fail. To converge as you
scale up actually well, when you scale up, they
degrade. So bigger models
in their setting actually will also
actually got worse on physics, but not better.
So this is, wow. This
this is the kind of result that's give us
a pause. Because the world's
default reflects when something doesn't work.
Is a cryptoscope. Like okay.
So this this like, the the fields,
well, is is I think, like,
it's trust in scaling, trust in computing,
but probably facing
this kind of, OLD problem,
Phoenix. It reminds
us still, perhaps, think about structure.
So, like, now generation, is
not really intervention, and what team is not
really doing, and there's a boundary. Now,
between observing the world and acting upon
it. This is
the boundary address I talked about.
The third, sort of lie. Third lie.
Well,
so this is the family.
I I personally
put them, you know, a
lot of my energy
in in the past five years. So,
also, we're I my
own work, like, I call it the world the model
lives. So I wanted to be especially
careful here. For the line of work
like Dreamer, TDM, PC family,
the beach alpha two, Jenny,
or the Altamam are of this client.
So they predict with action conditioning
So they basically,
supposedly learn p over the next
z, given the current z and some
du a. Either
the z is like a explicit
reputation or an implicit reputation.
So here, the action is a kind of intervention,
and this is is and this is
genuine intervention interventional
work. So the
model has done something to the world. It's just not just
watching it. Well,
to make a concrete
I just, show you a four year
art. From my own work.
Just within the TDMPC.
So, the first work of TDMPC
was at ICML twenty eight twenty two.
So That's about to you learning
a latent dynamic model and past
TD learning. And plus
imagined model
predict control. And that was
well, verified to work for a single
task and it does show sample efficiency.
And we were very excited And
then we pushed it further and published
a second work in iClicker twenty
twenty four. That's the TDM piece two.
That's a scaled up version of it,
so that works on multitasks.
And it does have, seen much
more robust visual encoders
So a lot of the visual
fragility I've been worried about
earlier. Addressed at
this version. And then
there is the latest one, the new.
Published after this conference. So we actually
have the paper, and it's very clear with Nicholas
Neitz and Shiloh. On that,
that one has a long reach condition.
And use some pretraining. So here, the
demo per training plus the online
fine tuning, shows that,
it's able to like, jointly
train across 200 tasks.
So, the headline I wanna land
here is, like, the online model
based learning does scale.
That's actually, empirical statement
now. Not
a hope as before. But
here, is what
even the new the does
not do. Okay.
For the newt, there is a latent
world model, but
it's it's only for, like,
within, regime, interpolation
yet. It's still not really a strong
tool for cross regime extrapolation.
So if you trained in regime a,
one mass scale and one contact
model, or a type
of articulation topology and the deployment
in regime b the
model, is is will will not really
transfer. Okay? So,
that's actually the
response to actual the pro
point, and I'll get to the math in a in a few
slides. So,
my read on this family
that actually has the right warrant
is about leveraging the real intervention
But now, you know, well, the
experiments are, like, all kind
of locally. So the open
question becomes my view is,
like, isn't do you have action
for this line of of of of work?
But it becomes, like, what construct
your priors will let interventional learning
as trap lit, instead of only
interpolate and I'd really hope this
workshop takes this question seriously.
Okay. I actually
also want to mention the BI a
bit. Even though, you know, this is not
directly a world model. So
the route for the
BLA usually takes the beyond backbone plus
some kind of action head. Our representative
works like RG two, like the Openvala,
like the pack PyTorch,
like the Helix or Octo.
So, where this family is strongest
is is generally strong. And I wanna
give that credit before I get to the limits.
So if I ask in plain English and then get a
reasonable plan, the same model can handle
a wide range of tasks.
You know, within, familiar
domains. Maybe, most importantly, the
interfaces are human readable.
So when something goes wrong, you can breed the model's
intent. And last one is, and
and well, that last point
sometimes is underrated.
And, well, none of the other three routes
match it. But
so the route actually
has its own general strength, but it also in her
is the same structure challenge as route three.
And top it, it has two more difficulties of
its own. Okay.
The first is the action data itself.
Even though the largest open corpus
we have, like, an open x embodiment,
is pulled
across, many like, over
over over 20 robots.
Still on the order of just a million trajectories.
It sounds a lot, but, until we pair
it with, like, the text,
that allows the
GPTs to generalize. So,
the real intervention learning
well, a happens
inside that meeting.
So the the cross regime extrapolation
still does not emerge.
And then the second is more subtle.
It's like the physical understanding
the BA in hers from the
BOM is
grounded indirectly that's through the text
descriptions of FIDDIC. Really a
measure of the force. And let's throw the
passive images of the physical scenes.
So, the issue was, like, you
know, when the
when you start to fine tune the VLMs,
using certain, well, additional
data with force, you also
see the decay of
the original reasoning ability of
the original VLM. It becomes,
well, unfortunate that some of the existing abilities
are losing, and, still,
the new data is not
like, getting, enough.
Negative samples, to allow
it to really learn from the the
the type of of intervention.
Okay. So
it's a different starting point from the raw three.
But it's still, like,
meets at the same open frontier.
Okay. So,
now here is just the, like, a kind of
a a table that summarizes the
situation. I think that I I won't
read the table, details, just like a
summarization of what I was presenting
just now.
Okay. So, that's
not really just an untrue argument.
The benchmarks have given us empirical evidences,
plainly. Like, for some
of the work, new reps are not clear.
For this work of,
Pfizer. That's
that's the kind of
like, the
the the physical outcome prediction
and it's comparing human and
the current vision models So
it does see a, a 20%
gap. And then there are
further evidence, like, by the Calabrio dataset.
That does the counterfactual reason
contrafactual video reasoning. So
it also tests the descriptive,
tasks. The interesting part becomes, like,
you know, if you are asking
the screw a task, like, what just happened in
the video clip, that's essentially
a kind of a round one task if
you include the pros, a language
that would've worked generally well.
But if it goes to the counterfactual kind
of work, then the success rate
will drop sharply.
And then I think, I mean, like, the
the the that's the five word I just, I mentioned.
So you you you do see,
the limitations Well, for
this kind of a word model when it
comes really to the cross region
case to the counterfactual reasoning kind of
challenges. So,
this kind of also, like, comes
to the agreement that
only scaling up the observational data
is not via the interventional
level of generation.
Okay. So, if if we are using more
rigorous language, of of three d Pro,
these are, the forms,
like, level one of the run. Is
the association. Right? That's about
learning the
the the correlation, you can say.
That's like if you show show
you a million videos, you can learn that
the glasses when dropped tends to shatter.
Okay. That's a kind of a correlation, what passive
observation bias you It's useful,
but it's not yet causal. And
then there's level of intervention,
That's like, well,
if it's
about the p y of giving the two x.
That's like if a glass tends to shatter
when it falls, changes
to you know, like, if I were
to drop this glass, it will
shutter. So you don't need an ability.
Be able to conduct experiments
and then to be able to learn from
the the data actively
performed experiments.
Okay, by the experiments. I've done this
well, the the runs three, that's the the the counterfactual
level. It's about imagining. That's the
hardest one. Well,
like, you may ask the question,
had I dropped it from half the height?
Would it still half shattered?
Okay. That's another layer that's
not only, like, changing, like, the action to
it, but also
changing the, the the
the the state. You should be able to make the kind of
prediction. So if you are able
to do that, you must be able to understand
the real causality. Behind
it. So to put it short,
you can, have
a centerpiece result That's the causal,
hierarchy theorem. Like, almost surely,
no wrong distribution could determine a
round two distribution. Now
if you were to check the original statement, that's actually
based upon a a kind of mathematical
proof. Okay. So I would
say for a lot of so called
word model learning and purchase, they're all learning
from the, well,
passive data. And they are all of
the run one type. And then
fundamentally, it it
rules you out from the possibilities of real
understanding, like, the intervention.
Okay. So you do not see the
pros of your team of generative ability.
Okay. So comes to the point
of a virtual lesson. I also saw,
Sean talking about, his his own
bit less than, but but I would
also, refer to this literature.
So here, for
the Sudden '19
2019, a famous
write up, the picture lesson, it gave us
kind of an understanding of the general message plus
the computed beast to 100 properties.
But sometimes, this I think is is
misread as, like, don't design just a skill.
Okay. So the premise cropped, cannot
misread this. I think the most
important sentence in sentence piece,
So general method work because they capture
the right structure.
Like, transformer plus attention
captures the the structure of language and the
TD learning plus phoneme, equation
captured the structure of sequential decision.
So the scaling worked there because the
structure was there to scale.
But the question for us isn't
design versus scale. It becomes, like,
what's should we design for physical
understanding? And I would
tell you, like, I do not really have a question.
But I think I'd
like to, make this kind of a statement
that we do need to structures.
Help such a scale.
Okay. So,
let me check. Yeah. So,
so evolution had built NVIDIA's compute,
and they tried a lot of things. And then the
things, it converged on when faced
with how to acquire the physical understanding. It
was not, like, just a watch more video. It
becomes the
the learning behavior
of infants, like throwing, like pushing,
like, maybe grasping,
even putting things in a mouse.
So I also wanna be careful with the
word embodiment because it's
now today, it gets, like, thrown around.
Embodiment isn't just a body bolted.
Onto AI. It is the admission
that no intervention no
physical understanding. And
the physical causality actually
had a spatial structure. So forces have
application points So
directions, and transmission passes.
Three d, I'd argue, is is natural
inductive bias. And that's part
of why a full stack. This lineage
of three d, not just to the pixels.
Well, And then
there's the practical question, or where do
we get intervention data? The
real world intervention data is expensive.
That scales slowly and at a high cost.
For the virtual or physical worlds,
the scalable complement. It's a lineage
I've been building. Since the
2020. From my work of CPEN,
of a simulation engine of articulated object
physics to, you know, the space
of the, manipulation tasks.
Where
we see well,
today, that the simple
skills for the simple scales, if
you wanna do the same to real test,
the bottleneck is on the vision.
Today, for the complex scales, the
fact, we don't quite see vision as a bottleneck
instead of the physics is still.
Okay. So, the benchmark
with less contribution than
a diagnosis. And,
we keep to is poor,
Wow. How do we really implement,
like, the the the the idea of three
d is is natural inductive
bias. And for the last year's
CORO work, this work that's called
UniqloS, we were trying to
inject the point cloud kind of,
data structure
into a learned word model,
and, hopefully, that help
us to align the
simulation world better with the real world.
So there, we did see a tenfold improvement
over a GNN,
And lately, we see
work from the Momo bots from Allen Institute,
That's about really working
on the important preliminary tasks,
using the simulation data.
Which we can also say is kinda world model.
And, well, the the training policy
transferred to the real world with high success
rate.
So I just say, like,
the virtual tour real process and perfectly
working. At least for certain regimes.
The process is open.
Okay. Okay. So I'd like
to lastly ask you one question.
Of what the next representation must
satisfy. Okay.
So, if you take
the argument series after this point,
then the three hard requirements will follow.
Well,
I think the first one is, like, you to
come from intervention. I'm not going to explain more
because I think I've spent enough time on it.
And the second is that the repetition
must encode spatial code
of structure So FIDEX has the spatial
structure, an application
points, the transmission pass, the contact topology.
Now if the representation doesn't catch
carry that structure, it it'll
be very hard to recover the right behavior
from any amount of data. K? It can
be emerged, but at least there needs to
be certain kind of, like, in my
in my in my understanding, it's like some
kind of prior
that induced the emergence of the proper
structure. So that it
transfers. Well,
and then the third is the training signal has
to be tied to action consequences.
Not only the appearance, which
is quite a problem of computer
vision people needs to be aware The
PSR in the connotimetric people use
quite a lot. Learning a word model.
But I think that might not be
the best metric. Probably,
we would think of action success more
or action rewards more
to be the the correct motivation.
Or the signal to train the word model. So
here, we proposed the concept of, like,
actionable three d. The claim is that
physical intelligence, the most useful criteria
for three d understanding is
how much the representation
enables action success rate on
especially the unseen physical tasks.
Okay. So she has an RFI
or classification accuracy. They're all useful,
but they're not, perhaps not the
the the the right primary measure for this purpose.
Okay. So
Okay. So so I wanna spend
some extra time on this side. That is where
I think we have the most useful and perhaps
the least explored, handhold.
Okay. So if you ask me what's the proper
architecture or what's the key architecture,
I of maybe a well,
kind of a world model that allows FIDDIC
to extract it to some extent or say,
to be able to really capture the causality,
Well, basically, to me, that's the same meaning.
Is probably very hard to commit to today.
And honestly, actually, I don't know.
Because it just within the past five years,
I think I changed my mind of the trifectin,
the proper architecture.
But I wanna say something that probably
will be invariant for the next few years,
which is, like, the capabilities
physical understanding must demonstrate
well, which is from kind of, benchmark
perspective. Well,
they are the ones that have been settled for decades
by developmental psychology, and I think we
should anchor on them.
Okay. The first is well,
well, I'd like to enumerate, like, three
three capabilities that every human infant have.
Before, like, the 12.
Months each one calls for a different
kind of research effort. And
the first is the composition. It's
about, like, if I understand the part behavior
and I understand the behavior of composing
them, are you able to read them both, like, the behavior
of the whole? This is a kind of a
SpellKit's core knowledge program, and
what this needs is like, some kind
of a conversational or
object centric structure. In representation
and this kind of a architectural
commitment. A second
type is the permanence.
Well, here, is
about objects needs to persist
through allclusion and through interactions.
Like for pure to stage four, sensor
motor ability, like eight
to twelve months in inputs. Now
what this needs is at least,
I believe, some kind of memory ability.
It's like persistent state mechanisms.
And this is also architectural.
But it's kind of a different architectural
commitment than composition.
And then there's a level of, like, like, the counterfactual
expectation. That's
about to anticipate alternative outcomes.
And the and and, you know, the the
ability to surprise
when expectation is violated.
So this is like the the large
a violation of expectation paradigm
I noticed and this is a cognitive precursor.
Browse runs ready. So what this needs
is, like, some kind of intervention data and plus
some structural priors in my
opinion, for the ODE generalization.
This one is mostly a data and signal
problem, but, also, it involves certain
architectural design.
Okay.
I think my these three capabilities
are essential. And they actually are three
different kinds of work. Perhaps
we don't see them converge very early.
Perhaps you'll see a lot of people
starting to build the system with
all these abilities together.
Okay. So so,
so
Hear me?
Hello? Yeah. We can hear
you now.
This paper titled a lightweight library for energy
based joint embedding predictive
architectures. That's a round of applause for
Basile.
Thank you very much for the presentation. Actually,
I'm I just transitioned to Emi
Labs to continue my PhD, still
with the same supervisors.
So not meta anymore. This
is, this
is a code based paper named Ibi Jepa,
for energy based joint abutting predictive
architectures. The whole goal of this
project was to build a cut
base that allows people to iterate
fast and onboard fast.
On, the literature of JPA's word
models.
So yeah, basically,
we illustrate that this code base is very
simple and modular. With the three minimal
examples that kind of summarize
the the literature
on that, we go from image representation
learning to word
models which is on the right.
Here named action, condition, video, word
models. And we do planning with
those word models. We was kind
of the end goal of the
JETL literature.
So, yeah, the motivation for this paper, as I
said, is, to present JPAZ
from image to word models, so the whole span
of it. The whole idea of JPAZ
is to avoid pixel
space prediction. Because
the downshoot the downstream task were introduced interested
in is not generation, but
decision making task essentially, like,
classification, segmentation, word modeling, robotics, etcetera.
The existing code bases, that we
had a few months ago
were, mostly research code bases that were
quite large scale. So we wanna we
wanted to make a code base that was adapted for
students and and
researchers that start in the domain.
And we wanted to unify those three examples
that I gave which is like image
SSL, video SSL, action
action condition word modeling. And there
the whole view of energy based
models. Which is a literature that
dates back to the the eighties with
the Hopfield and the the simple
idea between, behind, energy
based models is that you you
wanna define or learn an energy function, which is
a scalar positive function
that, should be interpreted
as the likelihood of a two
pool of input of inputs being
associated one to another. This triple
of inputs in this case is,
a state x, a state x prime, and an
action and the question is
whether this action leads from
x to x prime. And the three examples
that we will give here fall into this representation.
We define this energy function e as a
prediction in embedding space in the
in the in the J PAL literature because of
the motivation I I mentioned earlier.
For images, there's no actions, and we wanna
learn an encoder that's invariant
to augmentations. For, the simple
video example, we want to perform
temporal prediction. So x and
x prime are just the past and the future.
And the final example is
with an action. And that allows to perform planning.
When we train such energy
based, JPA models,
the big risk is collapse.
There's a lot of paper that avoid collapse
with, like, stop gradient, EMA,
But here, we wanna focus on the setup
where the entire collapse mechanism is
really decoupled from the production mechanism.
That happens in two papers that some
of you may know, like Vic Craig or
more recently, Lojepa, which introduces
the Sigreg
wanna mention that SIGREG is a more
like, it's a it's a more constraining
anti collapse that imposes a constraint on
the whole distribution of embeddings. At
at the exit of the encoder. Whereas Vicreg
is only on the second moments. Variance and
the covariance.
Oh, yeah. And for word models, we need
some other regularizers like
the inverse dynamics loss or time similarity
loss, which I will discuss after. So for
the image example,
most of you know how it works. We
produce views of the same image. We embed
them in an encoder. We compute the loss
in the embedded space. Which
is, for example, the l two loss with
our regularizer denoted
r here, which can be Vicreg or
Siegfried.
In in the paper associated to the code base, we
show some key insights when using,
our code. If you use CGRIG,
you better be careful about, the
output dimension of the projector
in which, at at the exit of which
you compute the the the training loss.
Because as I said, it's it's a much stronger constraint,
so the output dimension of the projector
should be much smaller than the crate.
Right? Whereas, when using when using Vic
Ray, it's better to have a
projector that expands your
embeddings to and you wanna decorrelate
dimensions of your embedding.
And, yeah, for both, obviously, having a
projector is
discarded at evaluation is very useful.
So what you see here is the
is the, is the validation accuracy
on Cypher 10 of, very small models
trained on a single GPU for a few hours.
So, yeah, that's the key insights for the image that
you that you could try yourself.
For a video,
basically, this is the simplest example. So we wanted
to give a minimal example that's
still showcases the cavits and the
collapse modes that you wanna avoid when
training a JEPAS, So So in the video
JIPA here is like moving a mist. You have just numbers
bumping on the walls. And
you want to learn this deterministic dynamics,
like, there is no deceleration, acceleration.
It's just completely,
predictable dynamics. And
you want to learn an encoder and predictor,
Stricts that, when you at
inference at inference are gonna unroll
your predictor, you're gonna
predict well the positions of the numbers in the
future. Some
ablations, on
this on this video example.
Here, you see the variance, covariance, regularizer
loss on the left. In the middle,
you see the production loss decreasing throughout training.
You see, at the third position,
the mean average prediction error of those
positions of the numbers bumping on the walls.
And So as expected,
the losses, like, are correlated to
the downstream performance. Increasing
during training, And I think a key insight
of which we should be careful when training
joint embedding predictive word models is
having this multistep rollout loss, which is
not new, but has been used for decades
in RNN literature, for example, to make
sure that you align
your training objective with what you wanna do
at inference, which is autoregressive rollout.
So you can see on the right that
over time steps when enrolling your predictor,
Your average precision, doesn't
decrease too much if you have
this multistep rollout loss. So it it really helps.
That can apply so that applies to VGA
per two AC, for example. Those
types of papers.
And finally, what we're interested in here
is word models. Action condition word models.
Here, it's in embedding space.
And, you can see that we want to learn an encoder
f data. And a predictor j
phi. Such that we can perform
planning. And by planning, it's mostly
based on rolling out your predictor on
some actions and optimizing over those actions.
So this is illustrated on the bottom figure.
And I think what's key here to understand
is that we learn jointly the encoder and predictor.
This is what allows to have very shallow
architectures trained only on
the on the data that
is at hand. Compared to DWORD
model on VGIP or v j p two, which
are relying on pretrained photo encoders.
Which are much bigger and and
but also allow to perform more
diverse tasks. Right?
So, yeah, to to still connect with the
energy based setup, the left, you have
the planning energy that we minimize at
at the planning time, at evaluation time,
which is the distance between the goal x j
which would be the right
the right square that is circled
in red, which is like the gold
position of the agent a in a two
rooms environment. Right? We wanna make a
ball move to the door between
the two rooms and then to the destination. To
the target position.
So, yeah, when planning in latent space, we want
to minimize the distance in latent
space compared to the,
embedding of this goal state.
We can use various planners to do that.
Which are optimization procedures, like
the crest entropy method that some of you may know,
or the model predictive
path integral method, which are all methods
which optimize a sequence of actions given
a predictive model.
And I wanna give some key insights for people
who would use those these code
base and want to onboard with
training action condition word models and using them for
planning, what you gotta be careful
about I think would say the
most important thing to to to to
to remember is
if you are on an environment where the background
is not the same across sequences,
which is the case here, you see
there are three sequences.
And for those three sequences, the position
of the background, so the wall the
door, in in in green is not
the same. And the classical collapse
mode, which you can face
when training on such sequences,
is that your model would
forget about the moving ball, like the agent,
just focus on encoding the background, which is not
what you want. Right? You wanna focus on what moves.
And and a classical,
like, that that has been identified in previous literature.
As a collapse mode when training go JEPAS. On
sequences that have different background
across, between sequences, but
fixed background in time. So
So to avoid this collapse mode, we have a very
useful lost term
addition to CEG or Vicreg, which is
the IDM here, the inverse dynamics
loss. And you can see that if you remove this
loss term during training, you go from 97
to 1% performance. So you
might wanna use this
inverse dynamics in addition to the the classical regularizers
that we use, like variance covariance. Or
cigarette.
Which are, as we can see here, all contribute
to the overall performance of the
model when doing planning in this
environment. Thank you very much for
your attention. I wanna keep some time for questions.
And I wanna stress that this
code base is still under active development.
We think it's gonna help us
explore, like, we are already exploring,
other regularize regularizers
that would be easier to
use. So that's regularization theory
on the left. Hierarchical word
models is is under development.
We'll keep you posted.
To perform, like, more long horizon planning.
And also, there has been some recent papers
on learning the cost instead of just using
the distance in embedding space as a cost for
planning. That's also into our development.
So feel free to, check out the
code base, open issues, open PRs,
yeah, thanks so much for your questions.
So, if there are no questions,
we'll move on to the next contributor talk. Yeah.
Let's thank Bazile again, and congratulate.
So our next, contributor talk is gonna be
from Fanfang. Who's doing
a postdoc at UC San Diego, where he's going
to tell us about his paper, which titled, self improving
world models via asymmetric
forward inverse consistency.
Sorry for the delay.
Hi, everyone. My name is Fence. It's
a great, great pleasure to present our work.
Self improving world model via forward
reverse asymmetry. This
is a joint work with collaborators from
Stanford, CMU, Google,
and Harvard.
So, recently, we have seen tremendous progress
in order models across many domains such as
games, navigation,
and manipulation.
Well, these war models
when they these model models are accurate, then
they can support a wide range of
downstream application scale including
policy evaluation, policy learning, and
test time scaling. However so
all of these applications, they rely
on one strong assumption,
So the word model has to
correctly predict the futures
given, certain chunk of actions.
But in practice, this is quite challenging.
So recent benchmarks such as Water
RENA showed that, okay, existing water
models often struggle with action following.
So instead of truly incorporating
the given actions, so
these models hallucinate features that
look plausible but actually
in this aligning with the actions.
So in this work, so we ask two
questions. So first, what is,
why is action foreign difficult for a current
world model? And the second,
given the analysis, how
can we improve action following when we
only have a limited budget of interaction data,
especially for robotics?
Yeah. To understand this challenge, let's first look
at the difference and similarities between
world models and policy learning.
So in policy learning, we often
care more about, like, the optimal actions
that can solve a set of tasks.
So as a result, so the distribution of
the actions we need to model is
quite narrow. But in contrast,
for general purpose world model,
we need to we need the predictions to be reliable across
actually, a more broader range of actions.
So this includes not only optimal
actions, but also those, like, sub optimal
ones, exploration actions, random
actions. So
But, actually, this creates a fundamental challenge
because on one hand, you know, world
models can leverage large scale Internet
data to learn a broad knowledge about
the general visual dynamics. But
on the other hand, to make predictions really
controllable by these actions, we
still need action like, action labeled data.
Which is not so many in the real
world. So
in practice, like, collecting this, like,
action labeled robotic data in real world is
very slow, expensive, and even sometimes
can be, risky. So the
key question will become, like, given
a limited batch of data, how
can we really allocate them to improve
the model in the most effective
way? So,
yeah, to understand this,
there are two families of, current approaches.
The first is about you can use unpolicy
data collection, where we collect
rollouts given a set of policies.
So this this kind of way,
works pretty well for those, like, specific
policies. But it might sacrifice
the generality when you
generality of the resulting word model you
learned.
Yeah. And another way to turn
that is just focusing on information
maximization. So here, the idea
is very clear. So you just explicitly,
search for the action that are difficult for a word
model. Like, you're changing the word
model every time. So the key is to
basically estimate the future, like,
the prediction error under a calculated
action before collecting the ground truth
evaluation. Transitions. And we can
think of this process like a process of verification.
And, of course, if the verification
signals are reliable, and then
it could effectively guide the exploration,
However, in practice, sometimes this
can also result in a robustness
challenge. In
So here are the why this will
happen. So imagine we already
have collected some action label data,
from a distribution. We call this distribution
as distribution the
p of action. And
I would like to expand the exploration
range towards a more broader vision distribute video
distribution where we collect it in the
such as, like, collect it from the Internet, from YouTube,
and we call this distribution as
PO of video. Yeah.
So often, when we have
the carried data, like, move further
away from the original distribution, the p
action, So And then
the word model produced larger prediction
errors, like here,
So the prediction error from the source
distribution to the more,
like, broader range of distribution is getting larger
and larger from left to right.
But about the verification
signals? So
the verification the verification
signals will only be accurate
when it is really, close to the source
distribution. And as you can see,
so from left to the right, so
the the verifier will become
less reliable. But
this is problematic because the under
explored regions like the region on the right hand
side, so they are actually where
the new data is most needed.
But here, the verifier is least
reliable. So this gives us a paradox.
We need to solve.
So let's move to the second question. So
given that analysis, given that paradox,
how can we really improve action following with
limited data limited budget of data?
So Yeah. So
to solve this challenge, in
this work, we introduced word
action verifier, or in short, just WAV.
So it can sit three different components.
So first is about semi supervised setting.
Where you have two source of data. So
one is collected from action labeled robotic
interaction, which is very expensive.
And another is from action free action
free Internet data, so which is,
contain many different sources, and very
easy to get. And we use this
two set of data to create a semi supervised
learning setting, so that we can learn from
learn one from another. And then
the second component is about decompose
verification. So instead of just
just look at the arrow of the
word model prediction, we can actually
make the problem become easier by decomposing
into sub problems, So one
is related to state verifier, and another is
related to action verifier. To make
the problem become much more tractable.
And then given these two components, so
we can use, video
model to generate goals so
that to achieve kind of, like, goal oriented
consistency. So I will
introduce each component later.
So before we move into the first
part, so we first talk about, some assumptions
in this framework. So suppose we
have two data domains. So one is from the source
data, so which includes small
scale like robotics, robotics data with
action labels. And another is
from Target, so which is large scale Internet
and video data without action labels.
And we assume that label one is a
subset of unlabeled one, which is a natural
assumption. So instead
of leading exact prediction errors
before execution, so our goal is
to rank which cater interactions are more
likely to be more informative
during the process.
So the key idea is to
like previously we mentioned, we can decompose
the action condition prediction into
two conditions. So first is about
good prediction that
should be plausible of, should be a plausible
future state. And the second
condition is it should also be
reachable under a given action.
So if you look at the equation here
so this is generally a action
condition word model, And then it can be
expressed at this form, So
the green one is associated with state verify
oh, state plus
ability, and the the green one
sorry. The blue one is state plausibility,
and the green one is about action reachability.
And then we can create asymmetric between
this to really improve the word model.
Yeah. So specifically for
the for
the state of possibility, so we use action
free video to train a diverse
diverse, like, sub goal generator.
So which gives us a plausible future state.
So even when the action labels are missing,
So this can be generated as a off the
shelf video model, or you can use even, like, video
prior collected from the
like, massive datasets.
And the second factor is, like we
mentioned, is action reachability.
So instead of predicting the whole future, so
we use a sparse inverse dynamics model
to infer which action should should
cause transition. So
based on only on the action relevant features
instead of the full feature space, to
make it, really identifiable and make
it more easy.
So putting two things together,
so we also have the goal oriented consistency.
So, basically, we we first sample
a possible sample sample by a video
model or by a video prior. And
then we infer the action to Richard.
So after that, we ask the word model
to roll out the features given that inferred
action. So if
the predict if the predictive outcome
doesn't really match the sub goal,
this means that a useful region
the world model need to improve. So, basically,
you need to collect more data in that specific
region because that is under explored.
So that's why we use this verification
loss between the generated sub goal
and the ground truth outcome
and do this abstraction. To guide
the world model to explore the most difficult
subcategories from diverse plausible candidates.
Yeah. The we also have
theoretical analysis to support why this should
work. So, in short,
so sparse inverse verification can be easier
than dense forward generation when the state
is high dimensional. The environment
is highly stochastic, and
the the amount of action labeled data is really limited.
Yeah. So in terms of experiments, so we first
had this in mini grid with controllable settings.
So compared with uncertainty and also
learning based learning progress
based lines, So our our model
can give, error estimates that align
better with the ground truth So here, we
calculate the later calculate the error
and evaluate the correlation.
And we can also reduce
word model prediction error and improve
the action following capabilities.
And we also evaluated on
six robotic tasks from Robot Mimic
and Many School. These
simulated environments So we also
compare with, uncertainty based and the learning
progress based approaches.
And what is important here is that besides
predicting error we did on mini grids, well, we
also evaluate whether the neural network model can
improve downstream and policy learning
So here, we evaluate the reward function
learned by the given word
model given a diffusion policy. So
the goal is to and also
we consider several settings where
out of generics out of distribution data
are available. So, basically,
the goal is to test, like, not only
we can produce better word model, but also
leads to better control and a more robust generalization.
So here are the word model prediction error.
So you can see, our
model consist consistently give, like,
lower word model prediction error than baselines.
And And it is even
stronger in the low data low data
region. Where, like, choosing the
right interaction does matter here.
And then which is also important that,
we can achieve similar
prediction quality with roughly, like, half of the number
of samples used for other baselines.
And we also evaluate, in those,
distribution distribution generalizations
settings. Where the source domain is just
is compared, like, with targets improving
like, appearance shapes, object changes,
and also policy different from
different policy optimizations. Where
you have a diverse set of data. So for for example,
here, so robot cannot
really make the task.
And these data are especially hard
because the world model must generalize
in this under explored regions like we mentioned
before. So So,
yeah, so as the this kind of
OD setting becomes much more complex,
and we actually can perform even
better So as you can see, so
for prediction error, we can achieve the
best And similarly for reward function,
so here, we use, learned reward
a deficient policy
and then this also
means that so our learning
of the word model can translate into
better policy learning.
And when the complexity of out
of distribution all the
task difficulty is increasing, and
our model can achieve, like,
increasing in better performance.
Than the baseline. So
So And, also,
the video predictions, these are the open
loop video predictions. So
you can see, like, baseline can actually
also produce possible looking
features but often fair to follow the
physical dynamics and actions.
But our model gives predictions, like,
closer to the ground truth with better
physical and object consistency.
Yeah. To sum up, so
here we identify the key challenging in word
model active learning. Is
that the verification methods open
like, become much less
reliable in those under explored regions.
So our method tried to address this
by actually reframing word model
improvement as a verification problem
like using possible future states from video
data, action reachability from,
inverse dynamics model, and
this kind of using, forward
inverse cycle to guide the model
which data to collect next and which data to fine
tune on. And more broadly,
we believe this self
improving world model needs not only stronger
generation approaches, but also need
stronger verification signals where the
image, like, image future are physically,
physically possible and action consistent.
So if you're interested, feel free to check
out our paper and also our code.
Thank you, and happy to take any questions.
Just in the interest of staying on schedule,
I think if we have any questions first,
speaker fund, then, free to get
in touch with them after the talk. We're gonna move
on to our final contributor
talk and also our final talk for the day of the
workshop. Which is from
Chineng Wang, who's a PhD student at Northwestern
University gonna talk to us about
his paper, titled, Inact
Evaluating Embodied Cognition with World
Modeling of Ego centric Interactions.
Hello, everyone. My name is Shinawang.
I'm a second year physics student from Northwestern
University. I'm very happy to share with
you about our latest work in ACT,
on behalf of our team.
So this work is a joint effort of NorthWestern
University Stanford University, and UCLA,
And, credits also goes to Wanlong
Huang, Manindi. Behavior team, and
all the other coauthors.
So is
is naturally grounded through interaction with
a physical world. For
example, a two year old baby,
learns more knowledge through through interaction
with their environment. When baby touches
a table and feels that it
is hard and smooth, it connect this feeling with
the object. In cognitive science
literature, this is called embodied cognition.
So there are three important components
to this concept. The
first is understanding the spatial
relationships, of the scene
second is understanding the physical dynamics
of the environment. And third is having
the abstraction ability to alert
knowledge.
So So we all know that MLMs
nowadays are very good at you know, code generation,
mathematical reasoning. Or even
chatting. However, the current training
paradigm is quite large. Largely,
it disembedded. So they do not
train with a body or learns more
knowledge through physical interaction.
So in that case, we are curious
to what extent existing models possess this
kind of embodied cognition. Under the current
training paradigm. So to evaluate this,
we need to find a proxy task. We found
we found that word modeling is a perfect
feat. War modeling task inherently
requires an agent you know, to understand the
three capabilities I just mentioned,
such as, you know, understanding word dynamics,
understanding the meaning or purpose of an action,
and understanding its own embodiment
capability. So in in our
case, we chose the partial observable
Markov decision process framework
as our proxy. Using simulator
scene graph as a state space RGB
images as observation space, and action and
state action state differences as the
action space. So
here's a concrete trajectory. So
starting from state zero, robot
executes a sequence of action
such as playing a plate inside the fridge
not grasping the plate, closing
the fridge, it transition into the sink
a new state while generating a new egocentric observation.
So the key idea here is that each action is
structured interpretable change in the
scene graph. So simulator
provides cheap and scalable data pipeline.
So given simulated manipulation trajectories,
from behavior, we extract key frames
at the moment when the scene graph
changes. So
for example, currently,
the drill is
not on top of table
And now the robot is grasping the screwdriver
with its left gripper.
And robot is lifting up the screwdriver
and
Put the drill back into the toolbox.
So now that we have this collected
or segmented key frames, we
now can curate the our
questions this forward
and inverse model word modeling set settings.
So for for the forward setting,
that is given the current state image and the
set of shuffle next state images.
The model must reorder them into the correct temporal
sequence. So for example,
we we we shuffle the some
images we just sampled, and then
we provide the current current state and
correct sequence of actions. And ask
the alarms to predict the correct order of
the state images.
So the inverse task flips
the problem So
the image we show are so images
are shown in correct order, but action labels are shuffled.
So we ask the model to assign the right action
to each transition.
So for example, we shuffle
the actions and ask the elements
to predict the correct action order conditioning on
the given state
image sequence.
So we study interaction lens or the
transactional lens ranging from three to 10
steps evaluating around 30
open weight and proprietary MLMs.
Here's a few key takeaways.
So, first, now I'm MLM
performed drop sharply as the number of
steps increases. From around 70%
of accuracy task task accuracy
down to near zero at 10 steps.
So second model performed much better on the
inverse setting than the forward setting.
Suggest it's easier to match actions to
observe change than predict the future
states.
So third find
out we also hired some human annotators
to, evaluate our benchmark
on the data, and we find that human
no matter what kind of, step
number is, human also achieved
always achieved this near ceiling performance.
Across all of that cons.
And we find out the gap between humans and
humans is substantial and grew wider and longer
rises. Revealing this fundamental limitation
in current models, about the reasoning.
Especially in this egot centric interaction
settings. So
we also discover some interesting bias.
So MLMs shows this kind of, since, you
know, most, data that that
is used to to pretrain the models
are human data, So we
also reveal that amounts amounts
show this anthropocentric
biases. Such as right handedness,
which is which means that they perform
better when the robot arm appear on the
when you're using its right arm to perform the
task.
Additionally, we find that
models are very sensitive to like
real parameters So such
as if if the wheels are deviating
from the human to feel human like
field of view, such as using a
like, larger aperture or fish
eye lens. It will quickly hurt the
performance. This also
applies to the camera height.
So both high and low viewpoints degrade
accuracy. Compared to natural
human eye level perspective. So
we also developed this fine grained
taxonomy to review the why this model
feel. At in in the
setting. So let's say
given the ground truth action like the
ground truth state like the plate
plate is inside the fridge.
So ARROP now falls could fall in five
categories. So here
for the entity substitution,
the model could replace the wrong object
with the correct one. So
predicate substitution
with a wrong relationship is used
Polarity inversion where the direction
of the change is
changed. Hallucination where the predicted
action involves entities or relationships.
That is not presented in a scene.
And finally, the omission. Where the
model simply fails fails to produce
an answer.
And we analyze the distribution and
l m error types and we find that
we use g p d five as an example.
So here we we can see that g p d five tends
to, make hallucination or omission
mistakes Meaning that it either predicts
a state that does not exist or fails to
recognize one that should exist.
So So in summary,
ENACT, reviews a significant gap
between MMR's and human embodied
cognition. Particularly for longer
horizon reasoning. MOMs also exhibits
the signs of human bias.
So benchmark code and data
are publicly available And please feel
free to check out our project page and GitHub
repo and scan the QR code here.
And thank you, and
happy to take any questions later.
If you want. Yeah.
Okay. So the last thing before
we finish up is just some closing remarks.
We at the organizing team just wanted to
say, that we're so happy to see how much
of tremendous contribution that was made by the World
Wildlife Research community as a whole.
As a whole.
And it was extremely interesting to see so many
different perspectives in this exciting
research area that's, having so
much well, yeah.
It's going through a really just generally exciting
period at the moment.
So in particular, we'd like to thank our keynote speakers
and panelists. Who
are just Yeah. Terrific researchers.
And it was a real privilege
to hear what they have to say and such an interesting
topic. So Jorgen Schmidt Huber,
Sergei Levin, Jiaozhong Woo,
Mito Asran, Hao Su, Shane Gu,
Sarah Paraiso,
Fred Sala, Kevin Murphy, and
Michael Robat. Let's, thank them
again.
Then there's also the organizing committee. And
the advisory board who have worked really hard over the last few
months just to put together such an amazing
program of from all over the world.
This is my supervisor, Meng Yui Yang.
Zheidong Feng, Nicholas Hansen,
and, Francesco Fachio.
Thank them.
Then there's also the support team, my fellow PhD
students at Bristol University.
Oh, Imperial. Zhu, Jacob
Chok, Hungnam Ma, and Yue Shi.
And then last but not least,
we're very gracious for our sponsors, our industry
for the event, Snorkel AI and Tencent.
Yeah. So thank you very much everyone again,
and we hope to see you all again soon.